<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Belgiaes troubles, and triumphs VVherein are truly and historically related all the most famous occurrences, which haue happened betweene the Spaniards, and Hollanders in these last foure yeares warres of the Netherlands, with other accidents, which haue had relation vnto them, as the battels of Fleurie, and Statloo, the losse of Gulicke and Breda, the sieges of Sluce and Bergen, the conquest of St. Saluador in Brasilia, and the taking of Gosse by Charles Lambert, &amp;c. Written by William Crosse ...</title>
            <author>Crosse, William, b. 1589 or 90.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19644</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6072</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109106</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844756</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844756</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9596</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19644)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9596)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 954:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Belgiaes troubles, and triumphs VVherein are truly and historically related all the most famous occurrences, which haue happened betweene the Spaniards, and Hollanders in these last foure yeares warres of the Netherlands, with other accidents, which haue had relation vnto them, as the battels of Fleurie, and Statloo, the losse of Gulicke and Breda, the sieges of Sluce and Bergen, the conquest of St. Saluador in Brasilia, and the taking of Gosse by Charles Lambert, &amp;c. Written by William Crosse ...</title>
                  <author>Crosse, William, b. 1589 or 90.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 74, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Augustine Mathevves, and Iohn Norton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>The second book has separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>With a final leaf of commendatory verse by John Dowle.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Poetry.</term>
               <term>Belgium --  History --  1555-1648 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9596:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9596:1"/>
            <p>BELGIAES TROVBLES, AND TRIVMPHS. WHEREIN ARE TRVLY and Hiſtorically related all the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Occurrences, which haue happened <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the</hi> Spaniards, <hi>and</hi> Hollanders <hi>in theſe last</hi> foure yeares Warres of the Netherlands, with other <hi>Accidents, which haue had relation vnto them, as the</hi> Battels of <hi>Fleurie,</hi> and <hi>Statloo,</hi> the loſſe of <hi>Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke</hi> and <hi>Breda,</hi> the Sieges of <hi>Sluce</hi> and <hi>Bergen,</hi> the Conqueſt of St. <hi>Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor</hi> in <hi>Braſilia,</hi> and the taking of <hi>Goffe</hi> by <hi>Charles Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Written by WILLIAM CROSSE, maſter of Arts of St. <hi>Mary</hi> Hall in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and ſometimes Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine vnto Colonell <hi>Ogle</hi> in the <hi>Netherlands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by AVGVSTINE MATHEVVES, and IOHN NORTON, 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9596:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9596:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE, AND TRVELY noble Lords, the Earle of ESSEX, and my Lord MOVNTIOY, <hi>William Croſſe</hi> wiſheth the increaſe of Temporal, and the fulneſſe of Spirituall happineſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost Illuſtrious Lords, amongst all the Liſt of our Time-VVor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, I could find none to whom I might conſecrate this Firſt part of <hi>Belgiaes Troubles and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs,</hi> ſooner then to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured ſelues, as being the Sonnes of two ſo Noble, and high-deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Fathers, the Mirrours of theſe latter Ages; whoſe Examples concurring with the inbred vertue of your owne Diſpoſitions, inuite you to the Patronage of Arts, to the Profeſsion and Exerciſe of Armes: the former you haue manifested by your Munificence; the latter, by the free aduenture of your owne Perſons: as you my Lord of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> at your firſt aſcent into the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> for your Ingagements in the Seruice of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> your and laſt attending with much Conſtancy and Valour, in the troubleſome Leaguers of <hi>Meede,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:9596:3"/> 
               <hi>Roſendale.</hi> And you my Lord <hi>Montioy,</hi> for your worth and Nobleneſſe, exemplified at the Siege of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen op Zoom,</hi> for the reſcuing of <hi>Monſieur Breou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees</hi> Bodie from the <hi>Spaniards</hi> at <hi>Meede</hi> Leaguer neere <hi>Breda,</hi> and for the continuall perſeuerance in your Noble Reſolutions, and heroycall Indeauours: The Authour doubts that malicious Criticiſme may haunt and ghoſt this impartiall Poeme, which glorifies our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, according to their condigne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, a thing omitted by the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French</hi> VVri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, who giue ynough vnto themſelues, but vnto vs too little attributes of Honour. For theſe cauſes he ſeeks to ſhelter this Fraught vnder the Lee of your Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which if hee obtaines, by meanes of your Noble Graunts, hee ſhall for euer reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The deuoted Seruant of your Lordſhips</hi> William Croſſe</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="book">
                  <pb facs="tcp:9596:3"/>
                  <head>BELGIA'S TROVBLES AND TRIVMPHS. </head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>The first Booke.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <argument>
                     <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                     <p>IN this part continued from the beginning of the yeare of our Lord God, <hi>1621,</hi> vnto the Aſcenſion of our Sauiour, in the yeare <hi>1622,</hi> are contained the expiration of the laſt Truce, with a Propoſition of a new Treatie; which the States reiect, becauſe the <hi>Spaniards</hi> would not acknowledge them for free States in this Treatie. The preparations of both ſides for warre. The meeting of our Troups at <hi>Skenckeſconce.</hi> Their cruell March from thence to Dornicke. The terrible Sicknes which raigned in our Army. The imbattailing of our Foot-Companies on the North ſide of Dornicke. Graue <hi>Henricks</hi> fortunate eſcape from foure Cornets of the enemies Horſe. The burning of his Lodgings and Stables by a caſuall fire. <hi>Spino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laes</hi> oppoſition againſt the Prince of <hi>Oranges</hi> forces. <hi>Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbercks</hi> taking of Gulicke, and <hi>Inigoes</hi> repulſe at Sluce: together with the burning of <hi>50</hi> Dorps in little Brabant by the States Armie, and the taking of the Gouernour of Angola Priſoner by the Fluſhingers.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the calmes of ſweet-contenting Peace</l>
                  <l>Well paſſed were, and that luxurious eaſe</l>
                  <l>Had griped on thoſe Armes, which fighting were,</l>
                  <l>Imbru'd with blood, with danger, death &amp; feare;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bellona</hi> ſtorming with a fatall rage,</l>
                  <l>Out of th'Infernall Cells calls forth a Page,</l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:9596:4"/>
                  <l>Fell Diſcord hight, with whom ſhee thus doth treat:</l>
                  <l>Doe not thy trembling vaines deare Diſcord ſweat</l>
                  <l>Whole ſtormes of wrath? for that neglected warre</l>
                  <l>Creſt-fallen mournes in peace; and that, that barre</l>
                  <l>Of milk-ſop Treaties ſtoppes our raging Armes,</l>
                  <l>Stain'd with the blood of <hi>Belgiaes</hi> former harmes.</l>
                  <l>Behold that ſwelling State; obſerue and looke,</l>
                  <l>How proudly ſhee hauing the chaines off ſhooke</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Caſtiles</hi> thraldome, liues in pleaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g reſt,</l>
                  <l>And roaues from Holland to the fartheſt Weſt,</l>
                  <l>Spreading her tayle vnto<note place="margin">The Weſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies were firſt diſcouered by <hi>Columbus.</hi>
                     </note> that Indian Maine,</l>
                  <l>Found by <hi>Columbus</hi> for Gold-thirſting Spaine.</l>
                  <l>I long to drinke her blood, and to intombe</l>
                  <l>Her goared carkeiſe in my gaping wombe:</l>
                  <l>Rather let heapes of men, let millions die,</l>
                  <l>Then my blood-thirſtie ſoule ſhould want ſupply.</l>
                  <l>Think'ſt thou that Turnholts field where<note place="margin">Theſe three places in the Netherlands were famous for thoſe fights which haue been made in them.</note> thouſands fell,</l>
                  <l>Of ſlaughtred bodies could my longing quell?</l>
                  <l>Or famous Oſtend, which for three yeares ſpace</l>
                  <l>Maintain'd that ſiege, which did the world amaze?</l>
                  <l>Or that ſame blood, which fertiliz'd the ſand,</l>
                  <l>That Mountaine like doth riſe on Newports Strand?</l>
                  <l>Theſe were but drops vnto my dropſie ſoule,</l>
                  <l>Which drinking ſtill doth thirſt; goe fill my bowle</l>
                  <l>Brim full with vengeance, which I meane to powre</l>
                  <l>In ſtormes of blood on <hi>Belgiaes</hi> fruitfull ſhore.</l>
                  <l>There's liquor yet within the ſacred vaines</l>
                  <l>Of great heroicke Spirits, that remaines</l>
                  <l>An obiect for my luſt: there are the<note place="margin">My Lord of <hi>Oxford,</hi> Sir <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race,</hi> and Sir <hi>Edward Vere.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Veares,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Three thunder-bolts of warre, whoſe courage dares</l>
                  <l>T'affront whole Squadrons; there is <hi>Cecill</hi> braue,</l>
                  <l>Theſe would I haue to make the fielde their graue.</l>
                  <l>With theſe time-honour'd<note place="margin">The <hi>Ogles</hi> of Lincolneſhire came from the <hi>Ogles</hi> of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland.</note> 
                     <hi>Ogle</hi> let mee place,</l>
                  <l>A Branch ſprung from Northumbrian <hi>Ogles</hi> race,</l>
                  <l>And valiant <hi>Mountioy,</hi> who to <hi>Blunts</hi> great houſe</l>
                  <l>Freſh glory giues; with theſe then ioyne and rouſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Saintleger, Conway, Burrowes,</hi> and the reſt,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe daring valour fitly may conteſt</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9596:4"/>
                  <l>With Romes old Minions; let their whetted Armes</l>
                  <l>Vpon thy ſummons take on freſh Alarmes.</l>
                  <l>And ſince for richer ſtreames of Princes blood,</l>
                  <l>My ſoule doth long to drinke a crimſon flood,<note place="margin">A Horſlee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> or Bloodſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hirudo</hi>-like, faine would I ſucke the vaines</l>
                  <l>Of great <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> which with their mouing ſtraines</l>
                  <l>Giue life vnto the members of that State,</l>
                  <l>Who with their power the Spaniſh pride doe mate.</l>
                  <l>With this fierce Diſcord moou'd, breaks all the barres</l>
                  <l>Of ſleeping Peace, and ſets diſcordant Iarres,</l>
                  <l>Doubtfull ſuſpitions, iealous lurking feares,</l>
                  <l>Freſh boyling in the breaſts of<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Belgia</hi> ſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fies the N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therlands.</note> 
                     <hi>Belgiaes</hi> Peeres.</l>
                  <l>Nor doth ſhee reſt, but to increaſe the fire,</l>
                  <l>Addes fuell to the flames, ioynes pride with ire,</l>
                  <l>Malice with falſe, but yet pretended wrong,</l>
                  <l>With which ſhee makes the Spaniard to prolong</l>
                  <l>Treaties in ſhew; but yet inflames his ſprite,</l>
                  <l>With force to tame th'vnited Cantons might.</l>
                  <l>The cauſe grew thus, there were of colder blood,</l>
                  <l>Who aym'd at Peace, and at the publike good,</l>
                  <l>Vnwilling that the Chriſtians ciuill Iarres,</l>
                  <l>Should breed domeſticke, and inteſtine warres.</l>
                  <l>Theſe men perſwade a parle, both condiſcend,</l>
                  <l>But diſſonant, remou'd from concords end.</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Philip</hi> deeming that the twelue yeares truce,<note place="margin">The King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Spaine.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Did but the luſtre of his Right abuſe,</l>
                  <l>And that the webbe of <hi>Barneuelts</hi> deſigne,</l>
                  <l>Prou'd Fortunes ſcorne, an vnſprung fruitleſſe Mine:</l>
                  <l>Beſides, being vrg'don by the firme Decree</l>
                  <l>Of his owne Counſell, and the Roman See,</l>
                  <l>And by their Engines taught, th' <hi>Ignatian</hi> crue,<note place="margin">The Ieſui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>That 'twere more honour <hi>Belgia</hi> to ſubdue,</l>
                  <l>Then for to conquer from the Midland-Sea</l>
                  <l>The vaſt extent of Sun-burnt <hi>Barbarie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Vnto thoſe ſandie Deſerts, that<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Leuant</hi> ſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fies Eaſt, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny place E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward.</note> Leuant,</l>
                  <l>Whereas in troupes th'Alarbian Rouers haunt:</l>
                  <l>Then to diſplay their Enſignes on the Towers</l>
                  <l>Of proud <hi>Bizantiums</hi> Sultanized bowers</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:9596:5"/>
                  <l>Or ſubiugate all Greciaes fruitfull land,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Hemus</hi> top to <hi>Hellespontus</hi> Strand.</l>
                  <l>Theſe cauſes ioyned with his Titles prize,</l>
                  <l>Faire ſeeming to ſome raſh beholders eyes,</l>
                  <l>By which hee claimes from <hi>Burgundies</hi> deſcent,</l>
                  <l>Power abſolute, and ſupereminent,</l>
                  <l>Like fatall motiues, did ſtill animate,</l>
                  <l>The Spaniſh King, and <hi>Auſtriaes</hi> Potentate,</l>
                  <l>To ſeeke out warres in peace, and Treaties faine,</l>
                  <l>By which they might time and occaſion gaine.</l>
                  <l>True Spaniſh wiles, of <hi>Gondamars</hi> owne draught,</l>
                  <l>By which they haue French, Dutch, and Engliſh caught,</l>
                  <l>And wonne ſo many Scepters, ſo much ground,</l>
                  <l>By their forg'd Parlees, falſe deluding ſound,</l>
                  <l>Preuailing more with the <hi>Volponees</hi> caſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Read <hi>Guich. lib.</hi> 26.</note>Then e're they could winne with the Lyons face.</l>
                  <l>Thus did they wreſt forth of the Frenchmens hands,</l>
                  <l>Siciliaes creſted Hilles, Calabriaes lands,</l>
                  <l>Sweet Piemounts Vallies, and thoſe fruitfull plaines,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Theſin</hi> waters with his Chriſtall vaines;</l>
                  <l>All thoſe faire Regions, which extended lye</l>
                  <l>From th' Alpine Mountaines vnto Tuſcanie.</l>
                  <l>With this old Spaniſh tricke they gaue the foyle</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fredericke</hi> the Prince Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine.</note>To Princely <hi>Fredericke,</hi> and with Beamelands ſpoyle</l>
                  <l>Loading their hungry Troupes, inforc't the Rhine</l>
                  <l>To quit his Tribute to the Palatine.</l>
                  <l>With the faire ſemblance of this glorious gloze,</l>
                  <l>They thought th' intangled Hollanders to cloſe,</l>
                  <l>A Nation learn'd in their Caſtillian drifts,</l>
                  <l>Their policies and Spaniolized ſhifts.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">The Archduke <hi>Albertus.</hi>
                     </note>For <hi>Albert</hi> doth propound Conditions faire,</l>
                  <l>But Iudgement-weigh'd politique verball ayre.</l>
                  <l>Hee'l ſeeme t' acknowledge theſe free men for free,</l>
                  <l>Yet manumiz'd by force to libertie.</l>
                  <l>Hee'l treat with them, as treating with free States,</l>
                  <l>They being not ſo, but this diſanimates</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Nullum ſimile eſt idem.</note>Them from all parle; for nothing likes the ſame,</l>
                  <l>Quoth they, and then ſhall we leaue freedomes name.</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:9596:5"/>
                  <l>Shall wee bee ſeeming ſlaues, and loſe that good,</l>
                  <l>Which wee haue purchaſt with our deareſt blood?</l>
                  <l>Shall wee to Spaniſh thraldome chaine our necks,</l>
                  <l>And baſely ſtoope to thoſe Imperiall becks</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Auſtriaes</hi> Houſe? whoſe vaſte ambitions fire,</l>
                  <l>To th' Europeian Empire doth aſpire,</l>
                  <l>And ſeekes to giue the Law to all thoſe Nations,</l>
                  <l>Which in this Climate hold their habitations.</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould not wee be dealt with as the <hi>Swiſſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Three free Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, and ſo acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe fredome ſure and vndependant is?</l>
                  <l>Or as the rugged <hi>Griſon,</hi> who doth plough</l>
                  <l>The cragged Valtolinaes bending browe?</l>
                  <l>Or that <hi>Venetian</hi> Sea-commanding State,</l>
                  <l>To ballance <hi>Auſtriaes</hi> power ordain'd by Fate?</l>
                  <l>Wee are as free as <hi>Griſon, Swiſſe,</hi> or Shee,</l>
                  <l>That o're the Seas claimes wedded Soueraigntie.</l>
                  <l>Our Forces are as potent on both Maines</l>
                  <l>In Shipping, men, and th' vnexhauſted vaines</l>
                  <l>Of our<note place="margin">Exchequers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Treaſuries.</note> Cantoors, the Sinewes by which warre</l>
                  <l>Supported is, and Kingdomes ſtrengthned are.</l>
                  <l>Our Carbins mounted on their Frieſeland Steeds</l>
                  <l>Are matchleſſe preſt at all aſſayes and needes.</l>
                  <l>Our Foot are braue well diſciplin'd to fight,</l>
                  <l>Equall to th' ancient Greekiſh <hi>Phalangite.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our Magazins are filled with Munition,</l>
                  <l>Stuffed with ſtore, and ſwelling with prouiſion,</l>
                  <l>Beſides our Ships now Dockt within the Ports,</l>
                  <l>Our moouing Bulwarkes, and our flying Forts,</l>
                  <l>Like to the Perſian Fleet obſcure the skie,</l>
                  <l>Shadow the earth, and with their wings can flye,</l>
                  <l>Forth from thoſe Seas, that beat on Amſterdam,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the fartheſt Straights of <hi>Magellan,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To the Moluccoes, Ginee, and that ſhore,</l>
                  <l>From whence Caſtile tranſports her golden Oare,</l>
                  <l>With which ſhee buyes falſe hearts, and doth vnlocke</l>
                  <l>The ſtrongeſt gates without <hi>Bellonaes</hi> ſhocke.</l>
                  <l>Then like to braue <hi>Tuiſcoes</hi> ſonnes let's arme,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tuiſco</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Duch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And chuſe the leſſe, to ſhun the greater harme.</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:9596:6"/>
                  <l>With this both parties leaue their parling words,</l>
                  <l>Both Arme, and fall to right deciding Swords,</l>
                  <l>By which as by their Peeres they meane to trie</l>
                  <l>Which ſide ſhould haue the lawfull victorie.</l>
                  <l>The Spaniſh Galeouns which vnrigg'd had lyed</l>
                  <l>Euer ſince our farre-fam'd <hi>Eliza</hi> dyed.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe great<note place="margin">Ships of warre</note> Armadaes which for England ſtood</l>
                  <l>In Eightie eight, and like ſome Sea-borne wood,</l>
                  <l>Coaſted from Plimmouth to that narrow Sound,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Neptunes</hi> ſurge from Dunkirke doth rebound;</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Howard, Croſſe,</hi> and <hi>Hawkins</hi> did repell</l>
                  <l>That Weſterne ſtorme, which on our Regions fell,</l>
                  <l>Commanded are to take the curled Maine</l>
                  <l>Of foamy <hi>Neptune,</hi> and to entertaine</l>
                  <l>The Hollanders with their broad-ſided Tyres,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Aetna,</hi> ſpuing forth infernall fires.</l>
                  <l>The<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tertio</hi> in Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſignifies a Regiment.</note> 
                     <hi>Tertioes</hi> old, which Gariſon'd did lye</l>
                  <l>In Naples, Sicill, and in Lumbardie,</l>
                  <l>In the Maiorcan, and Sardinian Ile,</l>
                  <l>Once<note place="margin">Read <hi>Liuie, lib.</hi> 23 about the end.</note> famous for the Carthaginians foyle,</l>
                  <l>Receiue ſtrict orders, and moſt ſtrong commands</l>
                  <l>To paſſe th' Alpes, and towards the Netherlands,</l>
                  <l>With running Marches for to bend their courſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Albertus</hi> Armie there to reinforce.</l>
                  <l>Nor doe the Dutch like Lethargiſts ſecure,</l>
                  <l>Sleepe being prickt, but doe their minds inure</l>
                  <l>To all preuentions, policies, and care,</l>
                  <l>By which they may <hi>Caſtiles</hi> attempts out-dare,</l>
                  <l>And giue the checke to all their proud deſignes,</l>
                  <l>Their fearefull plots, and dang'rous new-ſprung Mines;</l>
                  <l>And ſince vpon defence that people ſtands,</l>
                  <l>Which dwells within the watry Netherlands,</l>
                  <l>Committees choſen are to view the Ports,</l>
                  <l>Their Sconces, Townes, and all their frontier Forts,</l>
                  <l>From Rayſe, and Embricke, and thoſe Eaſterne Verges,</l>
                  <l>Where Rhine doth meet with Iſſells billowing ſurges,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Rammekins, Fluſhing, and Briels head,</l>
                  <l>Seated vpon the Weſterne Oceans bed.</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:9596:6"/>
                  <l>The like they doe to Groningue on the North,</l>
                  <l>And all that bending Frontier, which runnes forth,</l>
                  <l>From cold Eaſt-Friſeland, and<note place="margin">The riuer of <hi>Ems</hi> diuideth Eaſt and Weſt Friſeland.</note> Ems frozen face,</l>
                  <l>Southwards to Waal, and Brabant bordring Maſe.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe full-mouthd Canons, which at Newports field</l>
                  <l>Inforc't th' <hi>Albertine</hi> Regiments to yeeld,</l>
                  <l>And with their<note place="margin">Caſes of Tin filled full of Musket bullets</note> Tarlin ſhot diſcharged ſure,</l>
                  <l>Made the Sand-hills a common ſepulture</l>
                  <l>For thoſe hote bloods, which neuer could agree,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſimpathize in congruous qualitie,</l>
                  <l>New mounted are, and ready for to make</l>
                  <l>Vpon their foes a ſecond Flanders Slate.</l>
                  <l>Their high-proofe Armours for their temper equall</l>
                  <l>To<note place="margin">At Millan and Siras are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding good Armors made,</note> Millans making, and to Siras mettall,</l>
                  <l>Their Corſlets ſtrong, in which their armed Pike</l>
                  <l>Immured ſtands prepar'd to ſaue or ſtrike,</l>
                  <l>Swords, Carbins, Muskets, Inſtruments of fire</l>
                  <l>New furbiſht are, to wreake their thundring ire.</l>
                  <l>Their winged Ships, the glory of their Armes,</l>
                  <l>From whom th' Iberians haue receiu'd ſuch harmes,</l>
                  <l>Famous for their Sea-fights made neere the Kay</l>
                  <l>Of rich Saint <hi>Lukars,</hi> and t' <hi>Hanannaes</hi> Bay,</l>
                  <l>New calked are within their ouzie Dockes,</l>
                  <l>T' incounter <hi>Caſtiles,</hi> and fierce <hi>Neptunes</hi> ſhockes.</l>
                  <l>And ſince that thoſe Laconian walls of bones,</l>
                  <l>More ſtronger are then Rampierd Earth or Stones.</l>
                  <l>And ſince that all defenſiue meanes are fraile,</l>
                  <l>If Maniples of armed Souldiers faile,</l>
                  <l>They ſend for reinforcements and ſupplies</l>
                  <l>From England, Scotland, France, and their Allies,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Swiſſerland.</note>T' Heluetian Cantons, and thoſe German Peeres,</l>
                  <l>Whom <hi>Auſtriaes</hi> greatneſſe fills with iealous feares.</l>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Belgia</hi> being arm'd, and thus prepar'd,</l>
                  <l>For ſelfe-defence againſt Inuaſions made;</l>
                  <l>Orders were giuen to their trayned Bands</l>
                  <l>Of Horſe and Foot their choyceſt<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vetera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>e</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies an old Souldier.</note> 
                     <hi>Veteranes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When as that dreadfull ſtorme began to fall,</l>
                  <l>Which menaced the vnited <hi>Belgians</hi> thrall,</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:9596:7"/>
                  <l>To take the Maſe, and ſwallow ſwifter Rhine,</l>
                  <l>In their Samroſes forc't with horſe and winde</l>
                  <l>Againſt the current of that purling flood,</l>
                  <l>Which neere<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Briſach,</hi> a ſmal town in <hi>Swiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerland.</hi>
                     </note> Briſach leaues Danowes neighbourhood,</l>
                  <l>And runnes along from out his Mountaine ſource,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Ocean with a Weſterne courſe.</l>
                  <l>The Randeuow's appointed neere the Bankes</l>
                  <l>Of Wahal, beating on the Southerne flankes</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">The <hi>Rhine.</hi>
                     </note>Of <hi>Skenks</hi>-Sconce, where this prince of German torrents</l>
                  <l>Diuides it ſelfe into two ſeu'rall currents,</l>
                  <l>And angry roaring runnes into the Sea,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe the Land parts Wahals company;</l>
                  <l>Which to reuenge, when Winter once doth frowne,</l>
                  <l>He yearely doth the<note place="margin">A part of <hi>Guelderland,</hi> lying neere the <hi>Rhine.</hi>
                     </note> Betowes Surface drowne.</l>
                  <l>The time when as our braue Battalions met,</l>
                  <l>Was when the Sunne in <hi>Virgoes</hi> lap doth ſet,</l>
                  <l>When mortalls <hi>Ceres</hi> inne to make them bread,</l>
                  <l>And preſſe downe <hi>Bacchus</hi> fruits with cluſters redd;</l>
                  <l>Twas Auguſts moneth, ere the <hi>Naſſauians</hi> marcht</l>
                  <l>To Grauenweert, or Spaniards counter, marcht</l>
                  <l>From Flanders, and from<note place="margin">The <hi>Wall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>un</hi> Countries.</note> Walchland, where are ſpunne</l>
                  <l>The fineſt Cambricks by the Belgian Nunne.</l>
                  <l>Then after three dayes in that Station ſpent,</l>
                  <l>Wherein we lookt for Friſelands Regiment,</l>
                  <l>And th' Amber-treſſed Friſons being come</l>
                  <l>From Franekaa; and from their Northren home,</l>
                  <l>Through Iſſels Channell to that necke of land,</l>
                  <l>Where all our Ships, and all our Troupes did ſtand.</l>
                  <l>Our Drummes doe ſound a March, our Enſignes flie,</l>
                  <l>And with their Serean colours beate the skie,</l>
                  <l>Our men diſmarch, and paſſe Rhines ſlimie ridge</l>
                  <l>Vpon their<note place="margin">Made of Punts.</note> Punted-new-compacted Bridge.</l>
                  <l>Thence leauing Eltam on the left hand file,</l>
                  <l>After the paſſage of a German mile,</l>
                  <l>Wee doubled Embricks Turrets mounted high,</l>
                  <l>Which oppoſite to famous Cleeue doe lie.</l>
                  <l>From thence we came to<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dornicke,</hi> a ſmall village in Cleueland.</note> Dornicks Champion fields,</l>
                  <l>Which ſtore of Corne, and Pulſe abundance yeelds,</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:9596:7"/>
                  <l>Where we diſlodg'd Weſt-Cleauelands ſturdie Boores</l>
                  <l>From houſe and home, and fed vpon their ſtores.</l>
                  <l>That day th' Heauens powr'd cataracts of ſhowers</l>
                  <l>Forth of <hi>Aquarius</hi> Tempeſt-breeding bowers</l>
                  <l>Vpon thoſe Sands, whereon with tyred pace,</l>
                  <l>Our bodies did the ſtorme it ſelfe out-face.</l>
                  <l>So that not onely out<note place="margin">Freſh water Souldiers.</note> 
                     <hi>Beſonioes</hi> faint</l>
                  <l>With this diſguſt, which did our Squadrons taint</l>
                  <l>With following Feuers, Agues, and Catarrhes,</l>
                  <l>With Leaguer Murraines, forced from the Iarres</l>
                  <l>Of angrie Nature; but th' old <hi>Phalangites,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The beſt Muskettiers, and the braueſt Pikes,</l>
                  <l>Whom neuer ſhowers of bullets could affright</l>
                  <l>At Newport, Oſtend, nor ar Turnholts fight;</l>
                  <l>Amazed with this Tempeſt, make a ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Vpon the Surface of the tyring ſand,</l>
                  <l>And leane vpon their bended knees and armes,</l>
                  <l>Diſconſolate for ſelfes, and others harmes.</l>
                  <l>So that if euer <hi>Conons</hi> warlike hoaſt,</l>
                  <l>Purſued at large from th' Aquileian coaſt,<note place="margin">Concerning theſe two long Retreats, read Sir <hi>Walter Rauleighs</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the World.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>By <hi>Theodoſius</hi> Reuenge breathing rage,</l>
                  <l>Who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> floods of blood, nor ſlaughtred heaps could ſwage,</l>
                  <l>Being led by that bold <hi>Brittans</hi> ſure command,</l>
                  <l>Through rich Italiaes tract, and Galliaes Land,</l>
                  <l>To that ſweet ſhoare, which oppoſite doth lie</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Cliffes of <hi>Charles</hi> bleſt <hi>Brittanie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had euer day, wherein the ſtorming skie</l>
                  <l>Diſtill'd his anger on mortalitie.</l>
                  <l>If euer that time-honour'd <hi>Bhalanx</hi> had</l>
                  <l>A day tempeſtuous, ominous and ſad,</l>
                  <l>When they retyr'd aboue two thouſand miles,</l>
                  <l>Maugre the Perſians force-ſupported wiles;</l>
                  <l>From that high land which lies beyond the Verges</l>
                  <l>Of pearld Euphrates Arrow-ſwifter ſurges,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the bankes of Euxin, and that flood</l>
                  <l>Of Phaſis, where free Trapizond then ſtood.</l>
                  <l>If e're (I ſay) they ſuffered Heauens frowne,</l>
                  <l>In cataracts of ſtormie ſhowres powr'd downe,</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:9596:8"/>
                  <l>Our men did then indure as much or more,</l>
                  <l>Then euer Greeke or Britton did before.</l>
                  <l>In that dayes March, wherein their eyes might ſee</l>
                  <l>Griefe ſtriue with paines, paines with varietie,</l>
                  <l>Contending which ſhould haue the leading place,</l>
                  <l>Amongſt our bands that hardly now could pace.</l>
                  <l>For there you might behold the Curacier,</l>
                  <l>Who neuer did the flaming Piſtoll feare.</l>
                  <l>Heere you might view the<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Carbins,</hi> taken figuratiuely for them who carry this weapon. A ſtand.</note> Carbins belching fire,</l>
                  <l>The Pike-men ſtout, and Musketiers to tyre;</l>
                  <l>And like ſome Ship ſtockt in the Lybian ſands,</l>
                  <l>To halt it oft, and often to make ſtands.</l>
                  <l>There you might marke the French and Lukar walls,</l>
                  <l>Two warlike Nations preſt at <hi>Mars</hi> his calls,</l>
                  <l>Who better can indure the ſcorching heat,</l>
                  <l>Then dropping ſhowres, and ſenſe-benumming wet,</l>
                  <l>From the Vangard vnto the Reare caſt backe,</l>
                  <l>Their marching paſe, and<note place="margin">A Galliard found out by <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling the order of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching.</note> 
                     <hi>Pirrhicke</hi>-Galliard ſlacke.</l>
                  <l>Heere you might ſee a Voluntier lacke breath,</l>
                  <l>Whom Honour had inforc't to ſeeke out Death</l>
                  <l>In forraine Climates, whoſe ſad deſtin'd lot</l>
                  <l>The Aire did cauſe, yet ſeem'd to weepe thereat.</l>
                  <l>Nor was the ſowre tempeſtuous frowning night</l>
                  <l>More cheerefull to vs, then this firſt dayes light:</l>
                  <l>But being Twinnes, and brethren of one birth,</l>
                  <l>They both alike inflict the groaning earth,</l>
                  <l>Both light and darkneſſe ioyne their ſeuer'd hands,</l>
                  <l>To powre reuenge vpon our weakened bands.</l>
                  <l>For after that our Squadrons quartered were,</l>
                  <l>Thirſt was their drinke, ſharpe hunger was their fare</l>
                  <l>Their Helmets were the pillowes for their heads,</l>
                  <l>Their gliſtring Corſlets were their Iron beds,</l>
                  <l>In which like <hi>Baſans</hi> King, they ſleepe, and dreame</l>
                  <l>Of nothing elſe but their afflictions Theame.</l>
                  <l>Your ſhaggie ſtraw more precious was then downe</l>
                  <l>Then ſofteſt plumes; for which men robbe the ground,</l>
                  <l>Deſpoyle the Floods, and ſearch the Chriſtall skie</l>
                  <l>For theſe light Emblems of their vanitie,</l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:9596:8"/>
                  <l>That ſo they might lodge in that various ſhell,</l>
                  <l>Wherein the plants and featherd fowles did dwell.</l>
                  <l>Our Gallants then wiſht for their Miſtreſſe Chamber,</l>
                  <l>Perfum'd with vnctious Nard, with Muske and Amber,</l>
                  <l>Who croſſe the Germane Sea to drinke a<note place="margin">Fanne is foure Cannes.</note> Fanne,</l>
                  <l>And learne the Poſtures of a Leaguer Canne,</l>
                  <l>Who for their Honors march vpon their Steed,</l>
                  <l>When brauer men vpon their feet muſt ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>Clad all in Roabes of that new Scarlet Die,</l>
                  <l>Which to the Tyrian is but mockery.</l>
                  <l>But when we muſt ſome wall or Rampier open,</l>
                  <l>Or ſome ſtrong Port by Petards to bee broken,</l>
                  <l>When fights are to bee made, and men releeu'd,</l>
                  <l>In Trench or Sconce, their courage then is ſteeu'd:</l>
                  <l>Their pendant Valour falls into their heele,</l>
                  <l>Before they doe the Sword or bullet feele.</l>
                  <l>Yet theſe mock-Souldier Gallants hauing ſpent</l>
                  <l>Three or foure months with feare and languiſhment</l>
                  <l>In ſome old Captaines Hutt, who knowes to drill</l>
                  <l>Them of their Coyne, and his owne purſe to fill,</l>
                  <l>Returne to <hi>London,</hi> where in euery ſtreet</l>
                  <l>You may theſe plum'd and Caſſockt Souldats meet;</l>
                  <l>Where, aske what newes they'l tell you they haue ſeene</l>
                  <l>The bloody Leaguer, and the deaths of men:</l>
                  <l>They'l ſweare th'aue been at <hi>Bergen,</hi> and that fight,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Mansfield</hi> made<note place="margin">At <hi>Flewrie,</hi> neere to <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murs.</hi>
                     </note> in fenced <hi>Namurs</hi> ſight,</l>
                  <l>And talke of nought but Orders, Poſtures, Motions,</l>
                  <l>Whereof themſelues haue ſcarce the verball notions.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thraſonian</hi> braues compar'd with Souldiers braue,</l>
                  <l>Who make the field their houſe, their bed their graue,</l>
                  <l>And ſcorne to ſpeake of what themſelues haue done,</l>
                  <l>That ſo they may the Braggarts Stigma ſhunne.</l>
                  <l>Nor were theſe glorious puffes the men alone,</l>
                  <l>Which curſ'd the warres, and wiſht themſelues at home,</l>
                  <l>But other <hi>Capuan</hi> Souldiers, Carpet Knights,</l>
                  <l>Who with their Crownes had bought out merits rights,</l>
                  <l>And in the time of that long twelue yeares peace,</l>
                  <l>VVherein like Iades they liu'd in pomperd eaſe.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9596:9"/>
                  <l>Procured had ſome Office of command,</l>
                  <l>By bribing gifts, and iuggling vnder hand:</l>
                  <l>Theſe men whom meanes, not merit had erected,</l>
                  <l>With this diſaſtrous night were much deiected,</l>
                  <l>And their creſt-fallen courage did ſinke downe</l>
                  <l>Lower then th'Earth on which they lodg'd vpon,</l>
                  <l>Curſing the day, wherein their fathers crownes</l>
                  <l>Had made them vaſſalls to <hi>Bellonaes</hi> frownes.</l>
                  <l>But after that<note place="margin">The Moone.</note> the ſiluer horned Planet,</l>
                  <l>Which hid her head like ſome declining Comet</l>
                  <l>In that fell Tempeſt, had vnlooſd her Carre</l>
                  <l>In Latmos Mount, and that the Sunne from farre,</l>
                  <l>Mounting his Steeds in our Horizons poynt,</l>
                  <l>Inlightned had the darkſome firmament.</l>
                  <l>Our men like to the Solar opening Flower,</l>
                  <l>Freſh courage tooke, freſh comfort in that howre,</l>
                  <l>Wherein bright <hi>Phoebus</hi> with his cheerefull face,</l>
                  <l>Began to runne the Zodiacks Weſterne race.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aduenue,</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.</note>Our Guards were then vpon th' <hi>Aduenues</hi> ſet,</l>
                  <l>Fires kindled were, and forrage ſtore was ſet,</l>
                  <l>Prouiſions by Direction were ſent downe</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Skenks</hi> ſtrong Sconce, &amp; Embricks rampard towne,</l>
                  <l>Beſides the ſhips wherein the baggage went,</l>
                  <l>Were to the durtie Dornicks quarters ſent,</l>
                  <l>Wherein the Souldiers did receiue ſupplie</l>
                  <l>In this firſt ingreſſe to neceſsitie,</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe ſad wants, which Cuſtome knowne became</l>
                  <l>Another Nature, to their Vertues fame.</l>
                  <l>Heere our Battalions did ſome three months lie,</l>
                  <l>Preſt with the terrours of Mortalitie,</l>
                  <l>With Lice, with Hunger, and vnceſſant Raine,</l>
                  <l>Which filld the Rhine, with all the bordring plaine.</l>
                  <l>Our men were ſhopt vp in thoſe Barnes and Cells,</l>
                  <l>Wherein the Milke-ſop Cleuiaes Peaſant dwels,</l>
                  <l>Where like ſome fleecie fold with hurdles pent,</l>
                  <l>We paſt our time in pining languiſhment:</l>
                  <l>And in that<note place="margin">Signifies a ſtanding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ampe.</note> Leaguer was our patience knowne,</l>
                  <l>More then our actiue Valour e're was ſhowne:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9596:9"/>
                  <l>For hauing ſpent the reliques of that ſtore,</l>
                  <l>Which was prouided by th' vplandiſh Boore;</l>
                  <l>And after that rich Embricks fertill plaine</l>
                  <l>Diſmanteld was of trees, of corne and graine</l>
                  <l>By our Forragiers, who did better know</l>
                  <l>To cut, then plant; to reape, then till or ſowe.</l>
                  <l>Our Conuoyes then did for their forrage poaſt</l>
                  <l>Beyond the Riuer to that Southerne coaſt,</l>
                  <l>Where ſtately Cleeue vpon a Mountaine ſtands,</l>
                  <l>Which all the Frontier thereabouts commands.</l>
                  <l>We marcht neere Goffe and Zantams new built walls</l>
                  <l>For ſtraw and fewell at our Drums ſad calls,</l>
                  <l>Where the proud<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Spinola,</hi> a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noueſe by diſcent.</note> 
                     <hi>Genoan</hi> Marqueſſe then did lie</l>
                  <l>With his beſt Horſe, and choyce Infanterie,</l>
                  <l>To ſtop our paſſage, and th'attempts to breake</l>
                  <l>Of the <hi>Naſſauian</hi> Squadrons, now growing weake</l>
                  <l>With a diſeaſe, which in their Troups did raigne,</l>
                  <l>With franticke fits, with ſenſe-confounding paine:</l>
                  <l>Which fierce contagion did not onely touch</l>
                  <l>The French, or Scots, our Engliſh, or the Dutch,</l>
                  <l>But ſpread it ſelfe, like to ſome broken ball</l>
                  <l>Of ſulphrous wild-fire through our Quarters all,</l>
                  <l>From Eltam where Cleeues Votaries did wunne,</l>
                  <l>Southwards to Greets, and towards the riſing Sunne,</l>
                  <l>Where Raiſe being iealous of the bordring foe,</l>
                  <l>Her horned Workes, and Rampiers new doth ſhow.</l>
                  <l>Neuer that <hi>Simois</hi>-neere intrenched troupe</l>
                  <l>With peſtilence did more infected droupe,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Phoebus</hi> moou'd for<note place="margin">Concerning this plague, read <hi>Homer</hi> the firſt of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Iliads.</hi>
                     </note> fayre <hi>Chriſcis</hi> Rape,</l>
                  <l>Whom <hi>Atreus</hi> ſonne to's luſt did captiuate,</l>
                  <l>Darted his wrath vpon thoſe Grecian Bands,</l>
                  <l>Which would not yeeld to <hi>Chriſeus</hi> faire demands.</l>
                  <l>Neuer the Plague wrought a more direfull bane</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Salems</hi> Citie, when <hi>Veſpaſian</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Read</hi> Ioſeph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Bello Iud lib.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>With his <hi>Pretorian</hi> Cohorts did ſurround</l>
                  <l>Mount Sions walls, and that more ſacred ground</l>
                  <l>Whereon the Temple ſtood, proud <hi>Aſiaes</hi> wonder,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſpired creſt <hi>Oſiris</hi> vaile did ſunder,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9596:10"/>
                  <l>Then our weake Troupes were with this murraine preſt,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe furie did our Cohorts all infeſt,</l>
                  <l>And like ſome ſad <hi>Mephitis</hi> pierſt their vaines,</l>
                  <l>Procuring death with fierce tormenting paines.</l>
                  <l>Some Regiments which could two thouſand ſhew,</l>
                  <l>When wee firſt marcht vnto the Randeuow,</l>
                  <l>Could ſcarce fiue hundred of that number tell,</l>
                  <l>Excepting thoſe, who by this ſickneſſe fell.</l>
                  <l>Some Companies whoſe Squadrons were compleat</l>
                  <l>Full ſixeſcore ſtrong, when we at <hi>Skencks</hi>-Sconce met,</l>
                  <l>Could not a Tertian of that Liſt produce,</l>
                  <l>Fit for the Seruice, and Imployments vſe;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe that did liue could ſcarce intombe the dead,</l>
                  <l>Nor giue due rights to them that periſhed:</l>
                  <l>Thoſe that were ſound could not attendance giue</l>
                  <l>Vnto the feeble, nor the ſicke relieue.</l>
                  <l>In eu'ry place was nought but deſolation,</l>
                  <l>Skie-piercing cries, and fearefull lamentation:</l>
                  <l>Vollies of Shot a fatall Dirge did ſing,</l>
                  <l>Which ecchoing from th'adiacent <hi>Rhine</hi> did ring,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe <hi>Golgoth'd</hi> banks became one vaulted tombe,</l>
                  <l>Incloſing heapes within their ſpacious wombe,</l>
                  <l>Amongſt which<note place="margin">Signifies the ſlaughter, or mortalitie of men.</note> Carnage grim-fac'd death did ſtalke,</l>
                  <l>And on theſe Trophees did triumphing walke,</l>
                  <l>Wiſhing her hand with one all-killing blow,</l>
                  <l>Might all our Legions to th'Infernall throw.</l>
                  <l>Some for this cauſe did blame the blameleſſe Lawes</l>
                  <l>Of potent Nature, and condemn'd that cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Which by ſome iealous<note place="margin">A law amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the <hi>Athenians,</hi> by which they baniſhed great men.</note> 
                     <hi>O eſtrociſme</hi> might baniſh</l>
                  <l>Theſe Spirits from this world, and cauſe to vaniſh,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Seats of valour, that ſtupendious frame</l>
                  <l>Vnto thoſe Elements from whence they came.</l>
                  <l>Others againe did curſe falſe <hi>Galens</hi> Art,</l>
                  <l>And our Campeſtrian Leaches, who doe part</l>
                  <l>The quinteſſentiall Spirits of trees and plants,</l>
                  <l>Of Stones and Mettalls: and ſupply the wants</l>
                  <l>Of feeble Nature with their Fomentations,</l>
                  <l>With their Elixars, Iulips, and Purgations,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9596:10"/>
                  <l>Who giue their patients ſome <hi>Aeſonian</hi> pill,</l>
                  <l>As they pretend, by which their bags they fill</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Perues</hi> Gold, and with <hi>Arabiaes</hi> wealth,</l>
                  <l>Themſelues being impotent, deuoyd of health,</l>
                  <l>Troubled with Coughs, with Agues, and Catarrhs,</l>
                  <l>With Dropſies, Gowts, with thoſe inteſtine Iarres,</l>
                  <l>Which from diſtemperd humours doe proceed,</l>
                  <l>When they deficient are, or doe exceed.</l>
                  <l>But all in vaine; for 'twas the firme decree</l>
                  <l>Of that all-changing, vnchang'd Deitie,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe purpoſe through defects doth neuer alter,</l>
                  <l>All potent, becauſe impotent to falter,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe power is ſuch, that in a twinckling eye,</l>
                  <l>It can conſume large-ſpread mortalitie,</l>
                  <l>Not being tyed to Fortune, Fate, or Chance,</l>
                  <l>Gods onely knowne through mans meere ignorance;</l>
                  <l>'Twas hee that ſtrucke with his all-powerfull hand,</l>
                  <l>Which checks the roaring Sea, which rules the land,</l>
                  <l>Our ſuffring Troupes, whoſe Valour oft had ſcapt</l>
                  <l>The Canons ſhot, and murdring Muskets fate.</l>
                  <l>'Twas hee that made thoſe fields a common graue</l>
                  <l>For th'Engliſh, Dutch, and all thoſe Nations braue,</l>
                  <l>Who ſcorning peace, themſelues to warres did wedde,</l>
                  <l>And chuſing thoſe deceaſ'd in Honours bedde.</l>
                  <l>But ere that this contagion was full ſpread,</l>
                  <l>Or that his force had got a<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hidraes</hi> head.</note> Lerncan head,</l>
                  <l>About Saint <hi>Michaels</hi> day, th' Archangels feaſt,</l>
                  <l>Fame bruited had, that from the bordring Eaſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Liguriaes</hi> glory, and proud <hi>Genoaes</hi> pride,</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Spinola,</hi> for's Fortune Deifide</l>
                  <l>By the Saint-making Conclaue, was falne downe</l>
                  <l>From Weezels walls, to Goffe and Zantoms Towne,</l>
                  <l>And that his Troupes with more then Spaniſh haſt,</l>
                  <l>Vpon their Punts the pearled Rhine had paſt,</l>
                  <l>Threatning to powre forth their long cankred ire,</l>
                  <l>In dreadfull ſtormes of Bullets, Sword, and fire.</l>
                  <l>This rumour firſt was grounded on the voyce</l>
                  <l>Of Fames<note place="margin">Are thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo called, who ſpeak out of their bellies.</note> 
                     <hi>Engaſtromiſts,</hi> the vulgar noyſe,</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:9596:11"/>
                  <l>Who trumpet out for loud reſounding Fame,</l>
                  <l>Things not done for things done, and make the ſame</l>
                  <l>Which but appearing was, apparant true</l>
                  <l>To the deceiued worlds deceiuing view:</l>
                  <l>Who taking it, this Marchandiſe doth ſell</l>
                  <l>To thoſe Retaylors, whoſe broad eares doe dwell</l>
                  <l>In Tauernes, Barbers ſhops, and publike Marts,</l>
                  <l>Where lyes are ſold to hollow Spungeous hearts,</l>
                  <l>For Beere, for Wine, and that curſt Indian weed,</l>
                  <l>Whereon theſe puffes of noueltie ſtill feed.</l>
                  <l>But this report high mounted on the wing,</l>
                  <l>In our Dornician Tents did forthwith ring,</l>
                  <l>And came to <hi>Naſſawes</hi> honourable Count,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Counſell doth Spaines policies ſurmount;</l>
                  <l>Who like to <hi>Argus</hi> with his hundred eyes,</l>
                  <l>Attends the deſignes of their <hi>Mercuries,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of their <hi>Proteian</hi> Enginees of State,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſubtiltie doth ſeeke to maſter Fate:</l>
                  <l>Hee ſtraight growes iealous, that this great Brauado</l>
                  <l>Might turne at length to ſome nights Camiſado;</l>
                  <l>Or that the daring foes might courage take,</l>
                  <l>And our Diſaſters might them animate</l>
                  <l>T'incounter in Campania with our Bands,</l>
                  <l>Which now began to languiſh of all hands.</l>
                  <l>For theſe reſpects hee fortifies at Greets</l>
                  <l>Cloſe to the Riuer, which the<note place="margin">The Curtin is that part of the wall, which runs in length from one An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle to another.</note> Curtin beats;</l>
                  <l>Then oppoſite to Embricke builds a Fort</l>
                  <l>Commanding all the South and Weſterne Port:</l>
                  <l>Beſides, he Reinforcements ſends to Raiſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſets ſtrong Guards vpon the neighb'ring wayes,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe wide Meanders giue a paſſage free</l>
                  <l>Vnto th'incurſions of that enemy,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe malice hath long ſought by <hi>Romes</hi> aduice,</l>
                  <l>Ouer theſe Cantons free to Monarchiſe.</l>
                  <l>Nor ſo the Prince doth reſt, but takes th'Alarme,</l>
                  <l>Giues order to the Squadrons all to arme,</l>
                  <l>And drawes them into Battaile on that plaine,</l>
                  <l>Which from the Campe reſpects<note place="margin">This field lay to the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the Leaguer.</note> 
                     <hi>Bootee waine.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:9596:11"/>
                  <l>This <hi>Phalanx</hi> firſt did ſtand vpon a line</l>
                  <l>Whoſe depth was one aboue the perfit nine.</l>
                  <l>His ſteeled front which fac'd the riſing Sun</l>
                  <l>From pointe to point three thouſand yards did run,</l>
                  <l>Wherein each troupe, with all the diffrent nations</l>
                  <l>Imbattail'd ſtoode, and ranged in their ſtations.</l>
                  <l>The Vanguard our victorious Engliſh had.</l>
                  <l>With their red croſſed Enſignes, <hi>Cecill</hi> ladde</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Regiments, whom Gulicke once did ſee,</l>
                  <l>Chiefe in commande are th'Engliſh Infantrie.</l>
                  <l>When England, France and Holland did combine</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Brandenburge,</hi> and did their forces ioyne</l>
                  <l>T'impeach the Spaniarde, and to breake that plot</l>
                  <l>By which he Cleeue with <hi>Iuliers</hi> after got.</l>
                  <l>Neere him with equall diſtance<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Edward Veare</hi> Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Colonell to Sir <hi>Horati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Veare</hi> doth ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Who in <hi>Horatioes</hi> abſence did commaunde</l>
                  <l>Thoſe hardie Cohorts, which had often tried</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Iberians</hi> force, and all their Braues defied.</l>
                  <l>Next <hi>Ogle</hi> rangd his bands, that Martiall Knight,</l>
                  <l>Famous for Oſtends ſiege, and Newports fight,</l>
                  <l>Where he preuaild both with his ſworde and parling,</l>
                  <l>And ſhewd himſelfe both <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Hermes</hi> darling.</l>
                  <l>Cloſe vnto theſe vpon the left hand flanke</l>
                  <l>Great<note place="margin">My Lord <hi>Liſle.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Leiſters</hi> ſon marcht in the formoſt ranke,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe courage longd to reuenge <hi>Sidneyes</hi> blood</l>
                  <l>Spilt neere to <hi>Zutphen</hi> for our <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nions</hi> good.</l>
                  <l>The battell by that nation was tooke vp.<note place="margin">The Scots and French had the middle battell.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVho Neſſes ſtreames, and <hi>Fyndornes</hi> water ſup;</l>
                  <l>VVith theſe were ioynd their antient faſt Alies</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe natiue ſoile twixt <hi>Some</hi> and <hi>Garroun</hi> lies.</l>
                  <l>The French commaunded were by <hi>Chatillion.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By <hi>Hotteriue</hi> and <hi>Curtimeers</hi> braue baron.</l>
                  <l>The Scots were <hi>Brogues</hi> and <hi>Hinderſons</hi> ſole chardge,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe honour death at Bergen did inlarge,</l>
                  <l>VVhere he being ſhot gaue vp his glorious ſoule</l>
                  <l>Into his hands, who Armies doth controule.</l>
                  <l>The reare conſiſted<note place="margin">The Suitzers and the Dutch had the Reare.</note> of thoſe warlike bands,</l>
                  <l>VVhich dwell in Bearnes, and Baſils Cantond lands,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9596:12"/>
                  <l>Of the long treſſed Priſons, and the Dutch</l>
                  <l>VVhom Countries loue and libertie doth touch</l>
                  <l>VVith an inflamed Patriots burning zeale,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe thoughts tende all vnto the publike weale.</l>
                  <l>Beſides this liſt there were of Voluntiers</l>
                  <l>Braue numbers, and of brauer martiall Peeres,</l>
                  <l>Who for religions cauſe, for honours ſake</l>
                  <l>Had left their deereſt deares, to vndertake,</l>
                  <l>The wargods ſeruice: here <hi>Eſſex</hi> his Counte</l>
                  <l>Appeares as Leader in the formoſt frounte:</l>
                  <l>With him marcht he, that Holla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ds title beares</l>
                  <l>Amongſt the liſte of our illuſtrious Peeres,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Hopton</hi> too, whom let me not forget,</l>
                  <l>Borne in the fields of flowerie Sumerſet)</l>
                  <l>My friend and fellow both in Armes and Arts:</l>
                  <l>With the ſweete tune of which harmonious parts,</l>
                  <l>Thou doſt inforce my ſelfe, my muſe, my loue</l>
                  <l>T'admire their worths inſpired from aboue.</l>
                  <l>Thee vaſt <hi>Herciniaes</hi> woods, and <hi>Iſters</hi> bedde</l>
                  <l>Swift Albis current, and the Neckars heade,</l>
                  <l>Know and reſound their Panegiricke layes.</l>
                  <l>Which blazon forth thy fame deſeruing praiſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> the ſcourge of that Monaſticke frie,</l>
                  <l>Here likewiſe marcht with our Infantery,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mountgomrie, Chatillon,</hi> and diuerſe more,</l>
                  <l>From Almaine, France and cold<note place="margin">Scotland</note> Albaniaes ſhoare,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe boiling bloods did long to trie their might</l>
                  <l>Againſt the Marques in plaine open fight.</l>
                  <l>But long they might, for that<note place="margin">Marques <hi>Spinola.</hi>
                     </note> Ligurian Foxe,</l>
                  <l>Meant not to trie <hi>Bellonaes</hi> bloody knocks,</l>
                  <l>Nor to decide with dinte of trenchaunt blade,</l>
                  <l>The titles right, which Spaines grand Monarch made</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Read the hiſtory of the Netherlands pag. 119.</note>Vnto theſe Lands, o're which as <hi>Charles</hi> heire</l>
                  <l>Neere Nauncy ſlaine he claimes to domineere.</l>
                  <l>For though ſome numbers of the Spaniſh hoaſt,</l>
                  <l>Had paſt the Riuer from the farther coaſt</l>
                  <l>T'infeſt our men with inroades and Alarmes,</l>
                  <l>Reſolued ſtill t'affroant all hoſtile harmes;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9596:12"/>
                  <l>Yet ſtill the Marques with his ſtanding Campe</l>
                  <l>Neere vnto Zantum did himſelfe in camp,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Parties oft with our forragiers meete,</l>
                  <l>Which ſometimes beaten were, and ſometimes beate.</l>
                  <l>Amongſt the reſt <hi>Graue Henricke</hi> paſſing Greets</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Brunſwicks</hi> Duke, and his own Guidon meets</l>
                  <l>With foure braue<note place="margin">The colours which horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men beare.</note> Cornets of <hi>Albertus</hi> ſide,</l>
                  <l>Whom our men ſaw of them being vndeſcried.</l>
                  <l>For that ſame morne the wind blowing South and weſt,</l>
                  <l>Sent forth a vapr'ous fogge, and friendlie miſt</l>
                  <l>From th' Aeolian cloſets, which obſcurd the skie</l>
                  <l>So that things neere you could not well deſcry:</l>
                  <l>Which either vnſeene to the viſion were,</l>
                  <l>Or els their ſhapes ſelfe bigger did appeare,</l>
                  <l>The vapour darkening that tranſparent light</l>
                  <l>Whereby the Species conuoyed is to ſight.</l>
                  <l>Beſides the couert of a riſing ground</l>
                  <l>Did ſo the proſpect of theſe Troupers bounde,</l>
                  <l>That till the Prince was from their danger free,</l>
                  <l>They did not once his gliſtring Cornet ſee.</l>
                  <l>Which had they ſeene, not all fat Hollands ſtore</l>
                  <l>Growne rich with Perues wealth and Indiaes oare,</l>
                  <l>Not Ginees gold, nor all thoſe precious graines</l>
                  <l>Which Orenoque laues from Guianaes vaines</l>
                  <l>Could haue redeemd his life, nor ſet him free</l>
                  <l>From certaine death, or ſure Captiuitie.</l>
                  <l>Their odds was great, yet <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> cryes to charge,</l>
                  <l>And bids our Piſtols and Carbins diſchardge</l>
                  <l>Their murdring ſhot againſt the<note place="margin">Dutch horſe men.</note> Reiſters frount</l>
                  <l>Which foure to one our numbers did ſurmount.</l>
                  <l>But the <hi>Naſſauian Graue</hi> aduiſing flight</l>
                  <l>To be far ſafer then vnequall fight,</l>
                  <l>Strait giues the checke to<note place="margin">The Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> is alſo Biſhop of <hi>Halberſtat.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Halberſtats</hi> deſire</l>
                  <l>And makes his armed Curaciers retire:</l>
                  <l>Since no diſhonour tis our backs to ſhow</l>
                  <l>Where oppoſition needes muſt ouerthrow.</l>
                  <l>But in this ſpace ſome<note place="margin">Thoſe who conducted the Conuoy.</note> Conuoyers of our ſide,</l>
                  <l>VVho ſtragling neere the Counts ingagement ſpied,</l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:9596:13"/>
                  <l>Ran pricking on the ſpurre, and voic'd it out</l>
                  <l>In the <hi>Mauritian</hi> quarters round about.</l>
                  <l>That either he and <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> both were ſlaine,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe that both were priſoners made to Spaine.</l>
                  <l>This rumour poſting ſwifter then the winde,</l>
                  <l>VVith winged ſpeede doth pierce the Princes minde,</l>
                  <l>VVho like ſome Paphian conſecrated Doue,</l>
                  <l>VVhich mournes the loſſe or abſence of her loue,</l>
                  <l>Suſpecting this report, lamenting ſhares</l>
                  <l>His brothers chaunce with griefe and feeling cares:</l>
                  <l>VVith whom each Chiefe, each Souldier doth partake</l>
                  <l>And their ſelfe-griefes the Generals do make,</l>
                  <l>As when ſome dang'rous Rheume begotten Ache,</l>
                  <l>The royall ſeate of reaſon doth attach</l>
                  <l>That part being troubled, where the life doth reſt</l>
                  <l>The members all inferiour are oppreſt.</l>
                  <l>His ſteeled<note place="margin">A Legion is here taken for a Regiment: a ſquadron is a third part of a companie.</note> Legions weepe, his<note place="margin">A Legion is here taken for a Regiment: a ſquadron is a third part of a companie.</note> ſquadrons mourne</l>
                  <l>Their hearts, though danger proofe, for griefe do yearne,</l>
                  <l>VVhom neither feares nor terrours could ſurpriſe</l>
                  <l>The dreadfull bugs of ſtaggring cowardiſe,</l>
                  <l>Theſe looſe their mirth, and that ſoule gladding light</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe cheerefull rayes do clarifie the ſprite:</l>
                  <l>But yet not ſo they giue the raines to griefe,</l>
                  <l>That in this while their labour ſlackes releefe;</l>
                  <l>For forth they ſend their Curriers all in poaſt,</l>
                  <l>To ſearch the Champions Rhine diuided coaſt</l>
                  <l>Mounted vpon their well breathd Courſers backs</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe Pegaſean ſwiftneſſe ſcorneth trackes.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Cornets braue, whoſe garriſons did lie</l>
                  <l>Next to the frountiers of their Enemie,</l>
                  <l>And therefore beſt acquainted with their fights,</l>
                  <l>VVith all their<note place="margin">Stratagem is a feare of warre.</note> ſtratagems, and martiall ſleights,</l>
                  <l>Are forthwith orderd to repaſſe the Rhine,</l>
                  <l>And towards the reſcue to diſmarch in time</l>
                  <l>Their bands of Ordinance, whoſe high proofe frounts,</l>
                  <l>Safeguard the perſons of <hi>Naſſaiaus</hi> Counts,</l>
                  <l>Commaunded are as ſeconds to the horſe</l>
                  <l>VVith their beſt powers their power to reinforce,</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:9596:13"/>
                  <l>But if ingagd to farre, then to retire</l>
                  <l>And like the<note place="margin">The Prrthians when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired did vſe to ſhoote back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, See <hi>Plut in vita Antonii.</hi>
                     </note> Parthians backwards to giue fire.</l>
                  <l>But marke th' euent: he skowring o're the waſte</l>
                  <l>Of that large Champion with preuenting haſte</l>
                  <l>Meetes with thoſe bands, which to the Reſcue came</l>
                  <l>Vpon the ſummons of his dangers fame</l>
                  <l>Cloſe vnto Greets, where all arriuing ſafe,</l>
                  <l>Like ſome wracke ſcpaing mariners they laugh</l>
                  <l>At the remembrance of the danger paſt</l>
                  <l>Which not fore ſtald, was like to proue their laſt.</l>
                  <l>But although fortune fauour'd his retraite,</l>
                  <l>And ſaud the Counte, in that anguſtious ſtraite:</l>
                  <l>Making this action happy by th'euent,</l>
                  <l>Yet no man can approue the preſident,</l>
                  <l>It being againſt the maximes of all warre,</l>
                  <l>For thoſe who chiefetaines in commaunding are,</l>
                  <l>Without ſome waighty cauſe their liues t'expoſe</l>
                  <l>Vnto t'hazard of th' incountring foes.</l>
                  <l>For thus enuirond with a Punicke traine,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Marcellus</hi> Romes great Generall was ſlaine,<note place="margin">Reade <hi>Liuie lib.</hi> 27. about the midſt.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVho retchles went that hillocke to ſuruaye,</l>
                  <l>VVhere ambuſhed the Carthaginian lay.</l>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Bucquoie</hi> famous for our vnions foile,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Pragues</hi> rich conqueſt, and <hi>Bohemias</hi> ſpolie,<note place="margin">See the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall hiſtorie pag. 806.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>After the chance of ſundrie battels paſt,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Gabors</hi> troupes was vanquiſhed at laſt,</l>
                  <l>By thoſe Coſſackes which warrelike Poland breeds</l>
                  <l>And <hi>t'Huſſars</hi> fierce ſtill mounted on their ſteedes,</l>
                  <l>VVhere he being piſtoll'd by the barb'rous foe</l>
                  <l>Reſignd the trophees of Pragues ouerthrow.</l>
                  <l>But though the purling dewe, the vapr'ous Aire</l>
                  <l>Did our ambiguous hopes refreſh, repaire,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Henricke</hi> ſaue: yet the mallignant fire</l>
                  <l>Strait blighs this fruite of ſatisfied deſire.</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe flames being kindled through th' Aires ſecret quills</l>
                  <l>His lodgings ſeazeth, and with terrour fils</l>
                  <l>The quarters next where <hi>Ogles Cohorts</hi> lay,</l>
                  <l>Making the night looke like another day.</l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:9596:14"/>
                  <l>The ſpoyle was great, for when the raging flame</l>
                  <l>Vnto thoſe Inner Roomes with's furie came,</l>
                  <l>Precious nor priceles things were left vnſpard</l>
                  <l>But both alike the common danger ſhard.</l>
                  <l>His Turkie Carpets of vnualued price,</l>
                  <l>Made of the Median ſilkewormes fineſt fleece,</l>
                  <l>His Arras cloaths wrought by the Belgicke Dame</l>
                  <l>The portraitures of true reported fame,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">See the Lowe Country hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pag 456.</note>Where ſtoried out you might ſuruay at large</l>
                  <l>D'Aluaes intrenchment and the Reiſters chardge,</l>
                  <l>Romeroes onſlate, and the foule retreate</l>
                  <l>Made by theſe Almaines after their defeate.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Pag 863.</note>Graue <hi>Williams</hi> life ſaud by a watchfull Curre</l>
                  <l>Th' Alarum taking from the Spaniards ſturre,</l>
                  <l>Who by that Wallouns hand was after ſlaine</l>
                  <l>Whom Rome had made an Aſſaſſine for Spaine.</l>
                  <l>On th'other ſide characterd you might ſee</l>
                  <l>In liuelie formes of wrought Imagerie,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 457. of the ſame hiſtorie.</note>Counte <hi>Egmonds</hi> death, and Hornes vnworthy fate</l>
                  <l>Oſtends long ſiege and Flaunders bloody ſlate,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Barneueltine</hi> falſe <hi>Arminian</hi> plot,</l>
                  <l>Faſt bound with Caſtiles ſubtle Gordian knot.</l>
                  <l>Theſe mooueables with all his curious plate</l>
                  <l>Fitting the greatneſſe of rich <hi>Naſsawes</hi> ſtate,</l>
                  <l>VVherein t'Hollandiſh Ganimed did skinke</l>
                  <l>That Rheniſh <hi>Nectar</hi> which the Gods might drinke:</l>
                  <l>All theſe were ſpoyld by that conſuming fire</l>
                  <l>VVhich on the Prince powrd forth his wreakfull Ire;</l>
                  <l>Nor ſo this burning Element doth reſt</l>
                  <l>But ſpreddes it ſelfe, and farther doth infeſt</l>
                  <l>The ſtables, where his warrelike horſes ſtood</l>
                  <l>Of Europes race, and Africks choiceſt broode.</l>
                  <l>The nimble Gennets comming from the maine</l>
                  <l>Of rich <hi>Granado,</hi> and the ſoutherne Spaine,</l>
                  <l>From<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Alias Guadal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quibir</hi> a great Riuer in South <hi>Spaine.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Baetis</hi> banks, and from that fertill ſhoare</l>
                  <l>Where Siuill doth vnlade that Idold oare,</l>
                  <l>Which from her wealthy mines rich India ſends</l>
                  <l>To Aſiaes bounds, and Europes fartheſt ends.</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:9596:14"/>
                  <l>His Turkie ſteedes bredde neere the ſlimie ſlowes</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Strimon,</hi> which the rugged <hi>Thracian</hi> plowes,</l>
                  <l>Neere <hi>Haemus</hi> mounte, and thoſe high creſted fills;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe melting dewe <hi>Peneius</hi> channell fills;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſtately courſers which Barbaria yeelds</l>
                  <l>From Fezzes paſtures, and <hi>Marocchoes</hi> fields,<note place="margin">A great Riuer in <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barie.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>From parcht <hi>Numidia,</hi> and <hi>Zanhagaes</hi> bed</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>South</hi> from <hi>Atlas</hi> ſhowes his riſing heade</l>
                  <l>Were burned quite, or halfe dead, halfe aliue,</l>
                  <l>Twixt life and death did in this conflict ſtriue</l>
                  <l>Till life being vanquiſht by all conqu'ring death,</l>
                  <l>They loſt at once their torments and their breath,</l>
                  <l>Nor in this time the Spaniſh fire doth reſt,</l>
                  <l>But malice fuell'd ſtriues for intereſt</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Iuliers,</hi> Cleaueland and the Flemiſh coaſt</l>
                  <l>Flaming reuenge with their moſt powerfull hoaſt:</l>
                  <l>For theſe deſiegnes great <hi>Spinola</hi> doth lie</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Cleuiaes</hi> fields, and keepes a ſtill-fixt eye</l>
                  <l>Vpon our Legions, which began to breake</l>
                  <l>Their Summer ſtation, with the peſt-grown weake</l>
                  <l>And weſtward fell vnto that higher land</l>
                  <l>Which lyes twixt <hi>Eltam</hi> and <hi>Rhines</hi> checkerd ſtrande;</l>
                  <l>Twixt <hi>Embricke,</hi> and that <hi>Sconce</hi> which <hi>Skenke</hi> did frame</l>
                  <l>That ſo he might the doubtfull Cleuener tame,</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Geldriaes</hi> fartheſt confines, where the <hi>Waal</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From <hi>Rhines</hi> current to <hi>Maſes</hi> ſtreame doth fall.</l>
                  <l>Another armie by ſtout <hi>Borges</hi> ledde</l>
                  <l>For's ſeruice great and linage honoured,</l>
                  <l>By which he claymes an equall ranke with them</l>
                  <l>Who ſhew <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>udozaes</hi> or <hi>Toledoes</hi> ſtemme,<note place="margin">Two of the greateſt fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies in <hi>Spaine.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And Grandoed are for their <hi>Donnized</hi> birth</l>
                  <l>Liuing like gods vpon the Spaniſh earth,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beleaguers Sluce,</hi> and doth inuade <hi>Cazaunte</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Yperle</hi> ſeuers from the Continent;</l>
                  <l>Where oppoſite to <hi>Zealands</hi> watrie land</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Fluſhings</hi> ſeate this fortreſſe ſtrong doth ſtand:</l>
                  <l>Famous for that far famed nauall fight</l>
                  <l>Which our third <hi>Edward</hi> made in Sluces fight,</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:9596:15"/>
                  <l>When <hi>Phillip</hi> ſent his ſea Commaunding fleete</l>
                  <l>With our well rigged <hi>Argozies</hi> to meete.</l>
                  <l>Who grapling with our force their force withſtood,</l>
                  <l>And bath'd their prowes in French and Flemiſh blood</l>
                  <l>Which iſſuing from the wounds of thouſands ſlaine,</l>
                  <l>With's colour did th' Yperlian current ſtaine.</l>
                  <l>This towne a Cocke pitt was for <hi>Mars</hi> his game</l>
                  <l>Both parties ſtriuing to poſſeſſe the ſame</l>
                  <l>VVith bloody ſucceſſe of continuall warre,</l>
                  <l>VVhere thoſe that conquer'd were, now conqu'rours are.</l>
                  <l>For when theſe States themſelues did firſt vnite</l>
                  <l>To reſiſt <hi>Philips</hi> force and <hi>D'Aluaes</hi> ſpite,</l>
                  <l>And ſought th' oppreſſed Netherlands to free</l>
                  <l>From the hard yoake of Caſtiles tirannie,</l>
                  <l>Ere <hi>Anious</hi> Duke rich Antwerpe did Inuade,</l>
                  <l>Or ſtroue himſelfe Lord <hi>Paramont</hi> to make</l>
                  <l>Of wealthy Brabant, Iſendike and Sluce,</l>
                  <l>Subiected were vnto the Vnions vſe.</l>
                  <l>And ſo remaind till <hi>Parmaes</hi> duke poſſeſt</l>
                  <l>VVith generall power, his warrelike troupes addreſt</l>
                  <l>Vnto the conqueſt of this towne and Ile,</l>
                  <l>Which<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Roger Williams</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Baskeruile,</hi> Reade the Netherlands hiſtorie pag 966.</note> 
                     <hi>Williams</hi> kept and famous <hi>Baskeruile,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who for a ſeaſon brauely did maintaine</l>
                  <l>This place beſiegd, againſt the ſtrength of Spaine,</l>
                  <l>Till by ſurrender they the ſame did yeeld</l>
                  <l>To the Caſtilians maſters o're the fielde.</l>
                  <l>They kept this ſame vntill <hi>Serrano</hi> loſt</l>
                  <l>It to th' <hi>Orangians,</hi> whoſe laborious coſt</l>
                  <l>Regaind the towne, whilſt that beſiegd Oſtend,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 1616.</note>For thrice twelue months her bulwarks did defend.</l>
                  <l>By which aduantage that commanding fort,</l>
                  <l>Which ſo much did all Zealands good import,</l>
                  <l>Recouerd was, which now with might and maine</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Inigo</hi> ſtriues for <hi>Iſabel</hi> to gaine.</l>
                  <l>For this proiect he drawes with ſpeeding poſte</l>
                  <l>From Antwerpe, Gaunte, from Bruges and Aloſt,</l>
                  <l>From all thoſe neighbour garriſons which bide</l>
                  <l>In fruitfull Flaunders, and in Brabants ſide.</l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:9596:15"/>
                  <l>An Armie ſtrong, which reck'ned by the Liſt</l>
                  <l>Of thirteene thouſand Souldiers did conſiſt.</l>
                  <l>Theſe vnder their <hi>Burgonian</hi> Enſignes marcht</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Leaguer, neere to Auguſts laſt;</l>
                  <l>Where being come, like vndermining Moales,</l>
                  <l>Which make their way through th'earths anfractuous holes,</l>
                  <l>They draw their rowling Trenches tow'rds the mouth</l>
                  <l>Of the Towne Harbour, which from Weſt to South</l>
                  <l>Giues a free paſſage to the Cities Key,</l>
                  <l>For Ships of burthen from the German Sea.</l>
                  <l>Theſe with<note place="margin">Crooked turnes.</note> Meanders winding being caſt,</l>
                  <l>And brought within fit diſtance at the laſt;</l>
                  <l>They raiſe their Platformes,<note place="margin">
                        <p>A high worke of earth vpon which they plant Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
                        <p>A wall made of earth.</p>
                     </note> Caualiers and Mounts,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe height the Bulwarks breaſt by farre ſurmounts,</l>
                  <l>Then plant their Cannon, whoſe <hi>Promethean</hi> fire,</l>
                  <l>Vpon the<note place="margin">
                        <p>A high worke of earth vpon which they plant Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
                        <p>A wall made of earth.</p>
                     </note> Rampier powres his thundring Ire,</l>
                  <l>Which with vnceſſant peales they ſtill doe plie,</l>
                  <l>That ſo our men might not re-fortifie</l>
                  <l>The broken breaches, through whoſe ruin'd vault</l>
                  <l>They thought with eaſe the Bulwarke to aſſault.</l>
                  <l>Heere Bullets glancing from the batter'd wall,</l>
                  <l>Amongſt a Squadron of Defendants fall,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe mangled limbes, like men-ſhap't Meteors flie</l>
                  <l>Through th'horrid paths of the ſmoake-darkened skie.</l>
                  <l>Some other mounting o're the Souldiers head,</l>
                  <l>Meets with two Louers ſporting in their bed,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſoules are haſtned to th' <hi>Eliſian</hi> ſhade,</l>
                  <l>Through that ſwift paſſage which the bullet made.</l>
                  <l>Here fiery balls from murdring<note place="margin">Great pieces of Ordinance.</note> Bombards ſhot,</l>
                  <l>And to their higheſt leuell being got,</l>
                  <l>Make the <hi>Louanian</hi> Students thinke from farre,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Phaeton</hi> is new mounted in his Carre.</l>
                  <l>Nor doth our ſide their Shot and Powder ſpare,</l>
                  <l>But with thicke vollies beats the trembling ayre,</l>
                  <l>Which lighting on the <hi>Iberians</hi> workes much harme,</l>
                  <l>And with their blood the colder earth doth warme.</l>
                  <l>The Townes chiefe command <hi>Vander Noet</hi> did wield,</l>
                  <l>His honour'd ſonne, whom <hi>Newport</hi> once beheld,</l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:9596:16"/>
                  <l>To guard the <hi>Orangian</hi> Standart in that fight,</l>
                  <l>When warlike <hi>Maurice</hi> conquer'd <hi>Alberts</hi> might.</l>
                  <l>He like himſelfe, and like his Fathers ſonne,</l>
                  <l>Leaues nothing vnattempted, nought vndone</l>
                  <l>By which he might th'ingaged place maintaine</l>
                  <l>Gainſt all th'attempts of right-pretending <hi>Spaine.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To farther this, the Pioners are bid</l>
                  <l>To raiſe new Platformes with the ſwifteſt ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>Our<note place="margin">Great baskets of earth.</note> Gabions planted are, behind whoſe bulke</l>
                  <l>The ſmoaking Gunners with their Lintſtockes lurke:</l>
                  <l>Our Ordinance new mounted is to batter,</l>
                  <l>VVhich <hi>Babels</hi> walls, or <hi>Ecbatanes</hi> would ſhatter.</l>
                  <l>The Companies are quartred in the Towne,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe without vpon the Sandie Downe,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe valour doth their Mettall ſtiffe oppoſe,</l>
                  <l>To th'vtmoſt perill of the brauing Foes.</l>
                  <l>But although our ſide iealous of the good</l>
                  <l>And publike ſafetie, to their tackling ſtood</l>
                  <l>With matchleſſe valour; yet <hi>Inigoes</hi> force</l>
                  <l>Their courage, skill, and labour did inforce,</l>
                  <l>To purchaſe that <hi>Yperlian</hi> peereleſſe Gemme</l>
                  <l>Raught by the States from <hi>Flaunders</hi> Diadem;</l>
                  <l>Although that<note place="margin">The North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſt wind.</note> winde, which from <hi>Tartaria</hi> blowes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>From <hi>Rugeland,</hi> and <hi>Moſcouiaes</hi> plaſhy ſlowes</l>
                  <l>Congealed had the <hi>Yperle,</hi> and the <hi>Lieue,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And made their liquid armes and branches ſtiffe;</l>
                  <l>Yet ſtill the Spaniards heated with the fire</l>
                  <l>Of Honour and Reu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nge, did ſtill aſpire:</l>
                  <l>So that the Winters ſtormes, nor Natures threats,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe violence their hardie Legions beats,</l>
                  <l>Could once diuert their valour preſt to die,</l>
                  <l>Or Spaniolize this Towne by victorie.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes a<note place="margin">A Gentleman of a Company, who is to lye vpon his dutie.</note> 
                     <hi>Perdieu</hi> lodg'd vpon the face</l>
                  <l>Of Froſt-bound <hi>Tellus,</hi> in that very place</l>
                  <l>VVhere hee was ſet, is by the Sergeant found</l>
                  <l>Frozen to death, and faſtned to the ground.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes a Sentrie to his Poſture ſtanding,</l>
                  <l>And from the Rounders <hi>Quiuala</hi> demanding,</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:9596:16"/>
                  <l>Ere the laſt Round <hi>Coloſſus</hi>-like doth ſtand,</l>
                  <l>With's aſhie Pike congealed to his hand:</l>
                  <l>Yet theſe diſguſts of Nature ioyn'd with thoſe,</l>
                  <l>Which reuenge bandied from their Sluſian foes,</l>
                  <l>Could not enforce <hi>Inigoes</hi> Troupes to riſe,</l>
                  <l>Proiecting ſtill to gaine Sluce by ſurpriſe.</l>
                  <l>But when the Sunne with his All-cheerefull beames,</l>
                  <l>Had thawed the pauement of the Flemiſh ſtreames,</l>
                  <l>And that his <hi>Phlegon</hi> ſwich'd by ſpeeding time</l>
                  <l>Began t'approch that Heauen-diuiding line,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Zenith perpendicular doth ſtand</l>
                  <l>Ouer the Sun-burnt Aethiopian land.</l>
                  <l>Eighteene braue Cohorts were from Zealand ſent,</l>
                  <l>With danger-daring Reſolution bent,</l>
                  <l>To cut the Dike, and that lowe Champion drench,</l>
                  <l>VVhereon th'<hi>Iberians</hi> did themſelues intrench.</l>
                  <l>Then might you ſee that maſsie bounding frame</l>
                  <l>(VVhoſe Rampier did the Riuers fury tame)</l>
                  <l>Pierſt through and through, and giue a free acceſſe</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Floods, which made their ſwift addreſſe</l>
                  <l>To this inlarged rupture: then the Moales</l>
                  <l>Abandon'd quite their hollow vaulted holes;</l>
                  <l>Conies their Burrowes, Hares their Formes forſooke,</l>
                  <l>And their ſwift legges new poſtures vndertooke,</l>
                  <l>Swimming along with men-deuouring Sharkes,</l>
                  <l>With Muſicke-louing Dolphins, ſcaly Carpes,</l>
                  <l>With bearded Barbels, and that ruddy Fiſh,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Chines are ſeru'd vp for a daintie diſh</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Burgers, when their drunken<note place="margin">Is a Faire, or Reuell.</note> Kirmiſh</l>
                  <l>Inuites their braines with Rheniſh wine to skirmiſh.</l>
                  <l>This Deluge made the <hi>Borgian</hi> Bands retyre,</l>
                  <l>Croſt in the proiect of their proud deſire;</l>
                  <l>Becauſe they fayl'd both of Cazaunt, and Sluce,</l>
                  <l>Which they ſo long'd to gaine for <hi>Philips</hi> vſe.</l>
                  <l>But although <hi>Borges</hi> braue Deſigne was croft</l>
                  <l>By wauering Fortune, and his honour loſt,</l>
                  <l>Together with his Armies, pierſt the heart</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Iſabella</hi> with repining ſmart.</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:9596:17"/>
                  <l>Yet <hi>Vanderbercke,</hi> who <hi>Gulicke</hi> did beſiege</l>
                  <l>With's Legions raiſ'd from <hi>Naples, Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Liege,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Brought comfort to the Court, whoſe furrowed face</l>
                  <l>Lookt frowning ſad for <hi>Sluces</hi> late diſgrace.</l>
                  <l>Hee, whilſt that <hi>Maurice</hi> with his feeble Troupes</l>
                  <l>Incamp'd at <hi>Dornicke,</hi> and his Army droupes,</l>
                  <l>Being preſt with ſickneſſe, marcht vnto the Towne,</l>
                  <l>And there entrencht vpon the bordring ground.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pethan</hi> commanded for the <hi>Belgicke</hi> Peeres</l>
                  <l>As<note place="margin">Chiefe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour.</note> Archprefect, who for ſome fore-paſt yeares,</l>
                  <l>The Cities Helme, and Dutchies both had ſteer'd</l>
                  <l>For's loyall care, for's gouernment vnfear'd.</l>
                  <l>But now ſuſpition mounted on the wing</l>
                  <l>Of iuſt pretence, bred iealouſies within</l>
                  <l>Amongſt our Captaines, whoſe well trained Bands</l>
                  <l>VVere ſubiect to <hi>Pithans</hi> auſtere commands.</l>
                  <l>Hence ſprung this cauſe, the wealthy <hi>Iuliers</hi> Boore</l>
                  <l>Had hoorded vp in his well furniſht ſtore</l>
                  <l>Larger prouiſions, which might well ſupply</l>
                  <l>The pinching wants of our neceſsities:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe foreſeene preſſure did begin to threat</l>
                  <l>A Saguntine penuriouſneſſe of meat,</l>
                  <l>The tainted ſtore prouiſions being ſold,</l>
                  <l>By State-Commiſsion, which the Towne controld.</l>
                  <l>Beſides thoſe Paſtures where the<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Roar,</hi> a great Riuer in the Dutchie of <hi>Iuliars.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Roar</hi> fills</l>
                  <l>His ſlimie channell from the purling hills,</l>
                  <l>Did ſwarme with Heards of that large <hi>German</hi> breed,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe vſe might full releeue the Cities need.</l>
                  <l>For this reſpect the <hi>Gulikans</hi> aduiſe</l>
                  <l>Wauering <hi>Pithan</hi> prouiſions to ſurpriſe</l>
                  <l>From out the Champion, ere th'approaching foes</l>
                  <l>Should ſtop the paſſage, and th' Aduenues cloſe.</l>
                  <l>Good was the Counſell, but like verball winde,</l>
                  <l>It tooke no root within th'vnſetled minde</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Gulickes</hi> Gouernour, whoſe wanting care</l>
                  <l>From all defence our warlike Troupes doth bare.</l>
                  <l>For what out-daring death, ſelfe-lauiſh Sprite</l>
                  <l>Can ſtriue with hunger, or with famine fight?</l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:9596:17"/>
                  <l>Then thus ſuppoſe you ſee ſurrounded round</l>
                  <l>Faire <hi>Gulicks</hi> walls, and that their Trenches bound</l>
                  <l>Cloſe to the<note place="margin">An vtter work commonly rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed beyond all other Fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations.</note> Rauelin, and thoſe vtter workes,</l>
                  <l>Behind whoſe maſſe the ſtout Defendant lurkes.</l>
                  <l>Suppoſe you heare the dreadfull Cannon play</l>
                  <l>From their high-creſted Platformes, and diſplay</l>
                  <l>Strange characters of Death, whoſe ſad aſpect</l>
                  <l>Might terrour on Deaths ſecond ſelfe reflect</l>
                  <l>Lifes lauiſhneſſe, whoſe Adamantine heart</l>
                  <l>Meane terrours doe not mooue, nor cauſe to ſmart.</l>
                  <l>Cloſe to theſe brazen Trunks, the worlds laſt wonder,</l>
                  <l>True counterfeits of <hi>Ioues</hi> amazing thunder,</l>
                  <l>Deaths p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ologue acts his part, the Musket ſounds</l>
                  <l>Lowd ſummons vnto death, to blood and wounds.</l>
                  <l>Nor is this all wee ſuffer, famine raignes,</l>
                  <l>Cleanneſſe of teeth in euery ſtreet complaines;</l>
                  <l>Things horrid are deuour'd, Dogs, Mice, and Rats,</l>
                  <l>Lowd croaking Toadpoles, hunger-ſtarued Cats:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Flemiſh</hi> Courſer, and the <hi>Friſon</hi> Steed,</l>
                  <l>High pamperd for the Saddle now muſt feed</l>
                  <l>The Riders Colon, whoſe vnſatiate maw</l>
                  <l>Both againſt Reaſon, Nature, Cuſtomes Law,</l>
                  <l>Feeds on that fleſh, whoſe liuing backe did beare</l>
                  <l>Himſelfe through horrors mouth, through dangers feare.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe high-fed palats, which not long ſince far'd</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Friſelands</hi> fatteſt Fowle, <hi>Weſtphaliaes</hi> Lard,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Zealandiſh</hi> Salmon, and the wilde Boares haunch,</l>
                  <l>VVith which the richer Dutch doth cram his paunch</l>
                  <l>On ſolemne Feaſt-dayes; theſe for want of meat,</l>
                  <l>Things vilifide and dunghil'd now muſt eat.</l>
                  <l>To redreſſe this our men their Spirits rally,</l>
                  <l>And reſolute appoint a valiant ſally,</l>
                  <l>By whoſe aduenture they might either die,</l>
                  <l>Or manumize themſelues from penurie:</l>
                  <l>Since better 'tis for Valour once to bleed,</l>
                  <l>Then ſtill to feele affliction vnder need.</l>
                  <l>In this conflict<note place="margin">Captaine <hi>Iohn Haydon.</hi>
                     </note> young <hi>Haydon</hi> doth appeare</l>
                  <l>More then himſelfe, out-facing Fate and Feare,</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:9596:18"/>
                  <l>And with his Piſtoll arm'd, diſchargeth ſure</l>
                  <l>With euery ſhot a certaine Sepulture</l>
                  <l>To ſome blacke-viſag'd Spaniard, who doth fall</l>
                  <l>Neuer to riſe, before the laſt dayes call.</l>
                  <l>Amongſt the reſt, one of the proudeſt foes,</l>
                  <l>As Challenger himſelfe in Combate ſhewes,</l>
                  <l>Aduanc'd before the reſt, and there defies</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Goliath</hi>-like his brauer Enemies.</l>
                  <l>This Spur-gall'd <hi>Haydon,</hi> who accepts the fight,</l>
                  <l>And though vnarm'd, yet kills him in the ſight</l>
                  <l>Of both Battalions, then recharg'd falls backe,</l>
                  <l>To anſwere him too with his Piſtols cracke.</l>
                  <l>But the Retreat now ſounded, parts the fray,</l>
                  <l>And our men diſappoynted, cut their way</l>
                  <l>With their well tempred Fauchius, to that gate</l>
                  <l>From whence they made excurſions but of late.</l>
                  <l>This Salley paſt, wherein with doubtfull chance</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bellona</hi> ſhew'd her grimme fac'd countenance,</l>
                  <l>And all reliefe<note place="margin">Debard, or ſhut vp.</note> portculliz'd from the Towne,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Vanderbercks</hi> Intrenchments, who ſits downe</l>
                  <l>Reſolu'd to winne and weare, then courage droopes,</l>
                  <l>And mourning valour vnto famine ſtoopes,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Bilboe-ſteeled poynt was farre more keene,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Spaniards</hi> wrath, or <hi>Vanderbercks</hi> fierce ſpleene.</l>
                  <l>Theſe motiues vrg'd a parle, both condiſcend</l>
                  <l>To this condition, and Committees ſend</l>
                  <l>As Delegates in truſt, whoſe ſound aduice</l>
                  <l>The preſent difference might full compremiſe.</l>
                  <l>Both parties being agreed, Count <hi>Henrie</hi> takes</l>
                  <l>Reconquerd <hi>Gulicke,</hi> which <hi>Pithan</hi> forſakes,</l>
                  <l>Who now diſmarching through the Coleine port,</l>
                  <l>Surrenders vp this hunger-conqu'red Fort.</l>
                  <l>To reaffront this loſſe, when firſt the Spring,</l>
                  <l>To Winter-tyred mortalls ioy doth bring:</l>
                  <l>When May firſt opens thoſe ſelfe-named Flowers,</l>
                  <l>Which Aprill bloſſomes with his pearled ſhowers:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Naſſauian</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Henry <hi>of</hi> Naſſaw.</note> 
                     <hi>Henricke</hi> with ſelected Bands</l>
                  <l>Of Horſe and Foot, in fruitfull <hi>Brabant</hi> lands</l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:9596:18"/>
                  <l>Neere to <hi>Breda,</hi> from whence his dreadfull Armes</l>
                  <l>Tranſported worke ſtrange characters of harmes</l>
                  <l>In little <hi>Brabant;</hi> Famine, Sword, and Fire</l>
                  <l>Glutting Reuenge freſh boyling with deſire.</l>
                  <l>Some fiftie Dorpes were in a moment burn'd,</l>
                  <l>And their faire-fronted Edifices turn'd,</l>
                  <l>By the conſumption of the raging flame</l>
                  <l>To that firſt Chaos, from whence firſt they came.</l>
                  <l>In midſt of theſe Combuſtions <hi>Henry</hi> falls</l>
                  <l>Before well fenced, well mann'd <hi>Herentals,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where ſeeking by Petarre to force the place,</l>
                  <l>Our wanting<note place="margin">The Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard.</note> Van ſhew'd not that wonted face</l>
                  <l>Of ancient reſolution, whoſe default</l>
                  <l>Debars the reſt from<note place="margin">A Towne in little <hi>Brabant.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Herentals</hi> aſſault.</l>
                  <l>Yet after this repulſe, our Foot ſurpriſe,</l>
                  <l>Partly by force, partly by Compremiſe,</l>
                  <l>Two<note place="margin">Little Forts much vſed by the Dutch. An Incurſion of Horſe.</note> Sconces from the foes, whoſe trembling hands</l>
                  <l>Make good the Ports for <hi>Naſſaws</hi> ſure commands.</l>
                  <l>Beſides our Horſe a<note place="margin">Little Forts much vſed by the Dutch. An Incurſion of Horſe.</note> Caualgado make</l>
                  <l>Cloſe vnto <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> whoſe burnt Suburbs take</l>
                  <l>Impreſsions of our wrath; th' Archdutcheſſe ſees</l>
                  <l>The frowning face of theſe ſad miſeries,</l>
                  <l>Yet cannot ſhee redreſſe them: for mans will</l>
                  <l>Proiected reſolutions cannot fill,</l>
                  <l>Without iuſt meanes of power, which Heauen ſends</l>
                  <l>As Inſtruments t'accompliſh humane ends.</l>
                  <l>Thus this incurſion paſt, our men retire</l>
                  <l>Thorough the ſmoaking flames of <hi>Brabants</hi> fire</l>
                  <l>Vnto <hi>Breda,</hi> rewarded for their paines</l>
                  <l>With honours Crowne, and conquerd Spaniſh gaines.</l>
                  <l>Nor thus alone the Land with ſlaughter bleeds,</l>
                  <l>But vnto <hi>Neptunes</hi> Maine <hi>Bellona</hi> ſpeeds</l>
                  <l>With Engines of deſtruction, where ſhee ſtaines</l>
                  <l>With ſtreames of blood the Sea-gods watry plaines.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe vaſt Armadaes, which commanded lay</l>
                  <l>Neere to <hi>Baioun,</hi> and <hi>Saint Sebaſtians</hi> Bay,</l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:9596:19"/>
                  <l>Their Galeouns houering neere to <hi>Lisbones</hi> walls,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Tagus</hi> into <hi>Thetis</hi> boſome falls;</l>
                  <l>Their nimble Gallies ſlicing with their Oares</l>
                  <l>Thoſe billowing waues, which beat on <hi>Affrickes</hi> ſhores,</l>
                  <l>Sometimes on th'Oceans Maine incountring meet</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Amſterdams,</hi> or <hi>Fluſhings</hi> warlike Fleet,</l>
                  <l>Which homewards bound from <hi>Venice,</hi> or <hi>Ligorne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From <hi>Scanderoun,</hi> or <hi>Aegypt</hi> rich in Corne,</l>
                  <l>Doe proudly plow the Mediterran Maine,</l>
                  <l>Swelling with profit, and full fraught with gaine.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes againe <hi>Moy Lambert,</hi> or <hi>L' Hermite,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Willeks,</hi> or fierce <hi>Hugen</hi> this loſſe requite;</l>
                  <l>Who trauerſing thoſe Seas, whoſe rougher Tide</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Magellanus</hi> Streights doth Northweſt glide,</l>
                  <l>Neere to th'<hi>Honduras</hi> Gulfe, <hi>Domingoes</hi> Ile,</l>
                  <l>Or the <hi>Terceraes,</hi> famous for the foyle</l>
                  <l>Of valiant <hi>Stroſſy,</hi> meet ſome Spaniſh Hulke,</l>
                  <l>Or ſome ſwift Caruell, whoſe full fraughted bulke</l>
                  <l>Is loaden with that rich<note place="margin">At <hi>Petoſi</hi> in <hi>Peru</hi> are moſt rich Mines of Gold.</note> 
                     <hi>Potoſian</hi> Oare,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Lima</hi> ſends from <hi>Perues</hi> wealthy ſhoare.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes againe neere the <hi>Balſoran</hi> Sound,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Teneriffaes</hi> pike, where Amber's found</l>
                  <l>Of th'higheſt price, ſome of their armed Ships</l>
                  <l>Incounter with ſome Carracke, whoſe ſtrong ribs</l>
                  <l>Are ballaſt with thoſe drugs, which <hi>Chinaes</hi> plaines</l>
                  <l>Send from their fruitfull Aromatique vaines;</l>
                  <l>Or with thoſe Spices, which for barter'd Gold</l>
                  <l>Are by the<note place="margin">The Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>Iaua,</hi> and the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luccoes.</hi> A place in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fricke,</hi> ſubiect to the <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Iauans,</hi> and <hi>Moluccoies</hi> ſold.</l>
                  <l>Amongſt the reſt great <hi>Angolaes</hi> Viceroy</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Andaluzia</hi> bound, with ſmiling ioy</l>
                  <l>Th' Atlantique Ocean cuts, and proudly ſailes</l>
                  <l>Thorough the Maine, till ſome <hi>Dutch</hi> Sea-man hailes,</l>
                  <l>And bids him ſtrike: then as th' <hi>Hircanian</hi> beaſt,</l>
                  <l>Whom the purſuing Hunter doth inueſt</l>
                  <l>With's knottie Toyles, firſt ſeekes to ſcape the danger;</l>
                  <l>But that being vaine, he turnes his feare to anger,</l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:9596:19"/>
                  <l>And fiercely coaping with th'incountring foe,</l>
                  <l>Doth th'vtmoſt deuoir of his courage ſhow.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Portugueze</hi> vnequall to ſuſtaine</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Fluſhingers</hi> incounter, plies amaine</l>
                  <l>Both Helme and Yard, and forwards led by feare</l>
                  <l>Swifter then any wind, doth nimbly ſteere</l>
                  <l>Ouer the ridge of thoſe high-breaking waues,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe beating ſurge <hi>Terceraes</hi> foreland lanes.</l>
                  <l>But this being labour loſt, he turnes his head</l>
                  <l>Vnto the combate with a ſide-wind ſped:</l>
                  <l>Then their Canoniers with the<note place="margin">An Engine which Gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners vſe to charge Ordinance.</note> Carteridge ply</l>
                  <l>Their great and leſſer ſiz'd Artillery,</l>
                  <l>Larboord and Starboord readie for the charge,</l>
                  <l>Their Langrell, and their Croſſe-barre ſhot diſcharge:<note place="margin">Great ſhot v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at Sea,</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Muskettiers ſtanding vpon a Range,</l>
                  <l>Behind the Waſt-cloaths doe their bullets change,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Granado</hi> balls, from th'hand, or Bombard ſent,</l>
                  <l>With vaprous ſmoake obſcure the Firmament:</l>
                  <l>So that ſuruaying water, land, or ayre,</l>
                  <l>Death, dread, and danger ſwarmed eu'ry where.</l>
                  <l>The Sea-nimphs were afraid, and <hi>Neptune</hi> hid</l>
                  <l>His forked Maſe with feare aſtoniſhed.</l>
                  <l>The trembling Mermayds did for horrour quake,</l>
                  <l>As when th'incloſed winds the waters ſhake,</l>
                  <l>Thinking <hi>Prometheus</hi> hauing broke thoſe bands,</l>
                  <l>Which manacled his Vultur-griped hands,</l>
                  <l>And manumiz'd from his tormenting paine,</l>
                  <l>Did imitate <hi>Ioues</hi> Thunderbolts againe.</l>
                  <l>But when that both ſides to their cloſe fights came,</l>
                  <l>And tryed the laſt chance of this martiall Game,</l>
                  <l>From out the Scuttle-holes ſpouted ſtreames of blood,</l>
                  <l>Which clotted on the curled Ocean ſtood,</l>
                  <l>The Murderers from out their higher Tires,</l>
                  <l>Diſcharged dreadfull flakes of ſulphrous fires,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſtrong emiſsiue power with Tarlin kill'd</l>
                  <l>Whole hundreds, and with ſlaughtred carnage fill'd</l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:9596:20"/>
                  <l>Their vpper Decks, which ſtraight blowne vp did flye</l>
                  <l>Through the vaſt extent of th'inameld skie.</l>
                  <l>But at the length the <hi>Portugalls</hi> purſued</l>
                  <l>With danger of all hands, for Quarter ſued</l>
                  <l>Vnto the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who from the fartheſt South</l>
                  <l>Th'<hi>Angolians</hi> brought to<note place="margin">The Riuer of <hi>Fluſhing.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Scheldis</hi> watrie mouth,</l>
                  <l>Inriched for their hazard with that Gold,</l>
                  <l>Which heaped lay within that Galeouns hold.</l>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:9596:20"/>
                  <p>BELGIAES TROVBLES, AND TRIVMPHS.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Second Booke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>WHEREIN ARE RELA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all the moſt famous Occurrences which haue happened in the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, <hi>from the Aſcenſion of our</hi> Sauiour, 1622. vnto this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time, 1625.</p>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Augustine Matthewes,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Norton.</hi> 1625.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:9596:21"/>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:9596:21"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE, EDVVARD, LORD CONVVAY, Baron of Raggely, and one of his Maieſties principall Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries of State, And Sir HORACE VEARE, Col. <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the Engliſh in the Netherlands,</hi> WILLIAM CROSSE wiſheth that happineſſe which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues deſire.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, your knowne loues to the Vnited Prouinces of the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, and their Cauſe, ſealed by your Honours with the free expence of your deareſt blood, and the frequent hazard of your liues, haue beſides thoſe other motiues of your knowledge, iudgement, and experience in Subiects of this nature, inuited mee to this Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The first Part of <hi>Belgiaes Troubles and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs,</hi> belongs to the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and my Lord <hi>Montioy;</hi> the ſecond part is conſecrated to your Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſelues: Both theſe are rather a Diſcourſe, then a Poeme, as truely and Hiſtorically relating the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable and time-neerer Exployts, which haue paſſed betweene the <hi>Dutch</hi> and the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in theſe laſt foure yeeres Warres of the Netherlands. In this Liſt,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:9596:22"/> the Siege of <hi>Bergen,</hi> and that of <hi>Breda,</hi> the Battels of <hi>Flewry</hi> and <hi>Statloo,</hi> with the taking of <hi>Saint Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour</hi> in <hi>Braſilia,</hi> challenge aboue the reſt the chiefeſt place and prerogatiue. The reſt are minor geſts, and deeds of leſſe conſequence, yet worthy for their worths to bee kept in the cloſet of Remembrance. In all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe as in a repreſenting Glaſſe, you may ſee the mercie of God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended from time to time to this Eſtate, firſt erected from the Inforcements of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> tyrannie, ſince ſupported by the Auxiliary meanes of the <hi>Engliſh, French,</hi> and <hi>Scots,</hi> and maintained at this preſent in that greatneſſe, which the world ſees and admires, by Policie, Power, and Religion. If publike cenſure bee as impartiall as is the Poeme, the Authour ſhall thinke his endeuours fortunate: As for your Noble ſelues, he doth preſume vpon the candour and integritie of your Eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, vndoubtedly knowing, that you accept a mite as reſpectiuely as a talent, and esteeme the freedome of the Giuer, more then the value of the gift. Vpon this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance hee doth rest, and ſo doth for euer reſt</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Honours moſt deuoted Seruant,</hi> William Croſſe.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="2" type="book">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:9596:22"/>
                  <head>BELGIA'S TROVBLES AND TRIVMPHS.</head>
                  <head type="sub"> 
                     <hi>The ſecond Booke.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <argument>
                     <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
                     <p>IN this ſecond part continued from the Aſcenſion of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, <hi>anno 1622,</hi> vnto this preſent time, <hi>anno 1624,</hi> are contained a Deſcription of our firſt Leaguer at <hi>Rees,</hi> with the killing of an Jtalian Captaine by <hi>Beaumont</hi> a Frenchman hand to hand. His Excellencies aſcent to <hi>Gravenweert,</hi> and a Relation of a Camiſado, giuen by foureteene Troupes of the enemies Horſe vpon our quarters. Our march to the <hi>Buſſe,</hi> and our retreat from thence. The ſiege of <hi>Bergen,</hi> and that famous Battell fought neere <hi>Fleury,</hi> betweene Count <hi>Maunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> and <hi>Gonſaluo de Corduba.</hi> The co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſpiracie of <hi>Barne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velts</hi> two ſonnes, and other <hi>Arminians</hi> againſt the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> The Battell of <hi>Statloo,</hi> fought betweene <hi>Tilley</hi> and <hi>Bru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſwicke.</hi> The taking of S. <hi>Saluadour.</hi> The Siege of <hi>Breda,</hi> with the ſurpriſall of <hi>Goffe</hi> by <hi>Charles Lambert.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter our Troups had breath'd, and that the date</l>
                  <l>Of that ſame Feaſt, which Mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>als conſecrate</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Chriſts Aſcenſion,</hi> had proclaim'd the Field</l>
                  <l>Tour <hi>Belgicke</hi> Troups, with ſtrength and courage ſteeld,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Orders of Command.</note>Potents were ſent forth, full ſixe thouſand poaſt,</l>
                  <l>Vpon their Summons from that nether coaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of fertill <hi>Holland,</hi> to that higher land,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Rees</hi> ore-lookes the billowing <hi>Rhenus</hi> Strand.</l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:9596:23"/>
                  <l>There ſafe ariuing, with the deluing Spade</l>
                  <l>New horned Workes, Intrenchments new were made;</l>
                  <l>Behind whoſe breaſt they might themſelues defend</l>
                  <l>From <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>anderbercke,</hi> whoſe <hi>Argian</hi> eyes attend</l>
                  <l>Vpon our motions all, on each deſigne,</l>
                  <l>Which he ſtill thwarting, ſeekes to countermine.</l>
                  <l>Amongſt the reſt, with ſome <hi>Italian</hi> Horſe,</l>
                  <l>He ſeekes to gaine the<note place="margin">A Turnepike is a gate which giues entrance into the Camp</note> Turnepike, and to force</l>
                  <l>Our Horſe-guard led by <hi>Beaumont,</hi> who doth frount</l>
                  <l>The dreadfull ſhocke of this <hi>Italian</hi> brunt.</l>
                  <l>Him their <hi>Ligurian</hi> Leader hauing ſpied</l>
                  <l>By's wauing Plume, and Armour rich deſcried:</l>
                  <l>Come on, come on, quoth hee, let vs two trie</l>
                  <l>The doubtfull fortune of this Victorie;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Armes, that Plume ſhall be the Conquerors ſpoyle,</l>
                  <l>And honour'd marks of vanquiſht <hi>Beaumonts</hi> foyle.</l>
                  <l>With this his ſpurr'd Calabrian Courſer flies</l>
                  <l>Swifter then winde, and curuetting doth riſe</l>
                  <l>Beyond the briſtled<note place="margin">Haſpels are Engines made to throw down before the Turnepike, which point e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery way with pikes about an ell long.</note> Haſpels, where they ioyne</l>
                  <l>Force vnto force this Combate to define.</l>
                  <l>Not Almaine-like they wheele about at large,</l>
                  <l>But Poldron vnto Poldron, make the charge</l>
                  <l>With their death-belching Piſtols, both which ſtrike</l>
                  <l>With equall force, but fortune much vnlike.</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Beaumont</hi> ſlightly's wounded in the thigh,</l>
                  <l>T'other is ſlaine, and falls downe preſently,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe carkeiſe after many mortall blowes</l>
                  <l>Recouer'd is, recarried by the foes</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Campe, where they this chance lament,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">This Italian was <hi>Spinolaes</hi> kinſman.</note>Seal'd with the loſſe of one ſo eminent;</l>
                  <l>As alyed to the Marqueſſe, and for's Spirit,</l>
                  <l>Not dignified ſo much by Blood, as Merit.</l>
                  <l>After ſome month in this firſt Station ſpent,</l>
                  <l>Eight thouſand more were by Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> ſent</l>
                  <l>Towards <hi>Skenkes</hi>-Sconce; who doubling <hi>Arnhams</hi> walls,</l>
                  <l>Arriues at<note place="margin">Otherwiſe, <hi>Skenkes</hi> Sconce</note> 
                     <hi>Grauenweert,</hi> and from thence falls</l>
                  <l>Ouer the <hi>Wahal</hi> to thoſe Southerne bankes,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Skenks</hi>-Sconce with his thundring Cannon flanks.</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:9596:23"/>
                  <l>There being come, their Pioneers do raiſe</l>
                  <l>Strong<note place="margin">Little forts which the Dutch raiſe ſuddenly for their defences.</note> Redoubts on the paſſage of thoſe wayes,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe winding turnes runne from the Cleuian hill</l>
                  <l>To thoſe Intrenchments which our footebands fill.</l>
                  <l>Our horſe without, and vnintrenched lay</l>
                  <l>With watchfull care ſafeguarding night and day,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſmall Batauian<note place="margin">Villages.</note> Dorps, whoſe verge extends</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Nimegham</hi> to <hi>Geldriaes</hi> Eaſterne ends.</l>
                  <l>This ſeeming ſhewd aduantage doth incite</l>
                  <l>Proud <hi>Vanderbercke</hi> the <hi>Reezian</hi> foile to quite,<note place="margin">Camiſade a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> aſſaulte in their own lodginge.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>With ſome freſh Camiſade: for this deſigne</l>
                  <l>Some foureteene troups paſſe o're that Apennine</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Cleuia</hi> ſtands, who couered by the night</l>
                  <l>And a ſtill march, about the dawning light</l>
                  <l>Approch our vtter Sentries, and ſurpriſe</l>
                  <l>Them and the<note place="margin">Thoſe that walke the Round.</note> Rounders, whoſe ſleepe ſealed eyes</l>
                  <l>Betray the reſt; hence trauerſing that way</l>
                  <l>Neere vnto which our Scotiſh horſeguard lay,</l>
                  <l>Theſe proud Burgonian Reiſters forthwith finde</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Balfour</hi> ſurpriſd in ods, but not in minde;<note place="margin">Sir <hi>William Balfour</hi> that day comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the horſe guarde.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who thus ingagd receiues the dreadfull ſhocke</l>
                  <l>Of theſe ſwarte Rutters, rendring knocke for knocke:</l>
                  <l>Till at the length diſmounted he doth yeeld</l>
                  <l>Vnto the ſtronger, who thence ſcourd the field</l>
                  <l>After his Cornet, which retiring flies</l>
                  <l>Couerd with fire, oppreſt with Enemies,</l>
                  <l>And on the ſtation of our Footeguards fell</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Muskettiers theſe Carbins ſtraight repell.</l>
                  <l>For now from eu'ry ſide th'Alarum takes,</l>
                  <l>And each man to the battell Champion makes,</l>
                  <l>Where nought was ſeene vpon the bloudy plaine</l>
                  <l>But batterd armes, and carkeiſſes new ſlaine.</l>
                  <l>The loſſe was like, for our men did ſurpriſe</l>
                  <l>The<note place="margin">A Wallone who came the day before into our campe being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſ'd.</note> chiefe conductor of this enterpriſe</l>
                  <l>With a Burgonian Captaine; of our ſide</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Balfour</hi> was tae'n, and <hi>Weimars</hi> Duke lyes by't,</l>
                  <l>Vntill ſome better fortune ſhould decree,</l>
                  <l>Th' vncertaine ſcope of his Captiuitie.</l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:9596:24"/>
                  <l>To requite this affrount this proud ſurpriſe</l>
                  <l>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ince <hi>Maurice</hi> with ſix thouſand foote doth riſe</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Grauenweert,</hi> and floating downe wards fals,</l>
                  <l>Without the ratling Drums, or trumpets cals</l>
                  <l>Beyond fat <hi>Bommelweert,</hi> where he doth land</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Phalangiers,</hi> who paſsing by commaunde</l>
                  <l>Waft o're the <hi>Moſas</hi> Willow bordred banks</l>
                  <l>Whoſe waues do waſh well fenced <hi>Huiſdens</hi> flanks.</l>
                  <l>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ching from thence our vauntcurrors deſcrye</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Commonly called the <hi>Buſſe.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Shertokenbuſſe,</hi> whoſe maiden ports defie</l>
                  <l>All onſlats, all attempts, and proudly ſtands</l>
                  <l>Vpon defence with ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u'nteene choſen bands</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>VVallons,</hi> and <hi>Brabanſons</hi> readie preſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ich life, and limme to keepe the ſeathred neſt</l>
                  <l>Of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe free booters, who by<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Derricke</hi> was Captaine of two hundred free booters who lay in the <hi>Buſſe.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Derricke</hi> led</l>
                  <l>Themſelues to rapine, murder, pillage wedde,</l>
                  <l>And feeding on the contribution <hi>Boore,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Greaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> palmes, and paunch with his conſumed ſtore.</l>
                  <l>There hauing viewed that well defenced towne,</l>
                  <l>We made a ſtand vpon the bordring downe</l>
                  <l>About the time, that gliſtring <hi>Phaebus</hi> laues</l>
                  <l>His bright Carroch in Thet is weſterne waues.</l>
                  <l>Then orders were giu'n out, the caſd<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Petarrs</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins made to blow vp gates.</note> 
                     <hi>Petarres</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Strange Engins found out in our moderne wars,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſulphr'ous power the brazen gates would ſhatter</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Ecbatane,</hi> and that ſtrong portall batter</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">The Iron gates which <hi>Alexander</hi> made vpon the ſtreights of mount <hi>Canca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi>
                     </note>Whereas the ſteepe Caucaſean mountaines rockes</l>
                  <l>Are chaynd as priſ'ners with his Iron lockes:)</l>
                  <l>Theſe <hi>Corbett</hi> did commaund, the firſt aduenture</l>
                  <l>Was <hi>Tibals</hi> chardge, who formoſt was to enter</l>
                  <l>With that ſelected crue, that choſen band</l>
                  <l>Which he as <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eares</hi> Lieutenaunt did commaund.</l>
                  <l>Thus all things being diſpoſed for the fight</l>
                  <l>We roſe from thence, and marching all that night</l>
                  <l>Paſt thorough ſandy, rough, Maeanderd wayes</l>
                  <l>Where errour led our ſmall battalion ſtrayes.</l>
                  <l>So that we came not to the <hi>Buſsian</hi> gate</l>
                  <l>Before the dawning light, a time to late</l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:9596:24"/>
                  <l>The ſtrong portcullizd <hi>Turnepike</hi> to ſurpriſe</l>
                  <l>VVhich<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Grobbend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ncke</hi> was as then gouernour of the towne.</note> 
                     <hi>Grobbendoncke</hi> with's hundred watchfull eyes</l>
                  <l>Safeguarded ſure, who takes a cloſe Alar'me</l>
                  <l>VVith all his bands, commaunding all to arme.</l>
                  <l>This cauſ'd vs to retire, and homewards bend</l>
                  <l>VVith out th' effect of that proiected ende,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe hopes had brought vs to thoſe Champion plaines</l>
                  <l>VVhich <hi>Maſe</hi> enricheth with his flowing vaines,</l>
                  <l>The Spoiles of <hi>Brabant,</hi> and the conquer'd <hi>Buſſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Being the proiect of each wanting purſe.</l>
                  <l>In this retraite our troups were hunger preſt</l>
                  <l>Tired with trauaile, and with thirſt oppreſt:</l>
                  <l>So that vntill we toucht vpon the <hi>Maſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Towards whoſe ſtreames our Maniples did pace,</l>
                  <l>We far'd like ſome <hi>Alarbian</hi> hungrie theefe</l>
                  <l>Who trauerſing the deſert for releefe</l>
                  <l>Followes the tracke of ſome knowne Carauan,</l>
                  <l>Which to fulfill their Heath'niſh <hi>Alcoran,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Viſits that prophane <hi>Mahometan</hi> ſhrine</l>
                  <l>Plac'd by the Caliphs<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>echa</hi> in <hi>Arabia.</hi>
                     </note> neere th' <hi>Arabian</hi> Sine.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſtinking pooles, <hi>Cocitus</hi> like aſpected</l>
                  <l>Which the Maraſhes vapours had infected,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe puddle lakes wherein the water Toade</l>
                  <l>The Frogge and Horſleech keepe their ſafe aboade,</l>
                  <l>Were ſought, and ſearcht out to alay the fire</l>
                  <l>Of appetite freſh burning with deſire.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe liquour was more pretious to the mouth</l>
                  <l>Then all thoſe wines tranſported from the South</l>
                  <l>Which the <hi>Canarian</hi> Ilander doth ſup</l>
                  <l>On ſollemne feaſts in's <hi>Nectar</hi> crowned Cup,</l>
                  <l>Then that the <hi>Cretan</hi> neere <hi>Cerathus</hi> drinks,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Bachrach</hi> ſends from <hi>Rhenus</hi> ſandy brinks.</l>
                  <l>Yet after thoſe diſguſts ſurmounted all,</l>
                  <l>Which like ſome ſtorme vpon our troups did fall,</l>
                  <l>And thoſe freebooters all repulſed backe,</l>
                  <l>Which followd our <hi>Naſſauians</hi> by the tracke;</l>
                  <l>We paſt vnto the<note place="margin">A towne in <hi>Gelderland</hi> belonging to the ſtates.</note> 
                     <hi>Graue,</hi> where each man feedes</l>
                  <l>In plenties <hi>Magazin,</hi> and all our needes</l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:9596:25"/>
                  <l>Receiud ſupplies from thoſe fat Geldrian fields,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſwarming ſtoare, Bread, Beefe and Mutton yeelds</l>
                  <l>In greater meaſure, then that Eaſterne land,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">The lands of <hi>Aſſiria</hi> and <hi>Hungarie</hi> are very fruitefull.</note>VVhich borders on the roaring Tigris ſtrande,</l>
                  <l>Or thoſe <hi>Pannonian</hi> paſtures, where the graſſe</l>
                  <l>For's ſudden growth compariſon doth paſſe.</l>
                  <l>Thus hauing well refreſht our hungry bands</l>
                  <l>VVe doubled thoſe high creſted heathy lands,</l>
                  <l>VVhich forth extended from the billowing Maſe,</l>
                  <l>Do ouerlooke the Betowes various face.</l>
                  <l>From thence our tired legions ſpeeding came</l>
                  <l>Vnto the ports of<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nimegham</hi> ſtands high vpon the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of a hill.</note> high built <hi>Nimegham,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There reſting one whole night we made deſcent</l>
                  <l>Vnto the plaines of that lowe Continent,</l>
                  <l>VVhere neere to our Intrenchments <hi>Waal</hi> doth ſlide</l>
                  <l>From out the Rhines inameld diaprie ſide,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe weeping waues ſeemd to condole with vs,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe we miſt th' vnconquerd maiden Buſſe.</l>
                  <l>But in this ſpace that warre like <hi>Genoueſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Th' Infantaes Generall ſcorning pampred eaſe,</l>
                  <l>VVith theſe alarums rowſd doth angry fare</l>
                  <l>Like ſome Muſcouian winter pined Beare,</l>
                  <l>VVho when the Sun begins to melt the Snow,</l>
                  <l>VVhich pargetteth that Northerne Climats brow</l>
                  <l>Forſakes his denne, and roauing runs for praye</l>
                  <l>VVith all his Cubs their hunger to alay.</l>
                  <l>To quench this bloodie thirſt he ſends commands</l>
                  <l>Through <hi>Flaunders, Heinault</hi> and thoſe <hi>VVallon</hi> lands,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe Frontier from the Britiſh Ocean bends</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Limburge,</hi> and <hi>Burgundiaes</hi> weſterne ends:</l>
                  <l>Inioyning all their Garriſons to arme</l>
                  <l>Vpon the ſummons of this firſt Alarme,</l>
                  <l>And at a day prefixt themſelues to ſhow</l>
                  <l>Neere <hi>Antwerpe</hi> their determin'd Randeuowe.</l>
                  <l>Theſe Regiments, with thoſe which <hi>Borges</hi> ledde,</l>
                  <l>Who neere to Sluce were winter-billetted,</l>
                  <l>Vpon this order to <hi>Steu'n Bergen</hi> paſt</l>
                  <l>In warrelike manner neere to <hi>Iulies</hi> laſt.</l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:9596:25"/>
                  <l>That towne being wonne, they lingerd not an houre</l>
                  <l>But ſtraight-waies marcht with their victorious power</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Bergen,</hi> where their men the<note place="margin">A Terrier in properly any thing that puts it ſelfe into the earth.</note> 
                     <hi>Terriers</hi> play</l>
                  <l>Behind that Mount, which oppoſite then lay</l>
                  <l>Vnto the port of <hi>VVowe,</hi> from whence their workes,</l>
                  <l>Behind whoſe couert all their Armie lurkes,</l>
                  <l>Extended ran vnto the <hi>Kickepotte</hi> forte,</l>
                  <l>Which ouerlookes the Cities Southerne porte.</l>
                  <l>Vpon their firſt approch ſome Squadrons preſt</l>
                  <l>Did Sallie forth, and ſallying did Inueſt</l>
                  <l>That hillocke, where the <hi>Vauzian Engliſh</hi> ſtoode,<note place="margin">The Engliſh of my Lord <hi>Vauxes</hi> regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>In Caſtiles cauſe ſelfelauiſh of their blood.</l>
                  <l>Harde was the fight, for nation againſt nation</l>
                  <l>Engliſh 'gainſt Engliſh fought with emulation;</l>
                  <l>But ſtill the Marques ſending freſh ſupplies,</l>
                  <l>With number more then valour wonne the priſe</l>
                  <l>From the beſieged, who with ods ſurchardg'd</l>
                  <l>Retired, and retiring ſtill diſchardg'd</l>
                  <l>Their murdring Muſkets on the Spaniſh files,</l>
                  <l>Which ſix to one ſurpaſt our<note place="margin">A Maniple is a diuiſion of files.</note> Maniples.</l>
                  <l>After the paſſage of this firſt affrounte,</l>
                  <l>The foes incouragd did their Cannon mount</l>
                  <l>Vpon new<note place="margin">A place to mount Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance on.</note> platformes raiſ'd, whoſe thundring reach</l>
                  <l>Hauing inforcd an aſſaultable breach,</l>
                  <l>They ſcald the ruines, and began the fight</l>
                  <l>Vaild with the Curtin of a Mooneſhine night</l>
                  <l>About the ſecond Round: with various chaunce</l>
                  <l>In this conflict <hi>Mars</hi> ſhewed his countenance</l>
                  <l>Vnto both parties, for the Martiall foe</l>
                  <l>Sometimes was beate; ſometimes did ouerthrow:</l>
                  <l>Thrice being repulſd, they thrice did reaſſaile</l>
                  <l>And though oppreſt, their courage ne're did faile:</l>
                  <l>For knowing valour to be actions Spirit,</l>
                  <l>Which Crownes our proiects with ſucceſſefull merit,</l>
                  <l>They rallied ſtill, till <hi>Phaebus</hi> lift his head</l>
                  <l>From pearld <hi>Auroraes</hi> ſaffron coulered bedde:</l>
                  <l>Then being ſubiect to the pointeblancke ayme</l>
                  <l>Of eu'ry markeman, they forſooke the game</l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:9596:26"/>
                  <l>Vnequall of their parts, and backewards plied</l>
                  <l>Vnto their Trenches from the bulwarkes ſide.</l>
                  <l>The loſſe was great, twelue hundred Spaniards kild</l>
                  <l>The bending Circle of our<note place="margin">A Fortification made in forme or manner of a horne.</note> 
                     <hi>Horn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>worke</hi> fild,</l>
                  <l>Two hundred of our ſide did likewiſe dye</l>
                  <l>Leauing their fames pawnes to Eternitie:</l>
                  <l>Amongſt the reſt <hi>Purfry</hi> my noble friend</l>
                  <l>In honours bedde ſeald vp his glorious ende,</l>
                  <l>The like was<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Michael Eueret</hi> and Captaine <hi>Loueles.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Eueretts</hi> chance, and <hi>Loueleſſe</hi> lot,</l>
                  <l>Both which with poyſned bullets being ſhot,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> skill could not appeaſe,</l>
                  <l>Nor Surgerie the venoms rancour eaſe,</l>
                  <l>Exchaungd their liuing fleſh to liueleſſe duſt</l>
                  <l>Till heau'n thronizd immortall riſe they muſt.</l>
                  <l>Inhuman warre thou horſeleech of mankinde,</l>
                  <l>Which pleaſure in diſpleaſure ſtil doſt finde,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe manſions are deaths hollowe charnelld caues</l>
                  <l>Large fields of ſlaughter, where thy furie raues</l>
                  <l>Vnlimitted, and boundeles in that luſt,</l>
                  <l>Which nought but bloud and murder content muſt.</l>
                  <l>Were not the <hi>Roman</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The darte which the Romans</note> pile, the <hi>Parthian</hi> ſhaft,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Graecian</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The pike which the <hi>Macedonians</hi> vſd.</note> 
                     <hi>Sariſſe,</hi> and <hi>Moriſcan</hi> dart,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>T'heluetian</hi> halberd, and our <hi>Britiſh</hi> bill</l>
                  <l>Potent inough thy greedineſſe to fill</l>
                  <l>With ſlaughtred bodies? but that <hi>Organs</hi> new</l>
                  <l>Muſt terriblize themſelues to mortals <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iewe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which thou haſt found out in this latter age,</l>
                  <l>To Cocker vp thy blood ſtill thirſting rage.</l>
                  <l>Now muſt that<note place="margin">Great ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</note> Brazen fire outbelching trunke</l>
                  <l>Founde out by that accurſed German Munke,</l>
                  <l>Whole myriads kill, and raiſe of bodies ſlaine</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pyramide</hi> Mounttaines on the ſanguind plaine.</l>
                  <l>To furniſh this deuice, thoſe ſtinking cels</l>
                  <l>Wherein the louing <hi>Paphian</hi> Pigeon dwells,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Cellars, where our Engliſh skenker fils</l>
                  <l>That ruddie Claret ſent from <hi>Gaſcoines</hi> hils,</l>
                  <l>Muſt now be ſearcht for<note place="margin">Saltpeter.</note> 
                     <hi>Nitre: Swethlands</hi> braſſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Guipuſcan</hi> Iron, and that heauie maſſe</l>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:9596:26"/>
                  <l>Of palefac'd leade, ſent from the Northerne<note place="margin">From the Peake in <hi>Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhire</hi> comes great ſtore of Leade.</note> Peake</l>
                  <l>Muſt now with ſtreames from mangled bodies reake,</l>
                  <l>Clay muſt be fetcht from <hi>Padoaes</hi> fertill plaines,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sulphur</hi> from <hi>Sicills</hi> fire out belching vaines,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rozin</hi> from <hi>Rugeland,</hi> and that <hi>Borill</hi> coaſte,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Riga</hi> ſtands, now to the <hi>Swethner</hi> loſt:</l>
                  <l>To make<note place="margin">
                        <p>Theſe are in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gredients with which <hi>Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does</hi> and wilde fire bals are made.</p>
                        <p>See <hi>Machiael</hi> in the addition to his booke of warre pag. 45 45.</p>
                     </note> thoſe fierie balls, Granadin Squibs</l>
                  <l>Aſpected like crinited Comets glibs,</l>
                  <l>Which burning breake, and breaking peecemeale rent</l>
                  <l>All thats oppoſd to this fell inſtrument.</l>
                  <l>But as though all theſe Engins were but weake</l>
                  <l>Thy bloud <hi>Hydropicke</hi> thirſtines to breake,</l>
                  <l>The fatall bullet muſt impoiſ'ned be,</l>
                  <l>To wreake thy malice on mortalitie.</l>
                  <l>So that a wounded arme, a skarred thigh,</l>
                  <l>A pierced hand ſhall as for certaine die,</l>
                  <l>As if that hollow bloud conducting vaine</l>
                  <l>Some mortall hurt or dammage did ſuſtaine,</l>
                  <l>Or thoſe ſame cordiall ſtrings, which knit the life</l>
                  <l>Were ſundred quite by ſome <hi>Rauilliacks</hi> knife:</l>
                  <l>Were not O Rome thy<note place="margin">All theſe were notabletraitors</note> 
                     <hi>Gerrards, Lopes, Squires,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>Aſſaſsines,</hi> and fulminations fires,</l>
                  <l>Thy poyſnie ſimples fetcht from <hi>Concritan,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From <hi>Nubia, Tombut,</hi> and from <hi>Terminan,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From hot <hi>Cyrene,</hi> and that<note place="margin">Ponlus.</note> Eaſterne coaſte,</l>
                  <l>Whereon the roaring <hi>Ponticke</hi> ſeas are toſt,</l>
                  <l>Sufficient meanes to furniſh with ſupplie</l>
                  <l>The yawning gulfe of thy new Purgat'ry?</l>
                  <l>But that thy darling, and thy minion Spaine,</l>
                  <l>Thy ape of miſchiefe, muſt her honour ſtaine</l>
                  <l>Acquired by the fortune of faire Armes,</l>
                  <l>And blemiſh it with poyſon-contriud harmes.</l>
                  <l>But whilſt that my digreſſiue muſe thus fals</l>
                  <l>To this Inuectiue fit, the Cannon cals</l>
                  <l>Her wandring thoughts to <hi>Bergen</hi> whoſe loude ſound</l>
                  <l>From eu'rie platforme ecchoing doth rebounde</l>
                  <l>With greater noiſe, then when the<note place="margin">Two moſt furious batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſee the Turkiſh hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie pag 418. and pag. 584.</note> 
                     <hi>Scodran</hi> towers</l>
                  <l>Were batterd by the Barbr'ous Turkiſh powers,</l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:9596:27"/>
                  <l>Or When the <hi>Rhodian</hi> bulwarkes were defac'd</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Soliman,</hi> and all their glorie rac'd</l>
                  <l>Left nothing to the croſſed Chriſtian Knight,</l>
                  <l>But the ſad aſpecte of this diſmall ſight.</l>
                  <l>Our ordinance diſpoſ'd by <hi>Gibſons</hi> care,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe merit claimes an honourable ſhare</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Bergens</hi> ſafeguard, did the Spaniards plie</l>
                  <l>With frequent Peales of their Artillerie,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe leuelld ſhot vnto the foemen ſent,</l>
                  <l>Did Peecemeale <hi>Gabions,</hi> men and Rampiers rent;</l>
                  <l>And whilſt their bodies mounted, ſent their ſoules</l>
                  <l>To grieſly <hi>Plutoes</hi> darke Infernall hoales.</l>
                  <l>Some nine dayes after when the Chriſtall gate</l>
                  <l>Of that ſame day, which mortals conſecrate</l>
                  <l>To mightie <hi>Ioue,</hi> with ſhadie night was cloſ'd,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Companies of foote.</note>The <hi>Iberian Cohorts</hi> for the fight diſpoſ'd</l>
                  <l>By their Campemaſters, to the combat paſt,</l>
                  <l>Faſt in their orders, in their marching faſt:</l>
                  <l>Then hauing got the batterd Curtins baſe</l>
                  <l>They ſought to mount vpon that horneworks face,</l>
                  <l>Where<note place="margin">Colonell <hi>Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon</hi> a braue Scots man</note> 
                     <hi>Hinderſon</hi> with his, and our owne nation</l>
                  <l>Aranged ſtood in point of his owne ſtation.</l>
                  <l>The fight was cruell, doubtfull, full of blood,</l>
                  <l>Wherein <hi>Bellonaes</hi> Bridegroome wauering ſtood,</l>
                  <l>Vncertaine to which ſide the palme ſhould flie</l>
                  <l>To this of right, or that of Tyrannie.</l>
                  <l>For though the Spaniards chardgd, ours ſtill reſiſted</l>
                  <l>And though rechardgd, yet reſolute perſiſted</l>
                  <l>In their defence, vntill th' aſſaulting foe</l>
                  <l>His backe vnto th' <hi>Orangian</hi> troupes did ſhow.</l>
                  <l>But marke how fortune with her powerfull becke</l>
                  <l>As ſtepdame vnto valour giues the checke;</l>
                  <l>For although <hi>Hinderſon</hi> like<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Scaeua</hi> a vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunt Roman.</note> 
                     <hi>Scaeua</hi> ſtood.</l>
                  <l>Gainſt oppoſitions face, and ſtill made good</l>
                  <l>Th' ingaged place, yet one foule random ſhot</l>
                  <l>The conqueſt from this braue Commaunder got;</l>
                  <l>Which banefull pellet rob'd him of his breath,</l>
                  <l>Worthy to ſuruiue eu'n in the ſpight of death.</l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:9596:27"/>
                  <l>After this loſſe Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> ſends releefe</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Grauenweert,</hi> commaunded all in chiefe</l>
                  <l>By<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Charles Morgan</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell of a foote regiment vnder the States.</note> 
                     <hi>Morgan,</hi> who with winged meaſures ſpeedes</l>
                  <l>Vnto the towne, that now for ſuccour bleedes.</l>
                  <l>He wafting o're the diaprie-purled <hi>Waal,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From thence vnto ſwift <hi>Moſaes</hi> ſtreame doth fall,</l>
                  <l>And ſailing through that narrowe Midland ſea</l>
                  <l>Whoſe channell giues acceſſe to <hi>Bergens</hi> Kaye</l>
                  <l>Arriued at his chardge, and there propoſd</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Naſſawes</hi> orders, which being wel diſpoſ'd</l>
                  <l>By<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rihoue</hi> vvas gouernour of <hi>Bergen,</hi> and <hi>Fama</hi> was Colonell of a regiment of <hi>Wallons.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Rihoues</hi> counſell, and by <hi>Famaes</hi> care</l>
                  <l>From all aduauntage did th' aſſailants bare.</l>
                  <l>He skorning like ſome Frozen Flemiſh hulke</l>
                  <l>To lye ſhopt vp within the Rampiers bulke,</l>
                  <l>Giues life to action, through the poſterns Sallies</l>
                  <l>And though repulſt againe his ſquadrons rallies,</l>
                  <l>Vntill the vanquiſht foes of hope bereft</l>
                  <l>The deade halfe Moone vnto our Legions left.</l>
                  <l>Then reaſſaulting they forſooke th' aſſault,</l>
                  <l>Through our mens valour and their owne default;</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Morgan</hi> ſtill repells them with thick hailes</l>
                  <l>Of Muſket ſhot, with briſtled Iron flailes,</l>
                  <l>With ſmoaking wildefire balls, and blowne vp mines</l>
                  <l>Whoſe hollow vaults filld full with<note place="margin">
                        <p>An inſtrument made like a flaile to throw ouer the Rampier or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rapet vnto the Enemies.</p>
                        <p>Pouder that is vſd in mines or great ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
                        <p>The <hi>Wallons</hi> of the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricke of <hi>Leoge.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </note> Serpentine,</l>
                  <l>And taking fire by ſome ſulphureous traine</l>
                  <l>T'heauens with ſmoake, the land with bloud doth ſtaine.</l>
                  <l>On th' other ſide the Dutchmen taking heate</l>
                  <l>From our examples beames did brauely beate</l>
                  <l>The Spaniſh ſquadrons, which in ſucceſſe faild</l>
                  <l>As oft as they our horned wo kes aſſaild.</l>
                  <l>The like the Frenchmen did, and that ſtout nation</l>
                  <l>Which in rich <hi>Lukeland</hi> holds their habitation,</l>
                  <l>But then being ſubiect to <hi>Famaes</hi> commands</l>
                  <l>Imployed their ſeruice for the Netherlands.</l>
                  <l>In theſe conflicts braue <hi>Mountioy, Morgan, Gibſon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rich, Courtney, Conway, Halſewell, Hinderſon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cooke, Tibals, Pollard, Clarke</hi> and <hi>Killegree,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Knolles, Bacon, Turney, Kenniet horpe</hi> and <hi>Carey,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:9596:28"/>
                  <l>Shewed matchles valour, and deſerue to be</l>
                  <l>For this the children of Eternitie,</l>
                  <l>Being all ſelfe lauiſh of their deareſt bloud</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Bergens</hi> defence, and our vnions good.</l>
                  <l>Amongſt the liſt of the <hi>Philippicke</hi> bandes</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Blunt</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sergeant Maior <hi>Blunt.</hi>
                     </note> of his foes eu'n admired ſtands</l>
                  <l>Haples in this, that home-ſpunne diſcontents</l>
                  <l>Made him to follow Spaines ambitious bents.</l>
                  <l>In this meane time Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> hauing left</l>
                  <l>The diſunited vnion, and bereft</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">All the high <hi>Palatinate.</hi>
                     </note>Of all thoſe vpper Countries, where the Rhine.</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Neckars</hi> ſtreame his pearled ſtreames doth ioyne,</l>
                  <l>And all that fruitfull large-extended tract,</l>
                  <l>Which borders on the riuer, being ſackt</l>
                  <l>By both their Armies, and the pillagd Boore</l>
                  <l>Deſpoiled quite of all his former ſtore;</l>
                  <l>Which cluſter-crowned <hi>Bacchus</hi> did affoord,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Ceres</hi> yeeld from her all plenteous hoord.</l>
                  <l>The chardge of <hi>Manhein</hi> being giuen to <hi>Veare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Heidelberge</hi> deſignd to <hi>Herberts</hi> care,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Frankn'dale</hi> to <hi>Burrowes,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Almaine</hi> bands</l>
                  <l>Which ſtill ſtood firme to <hi>Fredericks</hi> commaunds,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">The <hi>Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</hi>
                     </note>His Excellence the <hi>Paltzian</hi> ſoile forſakes</l>
                  <l>In famous for our loſſes, and betakes</l>
                  <l>Himſelfe to that retraite, which crownd his name</l>
                  <l>With the triumphant wreaths of glorious fame.</l>
                  <l>Vnparralleld for conduct, and th' euent</l>
                  <l>Except by Conons worthie preſident:</l>
                  <l>Or that<note place="margin">Of theſe two retraites is mention made before. <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nophon.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Athenians,</hi> who from <hi>Elams</hi> hils</l>
                  <l>Retired to thoſe fields, which <hi>Phaſis</hi> fils,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Actaxerxes</hi> troupes his Armie chaſt</l>
                  <l>And for two thouſand miles his Legions fac'd,</l>
                  <l>For although <hi>Tilley</hi> reinforc'd with ayd</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">This relation I had from Sir <hi>Iames Rameſey</hi> who was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in all this ſeruice.</note>From all th'Imperiall circles, had forelayd</l>
                  <l>Thoſe paſſages, which giue a free acceſſe</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Almaine</hi> to the Frountring <hi>Lorraneffe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet the <hi>Mansfieldians</hi> hauing paſt the <hi>Sar</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Blieſſes</hi> ſtreames, (whoſe Chriſtall ſource from far</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:9596:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>Extracted, for diurnall tribute yeelds</l>
                  <l>His glaſsie purles to <hi>Lotharingiaes</hi> fields:)</l>
                  <l>Arriud at <hi>Sauerne,</hi> where<note place="margin">The Count <hi>Palatin.</hi>
                     </note> the <hi>Paltzian</hi> Prince</l>
                  <l>Giues the farewell to <hi>Mansfields</hi> Excellence,</l>
                  <l>And ſafe conuoyd through friendly <hi>Galliaes</hi> land</l>
                  <l>Imbarks himſelfe on the <hi>Caliſian</hi> ſtrande.</l>
                  <l>There hence our ſquadrons marcht into <hi>Lorraine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From whence the <hi>Guiſians</hi> claime their <hi>Origen;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And paſsing by that Frountiers Southerne ſide</l>
                  <l>Neere vnto which<note place="margin">A great riuer in <hi>Lorraine.</hi>
                     </note> Voloies current doth glide,</l>
                  <l>They doubled <hi>Mortaignes</hi> woods, <hi>Volgeſus</hi> Mountaine,</l>
                  <l>Fat <hi>Vaignies</hi> vallies, and the <hi>Moſells</hi> fountaine.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lottaringia</hi> or <hi>Lorraine</hi> tooke his name from one <hi>Lothari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> See <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator</hi> in his deſcription of it.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then leauing that <hi>Frauncelouing</hi> towenfull ſoile</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Lotharicke</hi> did with his name enſtile,</l>
                  <l>They bending Northwards, did their enſignes ſpreade</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Lutzenburge</hi> beyonde ſwift <hi>Semois</hi> heade</l>
                  <l>And came through many perils to <hi>Sedan,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Ducall</hi> ſeate of Princely <hi>Bullion:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where hauing well refreſht their pinching needes</l>
                  <l>And reſted ſome fewe dayes, their Armie ſpeedes</l>
                  <l>With running marches o'r the winding turnes</l>
                  <l>Of<note place="margin">Riuers which run through <hi>Namures.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Houle</hi> and <hi>Maſe,</hi> and that high mountains hornes</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Charlemont</hi> by <hi>Phillips</hi> Souldiers ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd</l>
                  <l>In view of <hi>Heinault</hi> and <hi>Namurs</hi> doth ſtand.</l>
                  <l>Then hauing through that territorie paſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>They layd the faire <hi>Namurcan Burrowes</hi> waſt</l>
                  <l>With fire, and ſword, and all thoſe hoſtile ills</l>
                  <l>Which hell with ſoules, the land with ſlaughter fills.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gonſaluo</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gonſaluo de Corduba</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the Spaniſh armed</note> mooued with theſe affrounting harmes</l>
                  <l>And iealous of his honour, forth with armes</l>
                  <l>With all thoſe <hi>Walloun</hi> bands, and Spaniſh legions,</l>
                  <l>Which quarterd lay within that <hi>Frountiers</hi> regions:</l>
                  <l>And taking the<note place="margin">The Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> Campaina, ſtraight forelayes</l>
                  <l>The crooked paſſage of thoſe broaken wayes,</l>
                  <l>Extended forth from <hi>Moſa</hi> to thoſe ſloughes,</l>
                  <l>Which the rich Femming and <hi>Brabanſon</hi> Plowes,</l>
                  <l>At Flourie neere <hi>Namurs</hi> he pitcht his Tents</l>
                  <l>With all the flower of his olde Regiments,</l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:9596:29"/>
                  <l>Whoſe Maniples computed by the liſt,</l>
                  <l>Of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u'nteene thouſand Souldiers did conſiſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Peazaunts</hi> of the Country.</note>And twentie thouſand Boores well armd with glaiues,</l>
                  <l>VVith Firelockes, and Herculean clublike ſtaues.</l>
                  <l>About the time, that bright <hi>Apollo</hi> ſteepes</l>
                  <l>His golden treſſes in th' <hi>Iberian</hi> deepes,</l>
                  <l>Counte <hi>Mansfield</hi> doth approach, and hauing ſpied</l>
                  <l>Their vaunt currours, vnto that hillocke hied,</l>
                  <l>Behinde whoſe couert all their Cohorts laye</l>
                  <l>To ſtop our march, and our battalions ſtay.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">There ran a little brooke betweene <hi>Man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>field</hi> and <hi>Corduba.</hi>
                     </note>Then wading through the flagge oreſhaded brookes</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Meander</hi> wiſe retorted turning nookes,</l>
                  <l>Vpon the farther ſide he makes a ſtand</l>
                  <l>And to <hi>Gonſaluo</hi> tenders this demaund.</l>
                  <l>Whether his valour were reſolud to fight</l>
                  <l>Vpon th' appearaunce of the morning light.</l>
                  <l>Or that his patience would giue parting leaue,</l>
                  <l>And ſo the webbe of both their ſafeties weaue.</l>
                  <l>The Corduban thus ſummond, thus replies:</l>
                  <l>Thinkes the <hi>Bohemian</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mansfield</hi> was Marſhall of <hi>Bohemia</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was Generall.</note> Marſhall to ſurpriſe</l>
                  <l>My wiſdome with his words? and curbe my ſprite</l>
                  <l>Lauiſh in this to doe my ſoueraigne right?</l>
                  <l>Can he conceiue his Legions ſhall depart?</l>
                  <l>Who thus haue torne th' Imperiall Eagles heart,</l>
                  <l>Deſpoild our veſtall Nuns, ranſackt our Friers,</l>
                  <l>And crammd themſelues with pillagd <hi>Ments</hi> and <hi>Triers;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He muſt account for all <hi>Bohemiaes</hi> ſpoile.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">At <hi>Hagenawe</hi> &amp; <hi>Heſeldorffe</hi> the Count ouerthrew th'Imperialls.</note>For t' <hi>Hagenawne,</hi> and <hi>Heſeldorffian</hi> foile,</l>
                  <l>Before he can our ſafeconduct obtaine,</l>
                  <l>And free aduenue into <hi>Brabant</hi> gaine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bohemiaes</hi> Gen'rall warmd with this replie;</l>
                  <l>Doth all the bent of his deuoirs applie</l>
                  <l>To croſſe their proiects, and with <hi>Linxean</hi> eyes</l>
                  <l>Vnto the depth of each aduauntage pries,</l>
                  <l>By which he might his <hi>Phalangiers</hi> defend,</l>
                  <l>And great <hi>Gonſaluos</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Regiment is a number of foote con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of more or leſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies.</note> Regiments offend.</l>
                  <l>He ſtraight commaunds his Cohorts all to lye</l>
                  <l>Armd and vnarmd, horſe and Infanterie</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:9596:29"/>
                  <l>That night in battell ray, behind that hill</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Southerne brow our Maniples did fill,</l>
                  <l>Vpon the morne when <hi>Sols</hi> irradiant light</l>
                  <l>Had rent the vaile of Sable coulered night,</l>
                  <l>He marſhalls his diuiſions, viewes their ranckes,</l>
                  <l>Suruaies all parts, both Vangard, Reare and flanks,</l>
                  <l>Giues motiues to their mettall, and doth cheare</l>
                  <l>Their wauering minds againſt the bugs of feare.</l>
                  <l>Theſe are, quoth he, thoſe feeble beaten bands,</l>
                  <l>So often foild by your victorious hands,</l>
                  <l>The reliques of the <hi>Leopoldian</hi> hoaſte,</l>
                  <l>And of thoſe Tertioes, which their honour loſt</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Heſeldorffe,</hi> when our men did defeate</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bauariaes</hi> Gen'rall and their Armie beate.</l>
                  <l>The reſt are <hi>Peazaunts</hi> rude,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Landeſdayes</hi> are dayes of ſolemne meeting.</note> vplandiſh Boores</l>
                  <l>Acquainted better with their <hi>Landeſdayes</hi> ſturres</l>
                  <l>With taphouſe quarrels, alefomented broiles,</l>
                  <l>Then with <hi>Bellonaes Hazardes</hi> or her toyles.</l>
                  <l>We are thoſe men, who haue <hi>Bohemia</hi> ſackt,</l>
                  <l>Conquerd<note place="margin">Three ſtrong townes in <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Prachadis, Pilſen</hi> and <hi>Piſacke</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Haue ſtroue with natures threats, with dangers dread,</l>
                  <l>And through their ſence afflicting terrours ſped</l>
                  <l>Vnto this bedde of fame, where we muſt fight</l>
                  <l>Or elſe our honourd liues abandon quite.</l>
                  <l>Behind vs lies<note place="margin">A high moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>olgeſus</hi> creſted ridge,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sambre</hi> before vnpaſſable by bridge,</l>
                  <l>Vpon the right hand runs the roaring Maſe,</l>
                  <l>Vpon the left, great <hi>Corduba</hi> doth face</l>
                  <l>Our armd battalions, ſo that we muſt die.</l>
                  <l>Or gaine our ſelues by glorious victorie.</l>
                  <l>All like this, but two thouſand mutineers,</l>
                  <l>Who making pay the ſhadow of their feares,</l>
                  <l>Diſlike their Gen'ralls motion and refuſe</l>
                  <l>T'ingage themſelues for his imploiments vſe.</l>
                  <l>The valiant Count on point of ſeruice ſet</l>
                  <l>With this refuſall mou'd doth ſtorming fret:</l>
                  <l>As when a retriud <hi>Partridge</hi> mounts the skie</l>
                  <l>Some Fauckener lets a caſt of Marlins flie</l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:9596:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>Whereof that makes it home, but this doth faile</l>
                  <l>And Caſtrell-like doth poorely turne her taile.</l>
                  <l>The Fawkner marking from ſome loftie tree,</l>
                  <l>The ſadde diſaſter of this ſport doth ſee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>And with ſterne words thats cowardiſe doth rate,</l>
                  <l>But cheeres the mettall of her ſoaring mate,</l>
                  <l>He chides them firſt, then ſeekes to mooue their hearts,</l>
                  <l>With melting flakes of his perſuaſiue arts;</l>
                  <l>He tells them, what diſhonour tweare, what ſhame</l>
                  <l>Vnto the luſter of the <hi>German</hi> name,</l>
                  <l>Thus to forſake themſelues, their friends, their chiefe,</l>
                  <l>And ſequeſtrate the meanes of their releefe.</l>
                  <l>He ſhewes that theſe were not their ſolemne vowes</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Manheim</hi> made, when they did there eſpouſe</l>
                  <l>Their lifes to's ſeruice, and obligd by oath</l>
                  <l>Againſt the Spaniards and Imperialls both,</l>
                  <l>Did freelie promiſe neuer to forſake</l>
                  <l>His Princely colours, but to vndertake</l>
                  <l>The ſhare of all aduentures, till the date</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">The free ſtate of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands.</hi>
                     </note>Expired were, for which the <hi>Cantond</hi> ſtate</l>
                  <l>Of Holland had their Legions entertaind,</l>
                  <l>Neuer before with diſobedience ſtaind.</l>
                  <l>But all theſe words like fuell did encreaſe</l>
                  <l>The raging fire of their ſtiffe ſtubbornes,</l>
                  <l>Wherefore he leaues this plot, and doth intreate</l>
                  <l>That if they would not fight, they would retreate</l>
                  <l>Or els aduaunce themſelues, and make a ſtand</l>
                  <l>Vpon that place, where he ſhould giue commaund.</l>
                  <l>This laſt being graunted, he doth ſtraight inlarge</l>
                  <l>The Frount of his battalions, and doth chardge;</l>
                  <l>As when ſome raine-engendred Torrents ſhocke</l>
                  <l>Both beate vpon an adamantine rocke.</l>
                  <l>Or when ſome ſulphrous fulminations fire</l>
                  <l>Lights on the creſt of ſome piramide Spire</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Bombards</hi> firſt did with their <hi>Torlin</hi> play,</l>
                  <l>And hundreds ſlaine vpon the Champion lay,</l>
                  <l>The bullet furrowed fielde with ſhot ſowen</l>
                  <l>And all the plaine with batterd Corſlets ſtrowen.</l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:9596:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>Then their<note place="margin">Looſe wings which begin the fight.</note> Forlorne death deſtined hope</l>
                  <l>With our looſe wings of Muſkettiers doth coope,</l>
                  <l>The lighthorſe failing fowle on both the flankes</l>
                  <l>Do chardge, and wheele, and wheeling change their rankes</l>
                  <l>The Muſkettiers from either ſide do poure</l>
                  <l>Of palefac'd bullets a death ſtorming ſhower</l>
                  <l>The Pikemen puſh, and puſhing with their Pike</l>
                  <l>Through maild habergeons, helmes and Corſlets ſtrike.</l>
                  <l>Foote ſtickes to foote, and hand doth gripe with hand</l>
                  <l>Each Frounter with his Frounter next doth bande:</l>
                  <l>With ſtreames of bloud the bloudie greene doth ſmoake,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe vapour tooke foment with eu'rie ſtroake.</l>
                  <l>Our Curaciers by valiaunt<note place="margin">Otherwiſe calld the Biſhop of <hi>Halberſhat</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> led</l>
                  <l>The laſt of all vnto this combat ſped</l>
                  <l>Whoſe footeſteps dread and danger did attend,</l>
                  <l>Wherſoeuer they did with their Cornets wend.</l>
                  <l>Heere a braue Souldier wounded with a bruiſe</l>
                  <l>Through th' orifice his fleeting ſoule out ſpues,</l>
                  <l>Heere a ſure Gunner ſhot off by the knees</l>
                  <l>Liues vpward, whilſt the nether fragment ſteeues.</l>
                  <l>Heere a man-woman <hi>Amazonian</hi> dame</l>
                  <l>A <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>otareſſe</hi> to <hi>Mars,</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> game</l>
                  <l>Shot neere her friend in his imbracements dies,</l>
                  <l>And liuing dying thus doth ſimpathize.</l>
                  <l>But in the midſt of this tumultuous broile</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> though ſhot out braueth feare and toile,</l>
                  <l>Both chardge and rechardge, fals on Frount and flancke,</l>
                  <l>Sometimes by file ſometimes giuing in by rancke.</l>
                  <l>From morne till noone this dreadfull fight did laſt,</l>
                  <l>But when<note place="margin">It was a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after mid day.</note> the ſunne had the Meridian paſt</l>
                  <l>Some thirtie minutes, all things being confuſd,</l>
                  <l>The Spainſh vanguard broake, their Chiefe amuſd</l>
                  <l>With our mens courage; <hi>Mansfield</hi> then appeares</l>
                  <l>More then himſelfe, and thus inflaming cheeres.</l>
                  <l>His laſt reſerue: come on, keene vp your ſpite</l>
                  <l>Againſt theſe Barbr'ous Demimoores deſpite;</l>
                  <l>Breake through the Frount of that halfe broaken troupe</l>
                  <l>And make their ſtiffnes to your valour ſtoope,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9596:31"/>
                  <l>With your well pointed blades hew out your way</l>
                  <l>Through their battalions which your courſe forelay.</l>
                  <l>No ſooner ſayd but done, for forth they ruſh,</l>
                  <l>And like ſome winter ſtorme do downe right puſh</l>
                  <l>All that's oppoſd, and rowting file by file</l>
                  <l>Rancke after rancke they paſſe that iron toyle</l>
                  <l>Vnto the ſtation of our mutineers,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe wauering fills both ſides with iealous feares.</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Corduba</hi> ſurmiſing that they lay</l>
                  <l>For a reſerue, his laſt purſuite to ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Durſt not ingage his ouertired bande,</l>
                  <l>But on the place of battaile kept his ſtand.</l>
                  <l>The loſſe was not vnlike; foure thouſand ſlaine</l>
                  <l>Of either ſide the Champions browe did ſtaine</l>
                  <l>VVith Purple ſtreames of their vermilion bloud</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe <hi>Rubie</hi> congeald on th' Earths ſurface ſtood.</l>
                  <l>Amongſt this honourd liſt ſtout <hi>Weimars</hi> Duke,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Rougiere</hi> their fatall deaths wound tooke</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mengeſheim</hi> was ta'en, and <hi>Brunſwickes</hi> arme was ſhot</l>
                  <l>VVho loſt his hand whilſt he the lawrell got.</l>
                  <l>This conflict being paſt, the Count doth march</l>
                  <l>(Mounted vpon a rich triumphant Arche)</l>
                  <l>Ouer the<note place="margin">A riuer which runneth into the <hi>Maſe.</hi> The Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Sambre,</hi> vanquiſheth the Boores,</l>
                  <l>Paſſeth through <hi>Brabant,</hi> ioyneth there his powers</l>
                  <l>Neere <hi>Roſendale</hi> with the<note place="margin">A riuer which runneth into the <hi>Maſe.</hi> The Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Naſſauian</hi> Graue,</l>
                  <l>Both being reſolud thin'gaged towne to ſaue</l>
                  <l>From the <hi>Caſtilians,</hi> who with might and maine</l>
                  <l>Applied the ſiege <hi>Bergen-opzom</hi> to gaine.</l>
                  <l>Fame bruiting this with her ſhrill Sounding winde</l>
                  <l>VVith iealous feares fils the Marqueſſes minde;</l>
                  <l>VVho doubting that both Armies might Surpriſe,</l>
                  <l>His paſſage vnto <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> ſtraight doth riſe</l>
                  <l>With all his<note place="margin">Regiments.</note> 
                     <hi>Tertioes,</hi> and to <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulcan</hi> turnes</l>
                  <l>His ſtrawe built ſtation, which inflamed burnes</l>
                  <l>The large extent of that well fenced frame,</l>
                  <l>Ere our <hi>Bergheneers</hi> to the pillage came.</l>
                  <l>But what <hi>Toledoes</hi> wiles,<note place="margin">The Prince of <hi>Parma.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Farnezes</hi> might,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gonſaluoes</hi> power, nor <hi>Spinolaes</hi> deſpite</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9596:31"/>
                  <l>Could not effect; for nine times ſeuen yeares</l>
                  <l>Againſt the fortune of the <hi>Belgian</hi> Peeres;</l>
                  <l>Home-ſpunne Sedition, if not croſt by Fate,</l>
                  <l>Was like to worke againſt our Vnions State.</l>
                  <l>This faction firſt was leauen'd by the ſower</l>
                  <l>Of call'd <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> whoſe clowdie ſhower</l>
                  <l>Seem'd to deface the cleare irradiant Sunne</l>
                  <l>Of reform'd Truth, which on theſe Regions ſhone.</l>
                  <l>New Sectaries theſe Rudiments did varniſh</l>
                  <l>With freſh additions, and did fairely garniſh</l>
                  <l>The Frontiſpice of that halfe rotten houſe,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Architecture did the ſoules amuſe</l>
                  <l>Of ſundry <hi>Belgians,</hi> which for ſhelter came</l>
                  <l>To this faire-ſeeming ſcarce ſubſtantiall frame.</l>
                  <l>This diffrence in Religion cauſ'd another</l>
                  <l>Diffrence in Faction, which th' <hi>Arminians</hi> ſmother</l>
                  <l>For ſelfe-behoouing reaſons, till the State</l>
                  <l>Was manag'd by t' <hi>Hollandiſh</hi> Aduocate,</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Barneuelt,</hi> a Paragon for wit,</l>
                  <l>For faction, greatneſſe, which entirely knit,</l>
                  <l>And linkt to's fortunes, were the golden bayts</l>
                  <l>That caught Plebeian minds with fond deceits:</l>
                  <l>He vaſſal'd as the rumour ſaith, to <hi>Spaine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Enuious to <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> couetous to gaine,</l>
                  <l>And ſpheare within his reaches that command,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Maurice</hi> held with his victorious hand;</l>
                  <l>Appalls the multitude with iealous feares,</l>
                  <l>With tickling rumours fills the glowing eares</l>
                  <l>Of his Aſſociates, tells them that t'indure</l>
                  <l>The proud <hi>Naſſauians</hi> yoake, and their grandeur,</l>
                  <l>Were to proiect their freedomes, and themſelues</l>
                  <l>Againſt the ridge of thoſe Monarchicke ſhelues,</l>
                  <l>Which mightie<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Philip</hi> the 2. King of <hi>Spaine</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Philip</hi> raiſed at the firſt,</l>
                  <l>To quench his vaſt ambitions Dropſie thirſt.</l>
                  <l>Beſides it were againſt the ſacred Lawes</l>
                  <l>Of God and Nature, to forſake the Cauſe</l>
                  <l>Of their Religion, which b' <hi>Arminius</hi> ſpred,</l>
                  <l>And replanted in <hi>Hollands</hi> fruitfull bed,</l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:9596:32"/>
                  <l>By his Diſciples, now deſpiſ'd, abiect,</l>
                  <l>VVas eu'n ſuppreſt by the <hi>Caluinian</hi> Sect.</l>
                  <l>Thus Policie ioynd with Religion ſhrowdes</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Barneueltine</hi> plots, and like thoſe cloudes,</l>
                  <l>Where a Parelion ſits, deceiues the ſight</l>
                  <l>Of raſh beholders with their ſpecious light.</l>
                  <l>But O diuine Religion, why ſhouldſt thou</l>
                  <l>To mens deſignes; nay, palliations bow?</l>
                  <l>O why ſhouldſt thou, whoſe radiant treſſes chaine</l>
                  <l>God vnto man, and man to God againe?</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould thy Name ineffable, diuine,</l>
                  <l>Zeales Cabinet, and pure Deuotions ſhrine,</l>
                  <l>Bee made a ſtale to all the blacke intents</l>
                  <l>Of humane proiects? and the bloody bents</l>
                  <l>Of their pretences, who pretending right,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Nimrods</hi> proud againſt thy Scepter fight.</l>
                  <l>So that there liues not that damn'd<note place="margin">A damned Murtherer.</note> 
                     <hi>Aſſaſſine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor that vnloyall loyalliz'd <hi>Ignatian;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not that <hi>Rauilliac,</hi> whoſe death poynted knife</l>
                  <l>Deſpoyl'd the braue<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. <hi>Gerard,</hi> who kild the prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Nauarrois</hi> of his life;</l>
                  <l>Not that<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. <hi>Gerard,</hi> who kild the prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Burgundian</hi> Murderer, that <hi>Squire,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor that <hi>Lopes,</hi> but drawes the twiſted wire</l>
                  <l>Of his ranke Treaſons from the faire pretence</l>
                  <l>Of gloz'd Religion, though his ſenſeleſſe ſenſe,</l>
                  <l>Right<note place="margin">Thoſe that haue the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexie,</hi> are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible.</note> Apoplecticke-like ne're feeles the motion</l>
                  <l>Of pietie, nor zealous true deuotion.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Barneuelt</hi> ſuppreſt, his faction quell'd,</l>
                  <l>His popular Colloſsicke props downe fell'd,</l>
                  <l>The Lernean Head of that rebellious rout</l>
                  <l>Being ſundred quite, whoſe falſehood went about</l>
                  <l>To ſubiugate the Netherlands againe</l>
                  <l>Vnto the rule of rule-deſiring <hi>Spaine.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Some few yeares after, this ſeditious crue</l>
                  <l>Makes head againe, and freſhly doth purſue</l>
                  <l>Their ancient quarrell, whoſe proiected bent</l>
                  <l>Fuell'd with malice, fedde with diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>Intends the wracke of the <hi>Naſſauian</hi> race.</l>
                  <l>But in their weales weale-publike to deface.</l>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:9596:32"/>
                  <l>There want not <hi>Catilines;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>The names of theſe 4. were</hi> Cor. Gerritzon Her. Herman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Iohn Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, Theodorick Leonardſon.</note> rich <hi>Harlem</hi> ſends</l>
                  <l>From cold North-<hi>Hollands</hi> Froſt congealed ends,</l>
                  <l>Foure Climate differing Sprites, inflam'd with fire</l>
                  <l>Of light Ambition, Soueraignties deſire,</l>
                  <l>With Enuie, and Reuenge, whoſe fuming terrours</l>
                  <l>Diſtract their ſoules into a maze of errours.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Barneuelts</hi> two ſonnes, winde vp the clue</l>
                  <l>Of all their doubts, and to their faction skrew</l>
                  <l>Other Aſſociates, in which damned Liſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Daniel Slatius <hi>an</hi> Arminian <hi>Preacher.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Slatius</hi> hath not the meaneſt Intereſt,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Cornewinder,</hi> and <hi>Adrian van Deicks,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whom blinde fold zeale to falſe rebellion pricks.</l>
                  <l>Thus was the plot; foure Aſſaſsines deſignd</l>
                  <l>For this blacke deed, were ſolemnly combind</l>
                  <l>By mutuall vowes, and interchanged oathes,</l>
                  <l>Which bluſhing <hi>Sol,</hi> and palefac'd <hi>Cinthia</hi> loathes)</l>
                  <l>To Piſtoll <hi>Maurice, Henricke,</hi> and the reſt</l>
                  <l>Of the <hi>Naſſauian</hi> ſtocke; this being confeſt</l>
                  <l>By two Conſpirators, the Prince ſtraight hies</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Riſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>wicke</hi> to the <hi>Hague,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Riſwicke,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Dorpe neere to the <hi>Hague.</hi>
                     </note> and there deſcries</l>
                  <l>In an <hi>Arminian</hi> houſe foure of this crue,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe malice did great <hi>Naſſaws</hi> death purſue.</l>
                  <l>All theſe were ſeiz'd by the<note place="margin">The Prince of <hi>Oranges</hi> guard</note> 
                     <hi>Pretorian</hi> band,</l>
                  <l>Impriſon'd, arraign'd, and by the powerfull hand</l>
                  <l>Of right-diuiding Iuſtice put to death,</l>
                  <l>As men vnworthie to vſurpe that breath,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe rancour had conſpir'd their Countries ſacke,</l>
                  <l>State-alteration, and religions wracke.</l>
                  <l>Such was the doome of <hi>Slatius,</hi> ſuch the lot</l>
                  <l>Of young <hi>Barneuelt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A ſmal harbor within a mile of the <hi>Hague.</hi>
                     </note> who to <hi>Scheueling</hi> got</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Laruates</hi> his viſage, doth his name exchange,</l>
                  <l>And in a Skippers habite ſeekes to range</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Holland</hi> to the rich <hi>Hamburgers</hi> Seat,</l>
                  <l>Againſt whoſe walls the billowing <hi>Elbe</hi> doth beat.</l>
                  <l>But found at <hi>Scheueling</hi> by the curious eyes</l>
                  <l>Of publike ſearch, hee for this Treaſon dies,</l>
                  <l>For what reward can Treaſon elſe expect,</l>
                  <l>But puniſhment, and rigours worſt effect?</l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:9596:33"/>
                  <l>But t'other of the ſonnes comes fairer off,</l>
                  <l>Who paſsing by the <hi>Geldrians</hi> vnto<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Goffe,</hi> a towne <hi>Cleeueland,</hi> as then vnder the king of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Goffe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There ſaues himſelfe, and pentioneerd to <hi>Spaine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>New proiects of reuenge doth entertaine,</l>
                  <l>Hoping his Sires and Brothers death to quite,</l>
                  <l>Wrought as he ſayes by the <hi>Naſſauians</hi> ſpite.</l>
                  <l>The Winter paſt in tortures, Aprill ſmiles</l>
                  <l>To ſee the labour'd preparations toyles,</l>
                  <l>Which both ſides take, t'enrich the colder earth</l>
                  <l>With ſtreames of blood, whoſe forc't abortiue birth</l>
                  <l>With Ruby-colourd Roſes decks the fields</l>
                  <l>Of rich <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> which that<note place="margin">The Biſhop of <hi>Colen,</hi> who is alſo Biſhop of <hi>Munſter</hi> and <hi>Leege.</hi>
                     </note> Biſhop weelds,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe triple-Mitred power, whoſe dreadfull awe</l>
                  <l>To all th' inferiour Circles giues the Lawe,</l>
                  <l>Supported by the <hi>Popes,</hi> and <hi>Caeſars</hi> grace,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Bauier,</hi> and potent <hi>Auſtriaes</hi> race.</l>
                  <l>Hee proud of theſe ſupports, and of that ayd</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Leege</hi> and <hi>Munſter</hi> ſends, had ſtrongly ſtayd</l>
                  <l>The current of our Vnion; and deuoted</l>
                  <l>Vnto the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> had Clerke-like quoted</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Machiuillian</hi> Index, for the ſhifts</l>
                  <l>Of policies, and falſe evaſiue drifts.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> inflam'd with this proud Prelats wrongs,</l>
                  <l>To reuenge which his boyling ſpirit longs;</l>
                  <l>Abandoneth his former wintring place,</l>
                  <l>Repaſſeth <hi>Ems,</hi> and cleare <hi>Viſurgis</hi> face.</l>
                  <l>Then ranſacking the cramm'd <hi>Weſtphalian</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Two great ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers in <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalia.</hi>
                     </note> Dorps,</l>
                  <l>With their releefe he feeds the Souldiers corps.</l>
                  <l>Strong was his Armie, numerous and faire,</l>
                  <l>Which breathed nought but hop'd <hi>Victoriaes</hi> ayre:</l>
                  <l>For now beſides his old well-trained Bands,</l>
                  <l>Which wintred in the <hi>Paterbornian</hi> lands;</l>
                  <l>New reinforcements warlike <hi>Haſsia</hi> ſends</l>
                  <l>From flaggie<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fulde</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> two riuers of <hi>Heſſen.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Fuldes,</hi> and <hi>Eders</hi> rouling bends.</l>
                  <l>The like the <hi>Saxon</hi> doth from thoſe cold hills,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Snow-bred torrent <hi>Albis</hi> channell fills.</l>
                  <l>Thus did the <hi>Rhinegraue;</hi> thus did <hi>Loueſtein,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Altenburg, Weimer, Schlic,</hi> and <hi>Vitgeinſtein,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:9596:33"/>
                  <l>All Collonels of thoſe farre-feared Legions,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> raiſed in theſe vpper Regions.</l>
                  <l>Th' Imperials were not for their number equall,</l>
                  <l>But paſsing our <hi>Beſonian</hi> Bands in mettall,</l>
                  <l>Conſiſting of thoſe Cohorts which <hi>Mortaigne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Truchſes</hi> led, and <hi>Dane</hi> alyed <hi>Holſteine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of the <hi>Croatian</hi> Horſe which <hi>Anhalt</hi> brought,</l>
                  <l>Of late vnto the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> faction wrought,</l>
                  <l>Of the <hi>Calabrian</hi> Bands, and of that force</l>
                  <l>VVhich<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Paulus</hi> the Pope ſent ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours to the Emperour in theſe warres.</note> 
                     <hi>Paulus</hi> ſent from <hi>Tibers</hi> ſandy ſource.</l>
                  <l>About the time that <hi>Munſters</hi> wealthy Boore,</l>
                  <l>VVith <hi>Ceres</hi> fruits renewd his former ſtore,</l>
                  <l>VVhen <hi>Maurice</hi> lay within faire <hi>Arnhams</hi> walls,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Mansfield</hi> lodg'd neere to ſwift <hi>Emſes</hi> falls:</l>
                  <l>The Duke to <hi>Statloo</hi> came, and on the bankes</l>
                  <l>Of<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Honnor</hi> is a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalia,</hi> which runs neere to <hi>Statloo,</hi> the place where the battell was fought. Are <hi>Croatian</hi> Horſmen.</note> 
                     <hi>Honner</hi> quarterd falſe <hi>Criphauſens</hi> rankes,</l>
                  <l>To make that paſſage good againſt the foe,</l>
                  <l>VVhich neere to <hi>Vulten</hi> did their Enſignes ſhow.</l>
                  <l>But hee being hooked by the golden bayt</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Tilleys</hi> promiſes, forſaketh ſtraight</l>
                  <l>The place of his Command, which <hi>Tilley</hi> taketh</l>
                  <l>VVith his<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Honnor</hi> is a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalia,</hi> which runs neere to <hi>Statloo,</hi> the place where the battell was fought. Are <hi>Croatian</hi> Horſmen.</note> 
                     <hi>Crabats,</hi> and from that Station maketh</l>
                  <l>To the <hi>Brunſwican</hi> Vanguard, which being charg'd,</l>
                  <l>At firſt acquitted well, and well diſcharg'd</l>
                  <l>Their Martiall duties; but at length being preſt</l>
                  <l>By the <hi>Croatian Rutters,</hi> which addreſt</l>
                  <l>Themſelues to their encounter, they forſooke</l>
                  <l>The bloody Combate, and themſelues betooke</l>
                  <l>To a diſhonour'd flight, which <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> ſeekes</l>
                  <l>To ſtop with blowes and words, but ſtill he meets</l>
                  <l>Thoſe fearefull buggs, which cowards ſoules affright,</l>
                  <l>VVho rather choſe to die, then liue to fight.</l>
                  <l>Are theſe, quoth hee, the ſolemne Ale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bench braues,</l>
                  <l>Made by theſe lumpes of clay, theſe ſodden ſlaues?</l>
                  <l>VVho when they were but tickled with the heat</l>
                  <l>Of ſulphrous Rheniſh, would whole Armies beat,</l>
                  <l>Would quarter Gen'rall <hi>Tilley,</hi> lard his heart</l>
                  <l>With points of ſteeled Pikes, t'auenge the ſmart</l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:9596:34"/>
                  <l>Done to my couſin <hi>Fredericke,</hi> and his Queene,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Ferdinands,</hi> and <hi>Philips</hi> mortall ſpleene.</l>
                  <l>But now being ſet vpon their Fortunes trialls,</l>
                  <l>They proue but hollow caskes, but emptie vials,</l>
                  <l>Big ſpeaking puffers, glorious of their words,</l>
                  <l>But Iades and daſtards, weaklings with their ſwords.</l>
                  <l>Fie, fie for ſhame, leaue off to runne and rout,</l>
                  <l>Rally<note place="margin">Rally, is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, or bring in order a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</note> your ſelues, and face it once about,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhall you ſee the God of Battels ſmile,</l>
                  <l>And vanquiſhers th' Imperiall Eagles foyle.</l>
                  <l>But maugre all theſe words<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they rout and runne,</l>
                  <l>As when ſome horned heard the hounds doth ſhunne.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">A ſmall towne vnder the States, which lay two leagues off.</note>They flie towards <hi>Breafort,</hi> whom the fierce <hi>Crabats</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Purſue, and ſtrike downe with the thundring claps</l>
                  <l>Of their <hi>Carbins,</hi> ſo that for two leagues ſpace,</l>
                  <l>You could ſee nought vpon the Champions face</l>
                  <l>But carnage of mankind, but Corſlets ſtrowen,</l>
                  <l>But poynts of Pikes, of Swords, and Halberts ſowen.</l>
                  <l>Two hundred foes were kill'd, two thouſand ſlaine</l>
                  <l>Of the <hi>Brunſwicans,</hi> and fiue thouſand ra'en</l>
                  <l>With ſpoyles, and Honour crowned <hi>Tilleys</hi> hoaſt;</l>
                  <l>But that which did inlarge their glory hoaſt;</l>
                  <l>Was their compaſsion, and their mercie knowne</l>
                  <l>Vnto the captiue <hi>Halberſtadians</hi> ſhowne.</l>
                  <l>After the fortune of this battell paſt,</l>
                  <l>By Treaſon, and our Souldiers rawneſſe loſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> retires with his halfe-broken Band</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Confines of fat <hi>Gelderland;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where entertaining, all the choſen beſt</l>
                  <l>For the State-Seruice, he caſhieres the reſt</l>
                  <l>Of that defeated ſelfe-betraying rabble,</l>
                  <l>Whom cowardiſe, or ſickneſſe made vnable</l>
                  <l>To follow his deſignes, whoſe Verge ſtill bends</l>
                  <l>To croſſe the Spaniſh and Imperiall ends.</l>
                  <l>Foure times from this had <hi>Cinthia</hi> cloſ'd her hornes,</l>
                  <l>And foure times runne compleat her menſtruall turnes,</l>
                  <l>When neere Decembers laſt, t'<hi>Hollandiſh</hi> Fleet</l>
                  <l>Bound for <hi>Braſill,</hi> commanded were to meet,</l>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:9596:34"/>
                  <l>If tempeſt ſcatterd, neere that necke of land,</l>
                  <l>Where Sugar rich Saint <hi>Saluador</hi> doth ſtand.</l>
                  <l>They from the<note place="margin">The Hauen of <hi>Amſterdam.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Texell</hi> looſing, plow'd thoſe waues,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe curled ſurge great <hi>Brittaines</hi> Foreland laues.</l>
                  <l>Then paſsing by rich <hi>Lisbornes</hi> foamie Bay,</l>
                  <l>And the <hi>Terceraes,</hi> they thence made away</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Teneriffaes Pike,</hi> and that deepe ſound,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Neptunes</hi> tumbling billowes doe rebound</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Gambra, Melli,</hi> and that Sunburnt ſhore,<note place="margin">Countries i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Affricke.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whence <hi>Ginee</hi> ſends her Idolized Oare.</l>
                  <l>Then ſayling Weſt Southweſt they paſt the mouth</l>
                  <l>Of<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Maragnon</hi> is a Riuer, which boundeth <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilia</hi> to the Northward,</note> 
                     <hi>Maragnon,</hi> and bending further South,</l>
                  <l>They coaſted all along that beachie Strand,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe checker borders faire <hi>Braſiliaes</hi> Land.</l>
                  <l>Heere from th' <hi>Aeolian</hi> wind out-belching cell</l>
                  <l>The God of ſtormes ſent forth a tempeſt fell</l>
                  <l>Vpon the <hi>Dutch,</hi> which did their Galeouns beat,</l>
                  <l>And ſep'rated their Sea-commanding Fleet.</l>
                  <l>So that e're <hi>Willecks</hi> came, mine<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Maragnon</hi> is a Riuer, which boundeth <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilia</hi> to the Northward,</note> 
                     <hi>Here van Dort,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Arriued in <hi>Los Sanctos</hi> ſpacious Port,</l>
                  <l>Who thundring with his Cannon, giues th' Alarme,</l>
                  <l>And makes the<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Willecks</hi> was Admirall, and my Lo. of <hi>Dort</hi> commanded fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the land. <hi>Negroes.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Blackes,</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> all to arme.</l>
                  <l>Then backe he falls into the watrie Maine,</l>
                  <l>To ſeeke out <hi>Hollands</hi> Admirall againe.</l>
                  <l>Three times the Sunne had dipt his <hi>Phlegons</hi> feet,</l>
                  <l>And cool'd his Paſterns in the weſterne deepe;</l>
                  <l>When that farre famed <hi>Tiphis</hi> of aduenture</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Willeks,</hi> doth with all his Squadron enter</l>
                  <l>The foamie mouth of the <hi>Braſilian</hi> Bay,</l>
                  <l>And within diſtance of their Platformes lay:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Canoniers our moared Galeouns plie</l>
                  <l>With roaring peales of their Artillery;</l>
                  <l>Theſe anſwere them from t'high and lower Tires,</l>
                  <l>With<note place="margin">With vollies of ſhot returnd againe.</note> reuolets of their <hi>Promethean</hi> fires.</l>
                  <l>This ſalutation paſt, he ſtraight reſolues</l>
                  <l>To land his Troupes, and ſeriouſly reſolues</l>
                  <l>Each aduantageous courſe, no forme, no ſhape</l>
                  <l>Of what exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dient was, could once eſcape</l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:9596:35"/>
                  <l>His pondrous thoughts, for knowing words to be</l>
                  <l>The ſolacers of feares infirmitie;</l>
                  <l>He thus inflames, thus comforts, thus exhorts</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Hollanders:</hi> Come on my braue Conſorts,</l>
                  <l>Heere's honour, riches, profit, and what not</l>
                  <l>VVithin <hi>Saluador</hi> to bee loſt, or got;</l>
                  <l>Heere are thoſe Ingots rich, thoſe precious graines,</l>
                  <l>Which<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reall,</hi> a Riuer which borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <hi>Braſill</hi> to the Southward</note> 
                     <hi>Reall</hi> waſheth from the mountaines vaines;</l>
                  <l>Heere is that Oare, for which the Negro ſlaues</l>
                  <l>Vnlocke the cloſets of th'Infernall caues,</l>
                  <l>Kept by theſe meagre Guardians, verball puffes,</l>
                  <l>Bigge lookers in their high <hi>Caſtillian</hi> ruffes,</l>
                  <l>But meere<note place="margin">Vaine glorious Braggarts</note> 
                     <hi>Quixotes, Rodomantading</hi> braues,</l>
                  <l>Faire frontiſpic'd like to their Grandoes graues,</l>
                  <l>But full of emptineſſe, and thoſe defects,</l>
                  <l>VVhich valour in ſelfe-bragging ſtill detects.</l>
                  <l>So that the ſpoyle is facill, if that wee</l>
                  <l>Can beat this<note place="margin">Hotch potch is any thing that is mingled; a <hi>Dutch-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> word.</note> Hotch-potch of mortalitle;</l>
                  <l>Theſe <hi>Spaniards, Portugals, Saluages, Moores,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVho keepe not, but are kept within the Towers</l>
                  <l>Of Saint <hi>Saluador:</hi> Nor is priuate gaine,</l>
                  <l>Nor priuate fame the ſole proiected ayme</l>
                  <l>Of this dayes ſeruice, but the publike good,</l>
                  <l>VVhich bleeding<note place="margin">Since the loſſe of <hi>Iuliers.</hi>
                     </note> ſince our <hi>Iuliacke</hi> loſſes ſtood,</l>
                  <l>Muſt be the ſcope of eu'rie Souldiers bent,</l>
                  <l>To which if wee giue iuſt accompliſhment;</l>
                  <l>Then th' <hi>Andian</hi> Mountaines which diuide the skies,</l>
                  <l>Shall ope their vaines to our new Colonies;</l>
                  <l>Then thoſe <hi>Braſilian</hi> woods,<note place="margin">The <hi>Andes</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide <hi>Peru</hi> and <hi>Braſill</hi> to the Weſtward. Theſe Trees are ſo big, that whol families dwell in them. A great Lake in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</note> whoſe maſsie Trees</l>
                  <l>Saluages hiue, like ſwarmes of <hi>Ruſſian</hi> Bees,</l>
                  <l>With all thoſe verdant Plaines, which <hi>Oregliana,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich <hi>Reall</hi> watereth, and curl'd<note place="margin">The <hi>Andes</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide <hi>Peru</hi> and <hi>Braſill</hi> to the Weſtward. Theſe Trees are ſo big, that whol families dwell in them. A great Lake in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</note> 
                     <hi>Eupana,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall bee the guerdons of our glorious toyle,</l>
                  <l>And honour'd Embleames of th'<hi>Iberians</hi> foyle.</l>
                  <l>This ſpeech being paſt, ſtout <hi>Willeks</hi> doth imbarke</l>
                  <l>VVithin the<note place="margin">Long-Boates.</note> Skiffes, which from their Galeouns warpe,</l>
                  <l>Two thouſand choſen men, whoſe ready ſprite</l>
                  <l>Straight vndertakes the danger of this fight.</l>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:9596:35"/>
                  <l>Then the lowd Cannon roares, the Souldiers ſcale,</l>
                  <l>The Mariners with Boat-hookes downe doe hale</l>
                  <l>The<note place="margin">Are pales ſet vp vpon the top or bottome of a Rampier. Parapet is a Worke made breſt high vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the top of a wall or Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</note> Paliſadoes: but the Fort well mann'd</l>
                  <l>At firſt to their defence did brauely ſtand,</l>
                  <l>And powr'd downe from the<note place="margin">Are pales ſet vp vpon the top or bottome of a Rampier. Parapet is a Worke made breſt high vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the top of a wall or Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</note> Parapetted walls</l>
                  <l>Pitch-burning hoopes, Granadoes, wild-fire balls,</l>
                  <l>Tarlin and Musket ſhot; but at the leng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h</l>
                  <l>Theſe Spaniſh Hoteſpurres looſe their former ſtrength,</l>
                  <l>Being ſtiffely charg'd, and to the towne recoyle,</l>
                  <l>Outwearied with this dang'rous combates toyle,</l>
                  <l>Leauing behind their euer honour'd Chiefe</l>
                  <l>Forlorne of all, deuoyd of all reliefe,</l>
                  <l>Who fights it out eu'n at the Rapiers poynt,</l>
                  <l>Vntill ſurcharg'd with odds, and vigour ſpent,</l>
                  <l>He ſheathed vp his Bilboe-tempred blade,</l>
                  <l>And to the Conqu'rours this ſubmiſsion made:</l>
                  <l>I yeeld my ſelfe, this Caſtle, and this Fort,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Saluadors</hi> Towne, and faire <hi>Los Sanctos</hi> Port,</l>
                  <l>To you my noble <hi>Dutch</hi> for all ſhall be</l>
                  <l>Now vaſſaliz'd to your new Seigneury:</l>
                  <l>Onely my Soule vncaptiued remaines</l>
                  <l>Free from th'aſperſion of thoſe baſer ſtaines,</l>
                  <l>Which brand theſe fugitiues, who had they been</l>
                  <l>But Souldiers true, but hardie valiant men;</l>
                  <l>Sooner ſhould<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rio grande,</hi> a Riuer which runs from the lake of <hi>Eupan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> into <hi>Marag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Rio grande</hi> haue chang'd his courſe,</l>
                  <l>And retrograde reuiſited his ſource;</l>
                  <l>Sooner ſhould th' <hi>Andian Alps</hi> haue waſht their head</l>
                  <l>In foamie <hi>Neptunes</hi> peeble-checkred bed,</l>
                  <l>Then any parcell of <hi>Braſiliaes</hi> land</l>
                  <l>Should once haue ſtoopt to <hi>Oranges</hi> command.</l>
                  <l>The Gouernour thus ſeaz'd, the Caſtle wonne,</l>
                  <l>The Fort ſurpriſ'd, and Saint <hi>Saluadors</hi> Towne</l>
                  <l>Being quitted by the foes; the <hi>Dutch</hi> Cohorts</l>
                  <l>Doe forthwith enter thoſe portculliz'd Ports,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe bending paſſage giues an open way</l>
                  <l>To this large Citie from <hi>Los Sanctos</hi> Bay.</l>
                  <l>Great was the ſpoyle, for Iewels, golde, and plate</l>
                  <l>Inricht the publicke, and the priuate ſtate</l>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:9596:36"/>
                  <l>VVith pillage ſtore; <hi>Potoſies</hi> golden barres,</l>
                  <l>The ſupporters of theſe <hi>Philippicke</hi> warres,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Peruvian</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Wedges of <hi>Peruuian</hi> gold</note> Ingots, redde <hi>Braſilian</hi> wood,</l>
                  <l>Rich Cochineale, and Sugar perfect good,</l>
                  <l>Became the guerdons of the <hi>Dutchmens</hi> paines,</l>
                  <l>And new additions to their ancient gaines.</l>
                  <l>The rumour of this loſſe no ſooner came,</l>
                  <l>Out trumpetted by truth-reporting Fame</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Court of <hi>Spaine,</hi> but reuenge wrought</l>
                  <l>Within their Councels breaſt, whoſe rancour ſought</l>
                  <l>To finde ſome proiect out, by which they might</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Los Sanctos</hi> loſſe, and Saint <hi>Saluadors</hi> quite.</l>
                  <l>Plots diffrent were propoſ'd; but at the laſt,</l>
                  <l>This ſuffraged in Common counſell paſt</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Spinola</hi> by conqu'red <hi>Bredaes</hi> gaine,</l>
                  <l>Muſt <hi>Spaines</hi> eclipſed Honour remaintaine.</l>
                  <l>For this deſigne the fierce<note place="margin">Spinola.</note> 
                     <hi>Ligurian</hi> takes</l>
                  <l>The field at <hi>Ballart,</hi> and from <hi>Ballart</hi> makes</l>
                  <l>Towards <hi>Hoochſtraten,</hi> and renownd <hi>Turnhout,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">At <hi>Turnhout</hi> the Spaniards were defeated eſpecially by the valour of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>For our mens valour, and th'<hi>Iberians</hi> rout:</l>
                  <l>Then paſsing by ſmall <hi>Gilſen, Baerle,</hi> and <hi>Cham,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>About mid-Auguſt all their Legions came</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Ginneken,</hi> and neere the <hi>Merkaes</hi> bankes</l>
                  <l>(Whoſe channell their intrenched Leaguer flankes)</l>
                  <l>They drew their Quarters out; th' <hi>Italian</hi> Bands,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Baglioni</hi> the <hi>Lumbard</hi> proud commands</l>
                  <l>Were lodg'd at <hi>Terheiden,</hi> their <hi>Almaines</hi> led</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> were all billetted</l>
                  <l>Within <hi>Terhague;</hi> the Marqueſſe with the men</l>
                  <l>Of his Diuiſions, lay at <hi>Ginneken,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Reſolued all to winne that glorious priſe,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Maurice</hi> got by <hi>Lamberts</hi> Turfe-deuice.</l>
                  <l>The Citizens on the defenſiue ſtand,</l>
                  <l>With new Supplies, and Reinforcements mann'd,</l>
                  <l>Which<note place="margin">Theſe were Colonels of the <hi>Engliſh, French,</hi> and <hi>Dutch.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Hauterine,</hi> which <hi>Gris,</hi> and <hi>Morgan</hi> ledd</l>
                  <l>From glaſsie <hi>Seines,</hi> and <hi>Tamſe's</hi> fruitfull bedd,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Lockeren</hi> brought from the Chriſtall <hi>Maſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From ſandie <hi>Rhines,</hi> and <hi>Iſſells</hi> watrie face,</l>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:9596:36"/>
                  <l>Commanded all by <hi>Juſtin</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who to the Towne, and Souldiers gaue the Law.</l>
                  <l>Beſides, the<note place="margin">The Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
                     </note> Prince reinforced with ſupplies,</l>
                  <l>Sent from his <hi>Engliſh</hi> friends, and faſt Alies,</l>
                  <l>Which braue <hi>Southampton</hi> led, which valiant <hi>Writhſly,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Eſſex, Oxford, Veare</hi> and <hi>Willoughby</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Commanded for the States, had paſt his Bands</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Holland</hi> through the rich <hi>Brabanſon</hi> lands,</l>
                  <l>To<note place="margin">Two villages in <hi>Brabant,</hi> where they firſt quarterd.</note> 
                     <hi>Meed</hi> and <hi>Stiueſand,</hi> where his care attends</l>
                  <l>To ſuccour his <hi>Breda</hi>-beleagred friends,</l>
                  <l>With all thoſe ſtratagems, which force or wit</l>
                  <l>Could yeeld, to farther, or to finiſh it.</l>
                  <l>The rumour of this ſiege, with th'expectation</l>
                  <l>Brought Voluntiers from eu'ry Chriſtian Nation</l>
                  <l>Vnto both Leaguers, in which honour'd liſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Poloniaes</hi> Prince claimes chiefeſt intereſt:<note place="margin">The Prince of <hi>Poland.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who comming from the cold <hi>Sarmatian</hi> plaines,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Rugeland,</hi> and high <hi>Almaine</hi> rich in vaines</l>
                  <l>Of ſundry Mineralls, arriu'd at laſt</l>
                  <l>(After the chance of many fortunes paſt)</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Auſtrian Iſabels</hi> renowned Court,</l>
                  <l>Where entertain'd with that Maieſticke port,</l>
                  <l>Which did befit his Greatneſſe he retires</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Campe from <hi>Bruxels</hi> ſtately Spires,</l>
                  <l>Deſiring more to ſee the Leaguers face,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Stations, and their Souldiers grace,</l>
                  <l>Then all that pompe, which <hi>Bruxels</hi> did affoord,</l>
                  <l>To entertaine this young <hi>Polonian</hi> Lord.</l>
                  <l>Vpon his firſt approach the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> foe</l>
                  <l>New poſtures of their ancient boaſting ſhow;</l>
                  <l>They bragge and braue it, that this braue <hi>Polaque,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Should take our ſtrongeſt works, and <hi>Breda</hi> ſacke,</l>
                  <l>Should lay the Rampiers leuell with the plaine,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Merks</hi> current with our Vermillion ſtaine.</l>
                  <l>But his deſignes were ſafer, for the Prince</l>
                  <l>Knew that Experience ſhould finde difference</l>
                  <l>Betwixt our Troupes, and thoſe <hi>Coſſackes</hi> which haunt</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Meotis</hi> Fennes, and <hi>Tartaries</hi> Leuant:</l>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:9596:37"/>
                  <l>He knew that here were no <hi>Tartarian</hi> Drouers,</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Prickers, nor <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alachian</hi> Rouers,</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Muskouitiſh,</hi> nor <hi>Hungarian</hi> Bands,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe fight on number, more then valour ſtands.</l>
                  <l>But heere were French and Engliſh nations bold</l>
                  <l>Within the Curtin of this Rampierd hold,</l>
                  <l>And theſe not led by<note place="margin">Theſe were <hi>Baſſaes</hi> ſlaine and defeated by the Prince of <hi>Poland.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Aliſ-beg,</hi> nor <hi>Nahan,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor by <hi>Cirkas;</hi> but by <hi>Lock'ren,</hi> and <hi>Morgan,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By <hi>Gris</hi> and <hi>Hauteriue</hi> men of that merit,</l>
                  <l>That death nor danger could not ſinke their Spirit.</l>
                  <l>Moreouer twas not the Caſtilians bent,</l>
                  <l>To take this place by forcible attempt,</l>
                  <l>By battering, <hi>Petarring,</hi> or <hi>Scalado,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By ſapping, mining, or by <hi>Camiſado,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They knew t'were labour loſt, t'were worke in vaine</l>
                  <l>To ſeeke by force this Fortreſſe ſtrong to gaine.</l>
                  <l>But famine was the plot, the <hi>Fabian</hi> courſe</l>
                  <l>By which they meant the Souldiers hearts to force,</l>
                  <l>And skrew to their conditions: for what ſtrength</l>
                  <l>So Adamantine is? but yeelds at length</l>
                  <l>Vnto the force of famine; there's no law</l>
                  <l>Can giue preſcription to a ſuffring mawe:</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſelfe muſt yeeld, and <hi>Pompey</hi> vaile,</l>
                  <l>If victuals with their hungry Colon faile.</l>
                  <l>T'accompliſh this great Caſtiles armie blockes</l>
                  <l>The friendly <hi>Mercke,</hi> and with their Cannon ſtoppes</l>
                  <l>The Land<note place="margin">Aduenue ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage</note> aduenues, fiue well fenced Forts</l>
                  <l>Do barre the mouth of our porcullizd ports</l>
                  <l>From all acceſſe: no Skoutes, no Spies could paſſe,</l>
                  <l>The Circling Rampiers large extended maſſe</l>
                  <l>But their obiected ſight muſt ſtraight wayes be</l>
                  <l>The pointeblancke ayme of Spaines Artillerie.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe mightie workes, which with your wandring eyes</l>
                  <l>On<note place="margin">The plaines in <hi>Wiltſhire</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Wiltſhires</hi> battell plaines you may deſcry;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe monuments left by the conqu'ring <hi>Danes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And the <hi>Saxons</hi> to eternize their names,</l>
                  <l>Were counterfeits, and workes of little fame</l>
                  <l>Compard with this <hi>Giganticke</hi> maſsie frame.</l>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:9596:37"/>
                  <l>To pierce them through, t'were to diuide the breaſt</l>
                  <l>Of Greekiſh <hi>Iſthmos,</hi> or to cut the creſt</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Athos</hi> and <hi>Olimpus;</hi> twere to draine</l>
                  <l>That ebbing flowing <hi>Mediterran</hi> maine,</l>
                  <l>Which runs betweene the ſweet<note place="margin">The Ile of <hi>Dorts.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Dordrecian</hi> Ile</l>
                  <l>And bleeding <hi>Brabants Rubie</hi> coul'red ſoile.</l>
                  <l>His Excellence knew this, and for this cauſe</l>
                  <l>Without all dallying demurres all delayes</l>
                  <l>He leaues his <hi>Meedan</hi> quarters, and doth fall</l>
                  <l>From thence vnto ſweete-ſeated <hi>Roſendale,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where he refortifies his winter ſtation,</l>
                  <l>Vſeth th' aſſurance of his former caution,</l>
                  <l>Seekes to cut off great <hi>Spinolaes</hi> Conuoyes,</l>
                  <l>And fill his Campe with <hi>Myriads</hi> of annoyes.</l>
                  <l>His brother <hi>Henericke</hi> at <hi>Longſtratten</hi> lay</l>
                  <l>Vpon the paſſage of the<note place="margin">Vpon the way of the <hi>Buſſe.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Boſhian</hi> way,</l>
                  <l>To cut of thoſe Supplies, which <hi>Brabant</hi> ſent,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Namurs, Heinault,</hi> and <hi>Burgundia</hi> lent,</l>
                  <l>Which the <hi>Limburgers</hi> brought in ratling Carres,</l>
                  <l>As contributours to theſe <hi>Belgian</hi> warres.</l>
                  <l>Both Armies lying thus, excurſions paſt</l>
                  <l>And frequent ſallies, where the various caſt</l>
                  <l>Of wauering Fortune gaue the glorious priſe</l>
                  <l>With doubtfull reuolution; in ſuch wiſe</l>
                  <l>That now the Dutchmen vanquiſh, now the foe</l>
                  <l>The Netherlandiſh Souldiers doth o'rethrow.</l>
                  <l>Amongſt the reſt courageous <hi>Breoutee</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Left heere this life t'acquire Eternitie;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe body <hi>Mountioyes</hi> daring reſcue gaue</l>
                  <l>The ſollemne rights of an obſequious graue.</l>
                  <l>Thus died the Captaine of th' <hi>Orangian</hi> guard,</l>
                  <l>Who ſallying forth the like diſaſter ſhar'd,</l>
                  <l>With diuerſe others, which in honours bed</l>
                  <l>Deceaſing liue, intomb'd, vnburied,</l>
                  <l>Worthy for worth euen to ſuruiue that death,</l>
                  <l>Which ſpoild them of their hor our breathing breath.</l>
                  <l>But where the ſworde one pettie ſquadron ſlew,</l>
                  <l>The Peſtilence to <hi>Plutoes</hi> manſion drew</l>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:9596:38"/>
                  <l>Thouſands of ſoules, whoſe numerous Cohorts</l>
                  <l>Crowded the paſſage of the Stigian ports.</l>
                  <l>So that no ſtragling ſoule could portage gaine,</l>
                  <l>From th'vpper world vnto th'Infernall maine.</l>
                  <l>But O thou ſcourge of Armies, why ſhouldſt thou</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Mars</hi> his ſteelie traine deſtruction vowe?</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould <hi>Bellonaes</hi> votaries indure</l>
                  <l>Thy bloodie fluxe, thy madding Callenture?</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould the ſwelling botch, the watrie blaine</l>
                  <l>That ſeate of valour with contagion ſtaine,</l>
                  <l>And tainte that purer conſecrated bloud</l>
                  <l>Which vow'd it ſelfe for <hi>Belgiaes</hi> publicke good.</l>
                  <l>Was't not inough to powre thy malice forth,</l>
                  <l>Vpon, the colder<note place="margin">All thoſe Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therene Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries were this laſt yeere much annoyed with the Plague.</note> 
                     <hi>Regions</hi> of the North?</l>
                  <l>To plague the warrelike Danes, the ſturdie Swecians,</l>
                  <l>The Rugians, Lappians, and the ſlow <hi>Norwegians?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Was't not inough for thy death miniond ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Golgothize</hi> the ſtreetes of ſtately Delfe,</l>
                  <l>And, make faire <hi>Leidens</hi> trembling ſtudents flie</l>
                  <l>From learnings once, now deaths Academie?</l>
                  <l>Was't not enough to lay weſt <hi>Frieſeland</hi> waſte</l>
                  <l>And waſte<note place="margin">Vtrocht.</note> 
                     <hi>Traiectum?</hi> but with winged haſt</l>
                  <l>Thou muſt inuade the Princes warrelike Campe,</l>
                  <l>And thouſands kill with that obnoxious dampe,</l>
                  <l>Which firſt infects the Subtle poared Aire,</l>
                  <l>And from thence doth our vitall ſtrength impaire,</l>
                  <l>By tainting thoſe vermillion flowing vaines,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe life-conducts with thy contagious ſtaines.</l>
                  <l>And could not heere plebeian bloud aſſwage</l>
                  <l>The boundles bounds of thy Luxuriant rage?</l>
                  <l>But muſt <hi>South-hamptons</hi> Earle, muſt <hi>Oxfords</hi> ſelfe</l>
                  <l>Dye by the darts of this accurſed Elſe?</l>
                  <l>Muſt<note place="margin">My Lord <hi>Wriotheſly</hi> eldeſt ſonne to th' Earle of <hi>Southampton.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Wriothſley, VVindham, Cheſter, Halſwell</hi> dye,</l>
                  <l>Slaine by the ſhafts of dire mortalitie?</l>
                  <l>But deade they are, whether that angrie nature</l>
                  <l>Enuied to earth their moore diuiner feature;</l>
                  <l>Or being malignant both to Armes, and Arts,</l>
                  <l>Skornd this Sublunar ſhould poſſeſſe thoſe parts,</l>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:9596:38"/>
                  <l>Thoſe ſeates of wonder, which with ſuch a meaſure</l>
                  <l>Were powred forth of great <hi>Pandoraes</hi> treaſure.</l>
                  <l>Yet theſe being gone,<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Iohn Rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliffe</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>pulſed <hi>Pompeio</hi> and <hi>Branch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> as they thought to paſſe ouer the <hi>Waal,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of <hi>Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoy.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Ratcliffe</hi> reputed dead,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Pompeyes</hi> repulſe Fame-eternized,</l>
                  <l>Liues, and ſuruiues, new Honours to attaine</l>
                  <l>From the defeated Colonels of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſince that they are dead, O that my Verſe</l>
                  <l>Could giue but life to their thrice-honour'd Herſe;</l>
                  <l>Then ſooner ſhould the Northerne Coachman ſteepe,</l>
                  <l>His falling Teeme within the <hi>Ruſsian</hi> deepe;</l>
                  <l>Sooner ſhould <hi>Thames</hi> forſake his Eaſterne courſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſliding backe runne Weſtward to his ſourſe,</l>
                  <l>Then that their Lawrell-conſecrated praiſe</l>
                  <l>Should want the Crowne of ſuch ſuruiuing Layes,</l>
                  <l>VVhich might giue life in death, and make that laſt</l>
                  <l>Beyond Times power, and cankred Enuies blaſt.</l>
                  <l>And as for thee, ſweet <hi>Breda,</hi> which doſt ſtand</l>
                  <l>Vpon the <hi>Merkaes</hi> peeble bordred ſtrand,</l>
                  <l>Since thou beleagred art with ſundry Legions,</l>
                  <l>Which came from thoſe<note place="margin">From <hi>Spaine.</hi>
                     </note> ſun-ſcorched weſtern Regions;</l>
                  <l>So that no ſtore of victualls, no ſupply</l>
                  <l>Can bring reliefe to thy neceſsitie.</l>
                  <l>And if the <hi>Spaniard</hi> ſtill ſo ſtrongly lies,</l>
                  <l>That neither <hi>Naſſaws</hi> force, nor ſlie deuice</l>
                  <l>Can raiſe the ſiege; if thoſe new leuied Bands,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Brunſwicks</hi> Duke, and <hi>Cromwels</hi> ſelfe commands,</l>
                  <l>VVhich vnder <hi>Maunsfields</hi> conduct, <hi>Rich</hi> and <hi>Lincolne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Burroughs</hi> leads, which <hi>Doncaſter</hi> and <hi>Hopton</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cannot inforce th'<hi>Jberian</hi> Troupes to riſe,</l>
                  <l>Nor gaine their way by <hi>Spinolaes</hi> ſurpriſe.</l>
                  <l>Then could I wiſh, that all that large extent,</l>
                  <l>VVhich lies within the Rauelins Continent,</l>
                  <l>VVere full of <hi>Indian</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A ſtrange kind of f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uit which growes in <hi>Peru.</hi>
                     </note> Cocoes, which doe grow</l>
                  <l>Vpon thoſe Plaines where <hi>Perues</hi> ſtreames doe flow,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſtrong oppletiue power doth ſtrangely fill,</l>
                  <l>And ſwallowed doth both thirſt and hunger kill.</l>
                  <l>Then could I wiſh, that ſome Spring-forced tide</l>
                  <l>Would make <hi>Merks</hi> current retrograde to glide,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9596:39"/>
                  <l>And when the forced riuer thus doth flow</l>
                  <l>Whole Cockly mountaines it might vpwards throw</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">When <hi>Rochell</hi> was beſiegd, great ſtore of ſhell fiſh were miraculouſly caſt vp vpon the ſhoare for the releefe of the Citizens.</note>Vpon the ſtrand; as when <hi>Aniou,</hi> and <hi>Guiſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thought <hi>Neptune</hi> flanked <hi>Rochell</hi> to Surpriſe:</l>
                  <l>It once befell vpon that ſandy ſhoare,</l>
                  <l>Where th' Ocean doth againſt <hi>Coreilles</hi> roare.</l>
                  <l>And then perhaps might <hi>Bredaes</hi> ſiege be ſuch</l>
                  <l>As was <hi>Oſtends</hi> or <hi>Bergens;</hi> and as much</l>
                  <l>The dammagd foe might then, and there ſuſtaine,</l>
                  <l>As they did in thoſe former ſieges gaine,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Veare</hi> and <hi>Morgan</hi> brauely did repell</l>
                  <l>That Spaniſh ſtorme, which on their Legions fell.</l>
                  <l>But whilſt my muſe thus Prayes, Fame from thoſe cels</l>
                  <l>Where audience, rumour, and relation dwells,</l>
                  <l>Brings vs ſad tidings, that ſtrong-flankt <hi>Breda</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Reconquerd is by warrelike <hi>Spinola;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who after eight moneths ſiege regaind that place,</l>
                  <l>Which ſo much did his Gray haird actions grace.</l>
                  <l>For although <hi>Maurice</hi> by ſurpriſing Cleeue,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Antwerpes</hi> cold attempt ſought to releeue</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beleaguerd Breda;</hi> though that <hi>Morgan</hi> braue</l>
                  <l>Reſolu'd to make th' ingaged place his Graue,</l>
                  <l>And ſtood on the defenſiue with that troupe</l>
                  <l>Which ſwoard nor famine could not make to ſtoope.</l>
                  <l>Although without ſtout <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eare,</hi> and <hi>Oxfords</hi> Count</l>
                  <l>Moſt daringly the Spaniſh workes did mount,</l>
                  <l>And wone two <hi>Rodoubts,</hi> whereas <hi>Payton, Winne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tubbe, Dacres, Hawley, Stanhop</hi> got within</l>
                  <l>The Parapetted Rampier, brauely fought</l>
                  <l>And death amongſt whole armed ſquadrons ſought.</l>
                  <l>Yet famine ſtill increaſing, whoſe affrounte</l>
                  <l>No courage though death-daring) can ſurmount,</l>
                  <l>And eight dayes foode being onely left to feede</l>
                  <l>The greedie Souldiers and the Burgers neede;</l>
                  <l>The Spaniards grant a parle, our men agree</l>
                  <l>Inforc'd thereto by meere neceſsitie:</l>
                  <l>Conditions to depart were ſuch, as we</l>
                  <l>Could hardly looke for from an Enemie:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9596:39"/>
                  <l>With <hi>Seroan</hi> colours flying, matches light,</l>
                  <l>Bullets in mouth, our waggons Loaden weight</l>
                  <l>With bagge and baggage, and a ſafe conuoy</l>
                  <l>To ſafeguard our's from all hoſtile annoy.</l>
                  <l>Beſides when as our Cohorts all diſmarcht</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Breda'es</hi> ports, and through their quarters paſt</l>
                  <l>The curteous <hi>Genoueſe</hi> ſaluteth all,</l>
                  <l>But ſpecially for <hi>Morgans</hi> ſelfe doth call,</l>
                  <l>Imbraceth him, and honouring a foe</l>
                  <l>So worthy doth himſelfe thrice worthie ſhow.</l>
                  <l>But though <hi>Breda</hi> be loſt, reconquerd <hi>Goffe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By <hi>Lambarts</hi> valour hath the chaines ſhooke off</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Caſtiles</hi> thraldome, and the taken towne</l>
                  <l>Mannd with a ſtrong <hi>Orangian</hi> Garriſon,</l>
                  <l>Makes all South <hi>Cleeue-lands Ceres</hi>-bleſſed ſhoare,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Rhine</hi> againſt ſtrong <hi>Grauenweert</hi> doth roare,</l>
                  <l>Pay contribution eu'n to that ſame land,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Iuliers</hi> on the Roars bankes doth ſtand.</l>
                  <l>This was that <hi>Lambart</hi> who with <hi>Heraugiere,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From <hi>Holland</hi> did that famous Turfe-boat ſteere,</l>
                  <l>When they fiue thouſand, ours but ſeu'ntie were,</l>
                  <l>Who this vnheard of enterpriſe did dare.</l>
                  <l>He waiting on the foes with <hi>Argian</hi> eyes,</l>
                  <l>Diſcouers by his ſubtle curious ſpies</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Goffes</hi> attempt was facill, for the moate</l>
                  <l>Was paſſable without the corked floate,</l>
                  <l>Without the <hi>Skiffe</hi> or <hi>Punt</hi> neere to that place,</l>
                  <l>VVhich did the VVeſterne bulwarkes platforme face.</l>
                  <l>For this deſigne he drawes two thouſand men,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Arnham, Embricke, Rees,</hi> and <hi>Nimeghen,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVho coue'red with a ſilent Mooneſhine night,</l>
                  <l>Arriud two houres before the dawning light</l>
                  <l>At their knowne Randeuouz, and from thence marcht</l>
                  <l>To the Townedike, which being ſafely paſt,</l>
                  <l>They ſcaled all at once the Rampierd wall,</l>
                  <l>And from thence on the Spaniſh guards did fall.</l>
                  <l>The fight was bloudie, for the vanquiſht foe</l>
                  <l>Fiue hundred of their <hi>Phalangiers</hi> could ſhow,</l>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:9596:40"/>
                  <l>Slaine on the place, but of the <hi>Dutehmens</hi> ſide</l>
                  <l>Scarce two full ſquadrons in this combate dyed.</l>
                  <l>But that which did the victours triumph croſſe,</l>
                  <l>VVas val<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ant <hi>Lambarts</hi> ſtill deplored loſſe,</l>
                  <l>VVho ouerheated in this toileſome fight</l>
                  <l>Reſign'd within eight dayes his honour'd ſprite</l>
                  <l>To mightie <hi>Ioue:</hi> his <hi>Manes</hi> great <hi>Naſſaw</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then whom this Ageno colder <hi>Fabius</hi> ſaw,</l>
                  <l>Purſued vnto thoſe bleſt <hi>Eliſian</hi> ſhades,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe euerliuing pleaſure neuer <hi>Fades,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhere all true <hi>Patriots,</hi> which for freedome fight</l>
                  <l>Receiue the Crowne of their deſerued right,</l>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:9596:40"/>
            <head>To my induſtrious friend Maſter <hi>W. C.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>VVHat ſullen Proſe in harſhnes did rehearſe,</l>
            <l>Smiles through thy ſoule with a diffuſiue light</l>
            <l>Like the <hi>Promethean</hi> fire: for by thy verſe</l>
            <l>Are wakened from the <hi>Chaos</hi> of blacke night</l>
            <l>The worthies of our time, that by thy pen</l>
            <l>Riſe from obliuions graue to life agen.</l>
            <l>And for their ſakes <hi>Mars</hi> with a ſteely Traine</l>
            <l>Of his vndaunted Sons preſents thy brow,</l>
            <l>The guerdon of thy ſweet Poeticke vaine</l>
            <l>A Lawrell of <hi>Mineruaes</hi> choiceſt bow:</l>
            <l>Proceede in thy deſignes, and let thy praiſe</l>
            <l>Out liue the crooked carping age of dayes.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohn Dowle Briſtol.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
